<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<movie>
<电影名>杀手没有假期 In Bruges</电影名>
<年份>2008</年份>
<评分>8.1</评分>
<封面>https://img2.doubanio.com/view/photo/s_ratio_poster/public/p2173386253.jpg</封面>
<导演>马丁·麦克唐纳</导演>
<演员>科林·法瑞尔 / 布莱丹·格里森 / 克蕾曼丝·波西 / 拉尔夫·费因斯 / 吕迪·布洛姆 / 伊丽莎白·贝林顿 / 奥利弗·邦泽 / 马克·多诺万 / 安·艾斯利 / 让-马克·法沃兰 / 艾力克·高敦 / 泽利科·伊万内克 / Sachi Kimura / 安娜·梅德利 / 路易斯·纳米</演员>
<简介>一对儿杀手，肯与雷（Colin Farrell 饰），在圣诞期间来到比利时古城布鲁日，他们将在这里接到联系人哈里（Ralph Fiennes 饰）指令的新任务。雷在不久前的一次暗杀中误杀了一名男童，怀着深深愧疚的雷情绪不稳，古城中的等待对他来说是一场难耐的煎熬。肯作为带领雷入行的前辈，试图帮助雷摆脱困境，但他的努力毫无收效。百无聊赖的雷在街上结识了女演员克洛伊，这个神秘女孩引发了雷一系列的冒险经历，与此同时，肯再一次被哈里催促，原来此次任务的真相是暴怒的哈里要雷为他的误杀行为付出代价，肯面对被自己一手引入杀手行当的年轻人，难以做出抉择，两名杀手，在夜色中的古城各怀心事……
                                    
                                　　本片获2009年英国学院奖最佳剧本奖等多项褒奖。</简介>
<reviews>
<review>
<作者>森林的火焰</作者>
<标题>冰炭置我肠</标题><作者评分>4</作者评分>
<时间>2008-06-06 09:43:13</时间>
<影评>
        出戏看过很久了，一直向人推荐说好说好。除了几个英国来的人心领神会以外，别处好象都沉了大海。于是我决定很没眼色地，痛说一说怎么个好法儿。顺手推广一下我顶喜欢的英国电影。


象所有其它的英国电影一样，打虎亲兄弟，上阵父子兵，电影里露的甭管大脸小脸，总是那些英国的脸。半部哈里波特都出现了：主角之一的老杀手是疯眼汉 Brendan Gleeson，黑帮老板是伏地魔Ralph Fiennes，年轻杀手闯下大祸的project，被杀的神父是斯内普Alan Rickman。


全世界的人都有偏见，或者说，叫stereotypes。英国人也不例外。可是英国人的stereotype编派得特别生动。白象一样庞大的美国一家三口，极度环保的加拿大人，比利时旅游景点的售票员不可理喻的无礼，阿姆斯特丹出名的满街都是妓女。老人热爱中世纪艺术，年轻人只对美女感兴趣。这些陈腐旧套如果放到好莱坞，也不过是多发一遍霉而已；在英国人手里就全都不同了。英国人不讲扼杀创意的极度政治正确。一点都不奇怪：从维多利亚时代风气幸存下来的文化，还有什么伪善没见过，不敢嘲笑的？


喜剧片看得多，黑色幽默也看得多，但是象In Bruges这样，一秒钟让人哭一秒钟让人笑的喜剧片还真的不多见。到电影渐渐进入紧张的时候，肝肠胃肺都拧到了一起。老杀手死去的一刻我真的马上要哭出来，一分钟以后黑帮老板诅咒一声掏出地图，我又要笑喷了。如是几次三番，从开头笑到最后。可是灯光明亮走出电影院，如果刚好有记者问我：你认为这是喜剧片吗？我可能答不出，揉揉红肿的眼睛。


很多美国电影为了抓人眼球，总是弄一个耸人听闻的开头，外星人都思不来的故事结构，再在电影的后半部分匆匆把所有情节和人物从四面八方收拢来，生硬地用钢丝拧在一起，让人在电影结束时生出咒骂“How dare you..."的冲动。In Bruges完全不是。每个人都个性鲜明，从开头到场结尾丝毫未变。混黑社会的几个男人，开旅馆的正怀着孕的老板娘，打心眼里讨厌外国人外地人的售票员，阴柔有钱的比利时枪贩子和他不争气混街头的蠢儿子。然而写电影的人把他们象七巧板一样拼成一出纵横来去的电影，处处用榫头严密地衔接起来。比起来，好莱坞电影根本是没揉开的，夹着生面疙瘩的面团。


我尤其喜欢的是剧中人的人格魅力。人格魅力不一定非是高大全人物才有，刘慧芳那就不能算人格魅力，那是“神格”，用现代网络语言来讲，恐怕要叫“雷格”。人格魅力就是，某个人身上那一点让人心生感动或欣赏的东西，就是人有时候不会放弃的一点坚持、固执或者宽容。现在流行的是分斤拨两世界观，理直气壮声称自己平生至爱是真金白银，把一切都折算成现金现美金（最近风头不好，可能要换现欧元），是相当时髦的人格。并不是我清高，而是人们普遍高估了经济砝码在自己和他人心目中的重量，尤其是在大部分人的生活早已免于冻饿之苦的年代。中国古话说“有钱能使鬼推磨”，其实现实中钱甚至不能使活人不怄气。年轻杀手误伤男孩以后的懊悔，老杀手对年轻杀手的爱护，冷血且有情绪控制问题的黑帮老板的坚持原则，怀孕的女旅馆老板的勇敢，都让人觉得他们活生生的能随时走近来。年轻杀手第一晚去和漂亮女孩约会，一粒扣子解开又系上，系上又解开，如是三番。老杀手看在肚里，又好笑又体谅。黑帮老板和老杀手决斗前在街头酒馆对酌，背后笑话卖枪的比利时人是在家里练瑜珈的。那轻松的朋友一刻稍纵即逝，然而没了它就完全不能解释后面的情节发展。


当然所有的英国电影里我百看不厌的是那些人都穿得那么齐整。他们的西服和大衣完美合身，不象美国人的裤子总垮着，肩膀总耸着，领子总张着。电影结束以后，我念念不忘的是旅店女老板美丽的奶油白色大衣和桃红围巾，想着自己什么时候也一定要买一件。
      </影评>
<有用数>1996</有用数>
<没用数>169</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>Back off, bitch</作者>
<标题>我把&lt;in bruges&gt;的台词抄了一遍。。【转】</标题><作者评分>4</作者评分>
<时间>2009-01-02 18:51:51</时间>
<影评>
         
http://www.douban.com/people/1972084/


原作者三天时间出的台词，牛逼闪闪的人物。




2009-01-02 18:41:25


In Bruges


Ray:After I killed them, I dropped the gun in the Thames,washed the residue off me hands in the bathroom of a Burger King,and walked home to await instructions.Shortly thereafter, the instructions came through."Get the fuck out of London, youse dumb fucks.Get to Bruges."I didn't even know where Bruges fucking was.

It's in Belgium.


Ray:Bruges is a shithole.        

Ken:Bruges is not a shithole.

Ray:Bruges is a shithole.

Ken:Ray, we've only just got off the fucking train.Could we reserve judgment on Bruges until we've seen the fucking place?

Ray:I know it's gonna be a shithole.


STREET

Ray:Shithole.


HOTEL

Ken:I think you have a couple of rooms booked under Cranham and Blakely?

Marie:Yes. No, we have one room booked.One twin room. Booked for two weeks.

Ray:Two weeks!

Ken:Do you have another room?

Marie:No, I'm afraid we're fully booked.With Christmas, everywhere is fully booked.

Ken:Okay.


ROOM

Ken:It's very pretty.

Ray:I'm not being funny, we can't stay here.

Ken:We've got to stay here until he rings.

Ray:Well, what if he doesn't ring for two weeks?

Ken:Then we stay here for two weeks.

Ray:For two weeks? In fucking Bruges? In a room like this?With you? No way!

Ken:Ray, I really don't like to say this...

Ray:You really don't like to say what?

Ken:Well... You know?

Ray:Fucking bring that up.


ON BOAT

Ray:Do you think this is good?

Ken:Do I think what's good?

Ray:You know, going round in a boat, looking at stuff.

Ken:Yes, I do.It's called "sightseeing."

Ken:Oh, look at that.It's a former hospital. From the 1100s.Bruges is the most well-preserved medieval townin the whole of Belgium, apparently.


SQUARE

Ken:Coming up? 

Ray:What's up there?

Ken:The view.

Ray:The view of what? The view of down here?I can see that from down here.

Ken:Ray, you're about the worst tourist in the whole world.

Ray:Ken, I grew up in Dublin. I love Dublin.If I'd grown up on a farm and was retarded,Bruges might impress me.But I didn't, so it doesn't.


TOWER

Ken:Trying to get rid of me coins.3, 3.50, 4,4.10, 4.20, 4.30, 4.40, 4.50, 4.60,4.70,4.80,4.90.Will you take 4.90?

Clerk:Entry is 5 euro.

Ken:Come on, man, it's only 10 cents.

Clerk:Entry is 5 euro.

Ken:Happy in your work?

Clerk:Very happy.


ON THE TOWER

I like it here.


SQUARE

Americans:Been to the top of the tower?

Ray:Yeah. Yeah, it's rubbish.

Americans:It is? The guidebook says it's a "must-see".

Ray:Well, you lot ain't going up there.

Americans:Pardon me? Why?

Ray:I mean, it's all windy stairs. I'm not being funny.

Americans:What exactly are you trying to say?

Ray:What exactly am I trying to say?Youse are a bunch of fucking elephants!

Americans:Right, you...

Americans Woman:You know, you're just the rudest man. The rudest man!

Ken:What's all that about?

Ray:They're not going up there.

Ken:Hey, guys, I wouldn't go up there. It's really narrow.

Americans Woman:Screw you, motherfucker!

Ray:Americans, isn't it?


PUB

Ray:Now, this is more like it. Proper holidays.One gay beer for my gay friend,and one normal beer for me, because I am normal.This is the life.

Ken:We're not staying here getting pissed.We are quietly sightseeing, like he says,and awaiting his call to see what we do next.

Ray:This is my vote on what we should do.We give it another day, two days, max.Then we check the papers again, and if there's still nothing in them,we phone him and say,"Harry, thank you for the trip to Bruges,"it's been very nice, all the old buildings and that,"but we're coming back to London now,and hide out in a proper country,"where it isn't all just fucking chocolates."

Ken:My vote would be we quietly sightsee, like he says,and await his call to see what we do next.You don't even know we're here hiding out.

Ray:What are you talking about?

Ken:You don't even know we're not here on a job.

Ray:What, on a job?        

Ken:Yeah.

Ray:Here in Bruges?        

Ken:Yeah.

Ray:Here in Bruges, on a job?        

Ken:Yeah.

Ray:Why? What did he actually say?

Ken:He didn't actually say anything.

Ray:Then why do you think it might be?

Ken:I don't think anything.But it's a bit fucking over-elaborate, isn't it?"Go take him to hide out." "Go take him to hide out where?""Go take him to hide out in fucking Bruges."You can hide out in Croydon.

Ray:Hmm.Or Coventry.Hmm.It is a bit over-elaborate.Hmm.But we haven't got any guns.

Ken:Harry can get guns anywhere.


ROOM

Ray:He's not gonna ring tonight.He's not gonna ring tonight.Let's go out.

Ken:Go out where?        

Ray:The pub.

Ken:No!

Ray:Let's go out and have a look at some of the...All the old medieval buildings and that.Because I bet they look even better at night, all lit up.Yes!


STREET

Ken:That there is called the Gruuthuse Museum.

Ray:They all have funny names, don't they?

Ken:Yes, Flemish.

Ray:In here it says, "The Belgians twice sheltered"fugitive English Kings from being murdered,1471 and 1651."

Ken:I used to hate history, didn't you?It's all just a load of stuff that's already happened.What are they doing over there?They're filming something. They're filming midgets!

Ken:Ray!

Director:So, on this scene, you're supposed to walklike a little, tiny mouse, yeah?Okay? Great.

Ken:Ray, come on, let's go.

Ray:My arse, "Let's go." They're filming midgets.Oh, my God! Look at that girl.She's gorgeous!

Ken:Ray, we're going right now.

Ray:Fuck off, are we!This is the best bit of Bruges so far.You and your buildings.

Ray:Hello.Do you speak English?        

Chloe:No.

Ray:Yes, you do. Everybody does.What are you filming midgets for?

Chloe:It's a Dutch movie. It's a dream sequence.It's a pastiche of Nicholas Roeg's Don't Look Now.Not a pastiche, but a...A "homage" is too strong. A "nod of the head"?

Ray:Wow, your English is very good.

Ray:A lot of midgets tend to kill themselves.A disproportionate amount.Herve Villechaize, of Fantasy Island.I think somebody off The Time Bandits.I suppose they must get really sad about, like,being really little and that.People looking at them and laughing at them.Calling them names. You know, "shortarse."There's another famous midgetI'm missing, but I can't remember.It's not the R2-D2 man. No, he's still going.I hope your midget doesn't kill himself.Your dream sequence will be fucked.

Chloe:He doesn't like being called a midget.He prefers "dwarf."

Ray:Well, this is exactly my point!People go around calling you a midget when you want to be called a dwarf.Of course you're gonna blow your head off!My name's Ray. What's yours?        

Chloe:Chloe.How did you get past the security man?

Ray:Getting past security men, it's sort of my job.

Chloe:You're a shoplifter?

Ray:No, not a shoplifter.It's a good joke, though.No.I'll tell you what I am at dinner tomorrow night.

Ray:Fuck.

Ray:How fucking cool.


HOTLE

Marie:Mr. Blakely?

Ken:Yes. No, Mr. Cranham. No. Yes. Mr. Blakely. Yes.

Marie:You have a message.

Ken:Shit!

(Harry):Number one,why aren't you in when I fucking told you to be in?Number two,why doesn't this hotel have phones with fucking voicemailand not I have to leave messages with the fucking receptionist?Number three, you better fucking be in tomorrow nightwhen I fucking call againor there'll be fucking Hell to pay,I'm fucking telling you. Harry.

(Marie):I'm not the receptionist,I'm the co-owner with my husband Patrice. Marie.


ROOM

Ken:Would you turn the fucking light off!

Ray:Sorry, Ken.

Ken:Keep the fucking noise down!

Ray:Someone's in a mood.You'll never guess what.

Ken:Will you shut your fucking mouth, please, and go to sleep?

Ray:Oh, sorry.Except I've gotta take me contact lenses out.

Ray:Altogether,I had five pints of beer and six bottles.No. Six pints of beer and seven bottles.And you know what? I'm not even pissed!You'll never guess what, Ken.Ken, you'll never guess what.        

Ken:What?

Ray:Got a date for tomorrow night.

Ken:I'm very happy for you.

Ray:With a girl.

Ken:Can you turn the light off, please?

Ray:Only been in Bruges one day,got a date with a girl in the film business,the Belgian film business.They're doing a film about a midget.


HOTEL

Ken:Miss?Marie?Sorry about the message last night.The man who left it is a bit of a...Well, he's a bit of a...

Marie:Cock?

Ken:Yes. He's a bit of a cock.

Marie:Morning.

Ken:Harry called last night.We missed him.

Ray:Jeez, he swears a lot, doesn't he?

Ken:We're staying in tonight. Whatever happens.

Ray:Hmm.Except...Hmm.        

Ken:Hmm.Except "hmm" what?

Ray:Except only one of us needs to stay in,really.Uh-huh.

Ken:And which one of us would that be, now, Ray?I thought you didn't like Bruges.

Ray:I don't like Bruges, it's a shithole.But I did already say I had a date with a Belgian lady in the Belgian film business, which I did already say about before.

Ken:Just don't get into any fucking trouble.We're keeping a low profile.And this morning, and this afternoon,we are doing what I want to do.Got it?        

Ray:Of course.Which, I presume, will involve culture.

Ken:Oh, we shall strike a balance between culture and fun.

Ray:Somehow I believe, Ken,that the balance shall tip in the favor of culture.Like a big, fat, fucking retarded, fucking black girl on a seesaw, opposite a dwarf.


CHURCH

Ken:Ray, did we or did we not agree that if I let you go on your date tonight,we'd do the things I wanted to do today?

Ray:We are doing the things that you wanted to do today.

Ken:And that we'd do them without you throwing a fucking moody,like some 5-year-old who's dropped all his sweets?

Ray:I didn't agree to that.I'll cheer up. I'll cheer up.

Ken:Up there, the top altar, is a phial brought back by a Flemish knight from the Crusades in the Holy Land.And that phial, do you know what it's said to contain?

Ray:No, what's it said to contain?

Ken:It's said to contain some drops of Jesus Christ's blood.Yeah, that's how this church got its name.Basilica of the Holy Blood.

Ray:Yeah. 

Ken:Yeah.And this blood, right, though it's dried blood,at different times over many years,they say it turned back into liquid.Turned back into liquid from dried blood.At various times of great stress.

Ray:Yeah?        

Ken:Yeah.So, yeah, I'm gonna go up in the queue and touch it,which is what you do.

Ray:Yeah?        

Ken:Yeah. You coming?

Ray:Do I have to?

Ken:Do you have to? Of course you don't have to.It's Jesus' fucking blood, isn't it?Of course you don't fucking have to!Of course you don't fucking have to!


SQUARE

Ray:You little fucking cunt.


CHURCH

Ray:Murder, Father.

Churchman:Why did you murder someone, Raymond?

Ray:For money, Father.

Churchman:For money?You murdered someone for money?

Ray:Yes, Father.Not out of anger, not out of nothing. For money.

Churchman:Who did you murder for money, Raymond?

Ray:You, Father.

Churchman:I'm sorry?

Ray:I said you, Father.What, are you deaf?Harry Waters says hello.

Churchman:The little boy.


ON THE PAPER..

1.Being moody.

2.Being bad at maths.

3.Being Sad.


MUSEUM

Ray:I quite like this one.All the rest were rubbish by spastics,but this one's quite good.What's that all about, then?

Ken:It's Judgment Day, you know?        

Ray:Oh, yeah.What's that then?

Ken:Well, it's, you know, the final day on Earth.When mankind will be judged for all the crimes.they've committed and that.

Ray:And see who gets into Heaven and who gets into Hell and all that?

Ken:Yeah.

Ray:And what's the other place?

Ken:Purgatory.

Ray:Purgatory?

Ken:Purgatory's kind of like the in-betweeny one.

Ray:You weren't really shit, but you weren't all that great, either.Like Tottenham.Do you believe in all that stuff, Ken?

Ken:About Tottenham?

Ray:The Last Judgment and the afterlife.Guilt and sins and Hell and all that?

Ken:Um...Well...


SQUARE

Ken:I don't know, Ray. I don't know what I believe.The things you're taught as a child,they never really leave you, do they?So, like, I believe in trying to lead a good life.Like, if there's an old lady, carrying her shopping home,I don't try and help her carry her shopping, I don't go that far,but I'll certainly hold the door open for her and that,and let her go out before me.

Ray:Yeah. And anyway, if you tried to help her carry her shopping,she'd probably think you were just trying to nick her shopping.

Ken:Exactly.        

Ray:This is the world we live in today.

Ken:At the same time as trying to lead a good life,I have to reconcile myself with the fact that, yes, I have killed people.Not many people. Most of them were not very nice people.Apart from one person.

Ray:Who's that?

Ken:This fellow, Danny Aliband's brother.He was just trying to protect his brother. Like you or I would.He was just a lollipop man.He came at me with a bottle. What are you gonna do?I shot him down.

Ray:Hmm.In my book, though, sorry, someone comes at you with a bottle,that is a deadly weapon, he's gotta take the consequences.

Ken:I know that in my heart.I also know that he was just trying to protect his brother, you know?

Ray:I know. But a bottle, that can kill you.It's a case of it's you or him.If he'd come at you with his bare hands, that'd be different.That wouldn't have been fair.

Ken:Well, technically, your bare hands can kill somebody, too.They can be deadly weapons, too.I mean, what if he knew karate, say?

Ray:You said he was a lollipop man.

Ken:He was a lollipop man.

Ray:What's a lollipop man doing knowing fucking karate?

Ken:I'm just saying.

Ray:How old was he? 

Ken:About 50.

Ray:What's a 50-year-old lollipop man doing knowing fucking karate? What was he, a Chinese lollipop man? Jesus, Ken, I'm trying to talk about...

Ken:I know what you're trying to talk about.

Ray:I killed a little boy. You keep bringing up fucking lollipop men!

Ken:You didn't mean to kill a little boy.

Ray:I know I didn't mean to.But because of the choices I made and the course that I put into action,a little boy isn't here anymore.And he'll never be here again.I mean here in the world, not here in Belgium.Well, he'll never be here in Belgium, either, will he?I mean, he might have wanted to come here when he got older.I don't know why.And that's all because of me.He's dead because of me.And I'm trying to...I'm trying to get me head around it, but I can't.I will always have killed that little boy.That ain't ever going away. Ever.Unless...Maybe I go away.

Ken:Don't even think like that.


ROOM

Ken:You look good.

Ray:What's it matter anyway?


PUB

Chloe:So, what do you do, Raymond?

Ray:I shoot people for money.

Chloe:What kinds of people?

Ray:Priests. Children. You know, the usual.

Chloe:Is there a lot of money to be made in that line of business?

Ray:There is in priests. There isn't in children.So what is it you do, Chloe?

Chloe:I sell cocaine and heroin to Belgian film crews.

Ray:Do you?

Chloe:Do I look like I do?

Ray:You do, actually.Do I look like I shoot people?

Chloe:No.Just children.

Ray:Mmm-hmm.I saw your midget today.Little prick didn't even say hello.

Chloe:Well, he's on a lot of ketamine.

Ray:What's that?

Chloe:Horse tranquilizer.

Ray:A horse tranquilizer?Where'd he get that? 

Chloe:I sold it to him.

Ray:You can't sell horse tranquilizers to a midget!

Chloe:This movie, I think it's gonna be a very good one.There's never been a classic movie made in Bruges until now.

Ray:Of course there hasn't, it's a shithole.

Chloe:Bruges is my hometown, Ray.

Ray:Well, it's still a shithole.

Chloe:It's not a shithole.

Ray:What? Even midgets have to take drugs to stick it.

Chloe:Okay.So, you've insulted my hometown.You're doing very well, Raymond.Why don't you tell me some Belgian jokes while you're at it?

Ray:I don't know any Belgian jokes.And if I did, I think I'd have the good sense not to...Hey, hang on. Is Belgium where there were all those child abuse murders lately?Then I do know a Belgian joke.What's Belgium famous for?Chocolates and child abuse.And they only invented the chocolates to get to the kids.What?

Chloe:One of the girls they murdered was a friend of mine.

Ray:I'm sorry, Chloe.

Chloe:One of the girls they murdered wasn't a friend of mine.I just wanted to make you feel bad.And it worked. Quite well.

Canadians:Fucking unbelievable.

Ray:What's fucking unbelievable?

Canadians:Are you talking to me?

(He pauses, even though he should just hit the cunt.And he repeats.)

Ray:Yes, I am talking to you. What's fucking unbelievable?

Canadians:Well, I'll tell you what's fucking unbelievable, shall I?Blowing cigarette smoke straight into myself and my girlfriend's face.

That's fucking unbelievable!

Ray:This is the smoking section.

Canadians:I don't care if it's the smoking section.All right? She directed it right in my face, man.I don't wanna die just because of your fucking arrogance.

Ray:Uh-huh. Isn't that what the Vietnamese used to say?

Canadians:Vietnamese? What are you talking about, the Vietnamese?That statement makes no fucking sense at all.

Ray:Yes it does. The Vietnamese!

Canadians:Well, saying it over and over ain't gonna make any more sense out of it.How does the Vietnamese have any relevance whatsoever to myself and my girlfriend having to breathe your friend's cigarette smoke?Tell me how saying...

Ray:That's for John Lennon, you Yankee fucking cunt!

Ray:A bottle? No, don't bother.

Ray:We're leaving.


OUT OF PUB

Ray:I don't hit women! I would never hit a woman, Chloe!I'd hit a woman who was trying to hit me with a bottle!That's different. That's self-defense, isn't it?Or a woman who could do karate.I'd never hit a woman generally, Chloe. Don't think that.God, you're pretty.

Chloe:I have to make a call.

Ray:Oh, no.You've gone off me, now, haven't you?Just because I hit that fucking cow.


ROOM

Ken:Hello?        

Harry:Where the fuck were you yesterday?

Ken:We just popped out for some dinner, Harry.We only popped out for half an hour.

Harry:Yeah? What'd you have?

Ken:For dinner?        

Harry:Yeah.

Ken:Pizza, at Pizza Hut.

Harry:Was it nice?

Ken:Yeah, it was all right. I don't know. It was Pizza Hut.The same as in England.

Harry:Well, that's globalization, isn't it? Is Ray there with you?

Ken:He's in the toilet.

Harry:Can he hear?        

Ken:No.

Harry:What's he doing?

Ken:What do you mean?       

Harry:Is he doing a wee or a poo?

Ken:I don't know, Harry, the door's closed.

Harry:Send him out on an errand for half an hour,but don't make it sound suspicious.

Ken:Ray? Why don't you go out down to the pub for half an hour?Yeah, yeah, I know I said you couldn't,but might as well enjoy ourselves, eh?No, I don't know if they've got bowling anywhere.Could have a look.Yeah, see you.Yeah. He's gone.

Harry:What'd you say to him?

Ken:I said, "Why don't you go have a drink,you say you've been cooped up?"

Harry:What did he say?        

Ken:Said, yeah, he would.And he might go have a look to see if there's a bowling alley around.

Harry:Was he just having a wee?

Ken:Yeah, I think so. I assume so.

Harry:Sure he didn't mind?

Ken:No, he was glad to get out.

Harry:He's definitely gone?

Ken:Yeah, yeah, he slammed the door.

Harry:That don't mean he's gone. Go check outside the door.

Ken:Harry, he's definitely gone.

Harry:You realize there are no bowling alleys in Bruges?

Ken:I realize that, Harry. The boy wanted to have a look anyway.

Harry:What are they gonna have, a medieval fucking bowling alley?

Ken:As I say, I think he was just glad to get out and about.

Harry:So, is he having a nice time, seeing all the canals and that?I had a lovely time when I was there.All the canals and the old buildings and that.

Ken:When were you here?

Harry:When I was seven. Last happy holiday I fucking had.Have you been on a canal trip, yet?        Ken:Yeah.

Harry:Have you been down, like, all the old cobbled streets and that?

Ken:Yeah.

Harry:It's like a fairytale, isn't it, that place? Ken:Yeah.

Harry:With the churches and that. They're Gothic. Ken:Yeah.

Harry:Is it Gothic?        

Ken:Yeah.

Harry:So he's having a really nice time?

Ken:Well, I'm having a really nice time.I'm not sure if it's really his cup of tea.

Harry:What?

Ken:You know, I'm not sure if it's really his thing.

Harry:What do you mean, "It's not really his thing"?What's that supposed to mean, "It's not really his thing"?What the fuck is that supposed to mean?

Ken:Nothing, Harry.

Harry:It's a fairytale fucking town, isn't it?How can a fairytale town not be somebody's fucking thing?How can all those canals and bridges and cobbled streets and those churches,all that beautiful fucking fairytale stuff,how can that not be somebody's fucking thing, eh?

Ken:What I think I meant to say was...

Harry:Is the swan still there?        

Ken:Yeah, the swan's...

Harry:How can fucking swans not fucking be somebody's fucking thing, eh?How can that be?

Ken:What I think I meant to say was,when he first arrived, he wasn't quite sure about it.You know, there's that big,dual carriageway when you get off the train?It mightn't have been here when you were here last, Harry.Well, as soon as he got into, like, the old town proper,and he saw the canals and the bridges and,you know, the swans and that,well, he just fucking loved it then.Couldn't get enough of it, the medieval part of town.It was just that initial, dual carriageway thing sort of put him off for a second.

Harry:Don't know if I remember a dual carriageway.Must be recent.Hasn't spoilt it, has it?

Ken:No, no, no, it's just that initial thing.And you know what?As we were walking through the streets,there was this sort of freezing fog hanging over everything,and it made it look almost like a fairytale or something.And he turned to me, do you know what he said?

Harry:What'd he say?

Ken:He said, "Ken, I know I'm awake,but I feel like I'm in a dream."

Harry:Yeah? He said that?

Ken:Yeah.

Harry:Meaning, like, in a good dream?

Ken:Yeah. Of course, like in a good dream.

Harry:Oh, good. I'm glad he likes it there.I'm glad we were able to give him something.

Something good and happy. Because he wasn't a bad kid, was he?

Ken:Huh?

Harry:He wasn't a bad kid, was he?Listen, take down this address. Raamstraat 17.That's "Raam," like "Ram," but with an extra "a."

Ken:Raamstraat 17.

Harry:You got that?

Ken:Yes, Raamstraat 17.

Harry:Good. There'll be a man there tomorrow morning at 9:00.His name's Yuri.

Ken:Yuri.        

Harry:He'll give you the gun.Ring me on the public phone at Jimmy Driscoll's about 3:00 or 4:00 tomorrow, after it's done.

Ken:After what's done?

Harry:Are you being thick?

Ken:No.        

Harry:Listen, I like Ray.He was a good bloke, but when it all comes down to it.You know, he blew the head off a little fucking kid.And you brought him in, Ken.So if the buck don't stop with him, where does it stop?Ken?If the buck don't stop with him, where does it stop?

Ken:It stops with me, Harry. That's an easy one.

Harry:Look, don't get shirty, Ken.Listen, I'm just glad that I was able to do something for the boy before he went.

Ken:Do what for the boy?

Harry:You know, have him get to see Bruges.I'd like to go to see Bruges again before I die.What was it he said again about... Yeah, "It's like a dream."

Ken:"I know I'm awake, but I feel like I'm in a dream."

Harry:Yeah.Give me a call when he's dead.



Eirik:That's my fucking girlfriend, you asshole.

Chloe:Eirik, what are you doing?

Eirik:Where are you from, fucker?

Ray:Ireland, originally.

Eirik:And you think it's okay to come over to Belgium and fuck another man's girl?

Ray:Look, I didn't know she had a boyfriend, all right?And I haven't fucked her, anyway. Ask her.I'd only put me hand on it.

Chloe:Eirik, put the gun down!

Eirik:Get down on your knees and open your mouth.

Ray:Don't start being silly.

Eirik:Get down on your...

Ray:Exactly at what point was it that all skinheads suddenly became poofs?Used to be, you were a skinhead,you just went around beating up Pakistani 12-year-olds.Now it seems a prerequisite to be a fucking bum-boy!

Ray:That's not gonna help you, man.

Chloe:Ray, there's only blanks in that gun.Eirik, don't!

Eirik:Now who's the fucking bum-boy?

Ray:You, you fucking bum-boy!Chloe, what exactly is going on here?

Eirik:I can't see! I can't see!

Ray:Of course you can't fucking see!I just shot a blank in your fucking eyes!Is this fella your boyfriend?

Eirik:No. I mean, he used to be.

Ray:Well, what's he doing here?

Chloe:We... We rob tourists, sometimes.

Ray:I fucking knew it was too good to be true!I knew you'd have never shagged me, normally.

Chloe:No! That's not true, I...I called it off tonight. I told him not to come tonight.Why did you come tonight?

Eirik:Chloe, I can't see, I swear it!

Ray:Stop whingeing like a big gay baby.I haven't had a shag in months!

Eirik:I can't see out of this eye, Chloe! I have to go to the hospital!

Chloe:I'll drive you.

Ray:Great! Now the whole night's ruined!

Chloe:No!You can stay if you want.I just don't know how long I'll be.

Ray:I just knew someone like you would never like someone like me.I just knew. 

Chloe:What do you mean, someone like me?

Ray:You know, someone nice.

Chloe:Call me. Please.

Eirik:Chloe!

Ray:Cha-ching!


PUB

Ken:Have you got some sort of problem?

Bartender:No, no problem.Four beers in 20 minutes. No problem.

Ken:Fuck off.

Midget:Beer and a red wine.

Prostitute:I'll be back.

Ken:How's the movie going?

Midget:It's a jumped-up Eurotrash piece of rip-off fucking bullshit.

Ken:Like, in a bad way?Your girlfriend's very pretty.

Midget:She ain't my girlfriend.She's a prostitute I just picked up.

Ken:Didn't know there were any prostitutes in Bruges.

Midget:You just have to look in the right places.Brothels are good.

Ken:Well, you've picked up a very pretty prostitute.

Midget:Thank you.

Ken:You from the States?

Midget:Yeah.But don't hold it against me.

Ken:I'll try not to.Just try not to say anything too loud or crass.

Ray:Hey-ho. Drowning your sorrows, huh?

Ken:What sorrows? 

Ray:You know, being a sad, old, ugly little man.One gay beer, please.

Ken:How'd your date go?

Ray:My date involved two instances of extreme violence.One instance of her hand on my cock and my finger up her thing,which lasted all too briefly. Isn't that always the way?One instance of me stealing five grams of her very-high-quality cocaine,and one instance of me blinding a poofy little skinhead.So, all in all, my evening pretty much balanced out fine.

Ken:You got five grams of coke?

Ray:I've got four grams on me and one gram in me,which is why me heart is going like the clappers,as if I'm about to have a heart attack.So if I collapse any minute now, please remember to tell the doctors that it might have something to do with the coke.

Ken:Give us a gram, then.

Ray:I thought you were laying off, because it makes you depressed?

Ken:You know what? Right now, I don't really give a fuck.

Ray:Why didn't you wave hello to me today when I waved hello to you today?

Midget:I was on a very strong horse tranquilizer today.I wasn't waving hello to anybody, except maybe to a horse.

Ray:Huh? What are you talking about?

Midget:Just horseshit.

Ray:You from America?

Midget:Yeah. But don't hold it against me.

Ray:Well, that's for me to decide, isn't it?Are you from America, too?

Prostitute:No, I'm from Amsterdam.

Ray:Amsterdam.Amsterdam is just a load of bloody prostitutes, isn't it?

Prostitute:Yes. That's why I came to Bruges.I thought I'd get a better price for my pussy here.

Ray:Huh?You two are weird.Would you like some cocaine?I've also got some acid and some ecstasy.


FIVE-STAR HOTEL

Ray:Herve Villechaize, I know, did.The dwarf off, I think, The Time Bandits, did.Lots of midgets...Dwarves, top themselves.Hmm. Shitloads.Would you ever think about it?

Midget:Huh?

Ray:Would you ever think about killing yourself because you're a midget?

Midget:Fuck, man! What kind of question is that?

Ray:We're just chatting, aren't we?See, Ken.this is the kind of hotel Harry should have put us in.A five-star, with prostitutes in.You know, sometimes, I think Harry doesn't even give a shit about us at all.Has he still not called?

Ken:No. Still hasn't called.

Ray:No news is good news, eh?

Ray:Who's she?

Midget:There's gonna be a war, man.I can see it.There's gonna be a war between the blacks

and between the whites.You ain't even gonna need a uniform no more.This ain't gonna be a war where you pick your side.Your side's already picked for you.

Ray:And I know whose side I'm fighting on.I'm fighting with the blacks.The whites are gonna get their heads kicked in!

Midget:You don't decide this shit, man.

Ray:Well, who are the half-castes gonna fight with?

Midget:The blacks, man. That's obvious.

Ray:But what about the Pakistanis?

Midget:The blacks.        

Ray:What about...Think of a hard one.What about the Vietnamese?

Midget:The blacks!

Ray:Well, I'm definitely fighting with the blacks if they've got the Vietnamese.So, hang on.Would all of the white midgets in the world be fighting against all the black midgets in the world?

Midget:Yeah.

Ray:That would make a good film!

Midget:You don't know how much shit I've had to take off of black midgets, man.

Ray:That's...Undeniably true.

Ken:See, Jimmy,my wife was black.And I loved her very much.And in 1976, she was murdered by a white man. So...Where the fuck am I supposed to stand in all this blood and carnage?

Midget:Did they get the guy who did it?

Ken:A friend of mine got him.

Ray:Harry Waters got him.

Ken:So tell me, Jim,whose side do I fight on in this wonderful war?

Midget:I think you need to weigh up all your options and let your conscience decide, Ken.

Ken:Two manky hookers and a racist dwarf.I think I'm heading home.

Ray:Yeah. I think I'll come with you.

Midget:What's... 

Ray:Back off, shorty!

Midget:You don't know karate.

Ken:Don't say you didn't have it coming.

Ray:Don't say you didn't have it coming.Shortarse!


YURI'S HOME

Ken:Meeting Yuri.

Yuri:Yes, I'm Yuri.

Yuri:Mr. Waters said that might be necessary.There are a lot of alcoves in the Koningin Astrid Park.You use this word, "alcoves"?

Ken:"Alcoves"? Yes. Sometimes.

Yuri:There are not many people around in these alcoves in Christmastime.If I were to murder a man, I would murder him here.Are you sure this is the right word, "alcoves"?

Ken:"Alcoves," yes. It's kind of like "nooks and crannies."

Yuri:"Nooks and crannies," yes. Perhaps this would be more accurate."Nooks and crannies," rather than "alcoves." Yeah.

Yuri:You are going to do it, aren't you? Mr. Waters will be very disappointed...

Ken:Of course I'm going to fucking do it.It's what I do.


HOTLE

Marie:Your friend was behaving rather oddly this morning.

Ken:Oddly? How?

Marie:Well, he asked me about the baby,and if I wanted a boy or a girl.I said I didn't mind as long as it's healthy, of course.But then he gave me 200 euros to give to the baby.I refused, obviously, but he was quite insistent.Would you give it back to him when you see him?I don't want to appear ungrateful,but it seemed like all the money he had.

Ken:Do you know where he is now?

Marie:He said he was going to the park.


PARK

Ken:Sorry, Ray.

Ken:I'm sorry.

Ken:Ray, don't!

Ray:Fucking hell! Where the fuck did you come from?

Ken:I was behind the thing.What the fuck are you doing, Ray?

Ray:What the fuck are you doing?

Ken:Nothing.

Ray:Oh, my God!You were gonna kill me.        Ken:No, I wasn't.You were gonna kill yourself!  Ray:What?I'm allowed to.

Ken:No, you're not!

Ray:What?I'm not allowed to and you are? How's that fair?

Ken:Can we go somewhere and talk about this, please?


Ken:I wasn't gonna go through with it, Ray.

Ray:You fucking looked like you were gonna go fucking through with it.Where'd you get that gun?

Ken:A friend of Harry's.

Ray:Fuck, man.Let me see it.Silencer, too.Nice.Mine's a bloody girl's gun.

Ken:I'm keeping it.        

Ray:Pardon me?Give me me gun back.        Ken:You're not getting it back.You're a suicide case.

Ray:And you were trying to shoot me in the fucking head.

Ken:You're not getting that gun back.

Ray:A great day this has turned out to be.I'm suicidal, me mate tries to kill me,me gun gets nicked and we're still in fucking Bruges.

Ken:Listen, I'm gonna give you some money and put you on a train somewhere.

Ray:Back to England?

Ken:You can't go back to England, Ray. You'd be a dead man!

Ray:I want to be a dead man.Have you been missing something?

Ken:You don't want to be a dead man, Ray.

Ray:I killed a little boy!

Ken:Then save the next little boy.Just go away somewhere,get out of this business and try to do something good.You're not gonna help anybody dead.You're not gonna bring that boy back.But you might save the next one.

Ray:What am I gonna be, a doctor?You need exams.

Ken:Do anything, Ray. Do anything.


ROOM

(Dear Ken,I went to the park so she wouldn't have to clean it up.Ray)

Ray:What a wanker!

Ken:He said this whole trip,this whole being in Bruges thing,was just to give you one last, joyful memory before you died.

Ray:In Bruges?The Bahamas, maybe.Why fucking Bruges?

Ken:I suppose it's cheaper.


TRAIN STATION

Ray:The rest of the acid and the ecstasy.Can I have me gun back, please?What am I gonna do, Ken?What am I gonna do? 

Ken:Just keep moving.Keep on moving.Try not to think about it.Learn a new language, maybe?

Ray:Sure, I can hardly do English.That's one thing I like about Europe, though.You don't have to learn any of their languages.

Ken:Just forget about home for a while.See how the land lies in six years, seven years.Seven years is not that long.

Ray:It's longer than that boy got.Me first fucking job.Great hitman I turned out to be.

Ken:Some people just aren't cut out for it, Ray.

Ray:Are you?

Ray:When are you going back to England?

Ken:I'll head back in a couple of hours or something.

Ray:Harry's not gonna be mad at you, is he? For letting me go?

Ken:I'll sort out Harry.

Ray:Just tell him I'll have probably killed meself in a fortnight, anyway.

Ken:You won't, will you, Ray?


Ken:Harry? It's Ken.Listen to this noise.Do you know what that is?Yeah, I know you know it's a train.Do you know what train?Well, it's a train that Ray just got on,and he's alive and he's well,and he doesn't know where he's going and neither do I.So if you need to do your worst, do your worst.You've got the address of the hotel. I'll be here waiting.Because I've got to quite like Bruges, now.It's like a fucking fairytale or something.


HARRY'S HOME

Harry's wife:Harry.

Harry's wife:Harry!

Harry:What?

Harry's wife:It's an inanimate fucking object.

Harry:You're an inanimate fucking object!

Harry:Now, you lot be good for your mummy and lmamoto, okay?'Cause Daddy's got to go away for a few days.

Harry's wife:Where are you going?

Harry:I've got to go to Bruges.

Harry's wife:Bruges? Where's that?

Harry:It's in Belgium.

Harry's wife:Why would anybody have to go to Belgium?

Harry:'Cause I've got to sort something out.

Harry's wife:Is it something to do with the phone?

Harry:It's something to do with Ken.It's a matter of honor.

Harry's wife:Well, it ain't gonna be dangerous, is it?

Harry:Well, of course it's gonna be dangerous if it's a matter of fucking honor!

Harry's wife:You are bringing the fellas with you?Tell me you're bringing the fellas with you.Harry.

Harry:I'm sorry for calling you an inanimate object.I was upset.


ON THE TRAIN

Police:You're Irish?        

Ray:Yes.

Police:What is your name?

Ray:Derek Perlurrl.

Police:You hit the Canadian.You hit the Canadian.

Ray:I "heet" the Canadian?I don't know what you're talking about.

Canadian:That's him! That's the motherfucker.

Police:You hit the Canadian, yeah?

Ray:Canadian? Shit.

Police:We're taking you back to Bruges.      Ray:Brilliant.


YURI'S HOME

Harry:Aye aye.

Yuri:Take your pick, Mr. Waters.

Harry:An Uzi?I'm not from South Central Los fucking Angeles.I didn't come here to shoot

20 black 10-year-olds in a fucking drive-by.

I want a normal gun for a normal person.

Yuri:I knew he wouldn't kill the guy.I could see it in his eyes when I was telling him about the alcoves.

Harry:About the what?        

Yuri:The alcoves.The alcoves in the Koningin Astrid Park.Oh, I also have some dumdums.You use this word, "dumdums"?The bullets that make the head explode?

Harry:Dumdums, yeah.

Yuri:Would you like some of these dumdums?

Harry:I know I shouldn't,but I will.

Eirik:Motherfucker.

Harry:Is he talking to me?

Yuri:No, Eirik's on your side, Mr. Waters.Your young friend blinded him last night.

Harry:Ray did?

Eirik:I was trying to rob him and he took my gun from me.And the gun was full of blanks,and he shot the blank into my eye.And now, I cannot see from this eye ever again,the doctors say.

Harry:Well, to be honest, it sounds like it was all your fault.

Eirik:What?

Harry:I mean, basically, if you're robbing a man and you're only carrying blanks,and you allow your gun to be taken off you,and you allow yourself to be shot in the eye with a blank,for which I assume the person has to get quite close to you, then,yeah, really, it's all your fault for being such a poof.So why don't you stop whingeing and cheer the fuck up?

Yuri:Eirik, I really wouldn't respond.

Eirik:I thought you wanted the guy dead?

Harry:I do want the guy dead. I want him fucking crucified.But it don't change the fact that he stitched you up like a blind, little gay boy. Does it?Thanks for the gun, Yuri.


SQUARE

Harry:Well?

Ken:The boy is suicidal, Harry.He's a walking dead man.Keeps going on about Hell and purgatory...

Harry:When I phoned you yesterday, did I ask you,

"Ken, will you do me a favor and become Ray's psychiatrist, please?"No. What I think I asked you was,"Could you go blow his fucking head off for me?""He's suicidal"?I'm suicidal. You're suicidal. Everybody's fucking suicidal!We don't all keep going on about it!Has he killed himself yet?No. So he's not fucking suicidal, is he?

Ken:He put a loaded gun to his head this morning.I stopped him. 

Harry:He... What?This gets fucking worse!

Ken:We were down in the park...

Harry:Let me get this right. You were down in the park?What's that got to do with fucking anything?Let me get this right.Not only have you refused to kill the boy,you've even stopped the boy from killing himself,which would have solved my problem,

which would have solved your problem,which sounds like it would've solved the boy's problem.

Ken:It wouldn't have solved his problem.

Harry:Ken, if I had killed a little kid, accidentally or otherwise,I wouldn't have thought twice.I'd have killed myself on the fucking spot.On the fucking spot.I'd have stuck the gun in me mouth on the fucking spot!

Ken:That's you, Harry.The boy has the capacity to change.The boy has the capacity to do something decent with his life.

Harry:Excuse me, Ken. I have the capacity to change.

Ken:Yeah, you do.You've the capacity to get fucking worse!

Harry:Yeah, now I'm getting down to it!

Ken:Harry, let's face it.And I'm not being funny, I mean no disrespect,but you're a cunt.You're a cunt now, you've always been a cunt.And the only thing that's gonna change is you're gonna become an even bigger cunt.Maybe have some more cunt kids.

Harry:Leave my kids fucking out of it.What have they done?You fucking retract that bit about my cunt fucking kids!

Ken:I retract that bit about your cunt fucking kids.

Harry:Insulting my fucking kids! That's going overboard, mate!

Ken:I retracted it, didn't I?Still leaves you being a cunt.

Harry:Yeah, I fucking got that.

Harry:Where's Ray now?

Ken:Oh, right about now, Ray is in one or other of the one million towns in mainland Europe it's possible to be in, other than here.


POLICE OFFICE

Ray:I'll get all the money back to you soon as I get through to me friend.

Chloe:It's not a problem, Raymond.

Ray:And I'll get all your acid and your ecstasy back to you, too.

Chloe:English humor!


SQUARE

Harry:I'm assuming you've got your gun on you.

Ken:That Yuri bloke's a funny fella, isn't he?

Harry:He does yoga.

Ken:"The alcoves."

Harry:Was he going on to you about the alcoves?

Ken:"The alcoves in the Koningin Astrid Park." Harry, I know you gotta do what you gotta do.It's a bit crowded round here, you know?

Harry:Well, I'm not gonna have a shootout in the middle of a thousand fucking Belgians, am I?Not to mention the other nationalities,just on their holidays.        Ken:Hmm.To see the swans and the Gothic and all the fairytale stuff, eh?

Harry:Are you trying to fucking wind me up?

Ken:No, Harry.

Harry:On top of calling me a cunt and calling me kids cunts.I might just have to fucking shoot you right here.Christ!

Ken:Let's go up the bell tower.Be quiet up there this time of evening.Let's go up there.


Ray:Yeah. Canadians.I feel a bit bad.They didn't kill John Lennon, did they?Anyway, supposed to turn up to court here in two days.

Chloe:Are you going to turn up?        

Ray:Don't know.What have I got to stay for really?

Chloe:The most beautiful woman you've ever seen in all of your stupid life.


Clerk:The tower is closed this evening.

Ken:No way. It's supposed to be open till 7:00.

Clerk:The tower is usually open until 7:00.Yesterday an American had a heart attack up the tower.Today the tower is closed.

Harry:Here, cranky, here's 100 for you.We're only gonna be 20 minutes.

Clerk:The tower is closed this evening.Understand, Englishman?


Ray:Jimmy, I've been wanting to say I'm really sorry for karate-chopping you the other night.That was way out of order.

Midget:You know, Ray,I'd find it easier to believe and forgive you, somehow,if the two of you weren't laughing straight in my fucking face!It's for the goddamn movie, man.


Ken:It is a nice town, Harry.I'm glad I got to see it.I didn't mean to be taking the piss out of it being a fairytale place.It is a fairytale place.It really is.        

Harry:Hmm.It's just a shame it's in Belgium, really.But then you figure if it wasn't in Belgium,if it was somewhere good,there'd be too many people coming to see it.It would spoil the whole thing.

Ken:Well, I'm glad I got to see it before I died.

Harry:What are you doing?What are you fucking doing?

Ken:I'm not fighting anymore, Harry.

Harry:All right, then I'm blowing your fucking head off.Don't come over all Gandhi. What are you fucking doing?Ken, stop messing about, please.Pick up your gun. I know I'm going to beat you anyway'cause you're a spaz, but...        

Ken:Harry,I'm totally in your debt.The things that have gone between us in the past,I love you unreservedly for all that.

Harry:What?

Ken:For your integrity.For your honor.I love you.The boy had to be let go.The boy had to be given a chance.And if to do that, I had to say,"Fuck you, and fuck what I owe you,"and fuck everything that's gone on between us,"then that's what I had to do.But I'm not fighting you.And I accept, totally, everything you've got to do.I accept it. Totally.

Harry:Oh, yeah?

Ken:Yeah.

Harry:Well, you say all that fucking stuff,I can't fucking shoot you now, can I?

Ken:It's entirely up to you, Harry.It's entirely your call.All I'm saying is I'm not fighting.

Ken:Oh, you fucking cunt!

Harry:Look, I'm not gonna do nothing to you just 'cause you're standing about like Robert fucking Powell.

Ken:Like who?        

Harry:Like Robert fucking Powell out of Jesus of fucking Nazareth!

Ken:My fucking leg!


Midget:The psycho dwarf turns out to just be a loveable little schoolboy,and it's all some kind of Boschian nightmare.Kiss my ass!

Ray:I guess at least there weren't any black people involved, eh, Jimmy?

Midget:I wasn't...I wasn't talking about...

Ray:There's gonna be a war between all the blacks and all the whites.And all the black midgets and all the white midgets,which would actually be really good.

Midget:That's just cocaine.

Ray:He didn't even want the Vietnamese on his side!

Midget:That's just cocaine.Listen, we're filming down by the pointy building tonight.It might actually be good for once.You guys should come along.

Chloe:We...I think we're just gonna have a quiet one tonight, Jimmy.

Midget:That's how it is!In another life.

Ray:They're great, aren't they?


You didn't. You didn't!


Eirik:Mr. Waters? Mr. Waters?

Harry:Who's that? 

Eirik:It's Eirik.

Harry:The blind boy?        

Eirik:Yeah.Yes.

Harry:What do you fucking want?

Eirik:The guy you're looking for,the guy Ray, he's downstairs at the bar.


Harry:I'm sorry, Ken.

Harry:But you can't kill a kid and expect to get away with it.

Harry:You just can't.


Harry:Where?        

Eirik:To the left when you come out.The bar to the left.


Ray:Ken!

Ray:Ken! Ken!

Ken:Harry's here.

Ray:What?

Ken:Take my gun.

Ray:Ken?Where's my gun?Where's my gun?

Ken:I'm gonna die now, I think.

Ray:Oh, Ken!Jesus!


HOTEL

Ray:Put that gun away, right now!

Marie:Mr. Blakely said you had left.

Ray:I need the key to the room right now.Quickly, now!And you gotta go home right now.It's very, very dangerous here.All right? Go home! Right now!        

Marie:Okay.


Marie:No, I won't let you up there!

Harry:Lady, get out of my fucking way, please.

Marie:No, I won't. I won't get out of your way.You'll have to go through me.

Harry:Well, obviously, I'm not gonna through you, am I,with a baby and that? I'm a nice person.But could you just get out of the fucking way, please?

Ray:Marie!Just let him come up, it's okay.Harry, swear not to start shooting until she's left the hotel.

Harry:I swear not to start shooting till she's left the hotel.I totally swear.

Marie:Well, I'm not going anywhere.This is my hotel.So you can fuck off!

Harry:I suppose you've got a gun up there?        Ray:Yeah.

Harry:Then what are we gonna do? We can't stand here all night.

Marie:Why don't you both put your guns down and go home?

Harry:Don't be stupid. This is the shootout.

Ray:Harry, I've got an idea.        

Harry:What?

Ray:My room faces onto the canal, right?I'm gonna go back to me room, jump into the canal,see if I can swim to the other side and escape.

Harry:Right.        

Ray:If you go outside and round the corner,you can shoot at me from there and try and get me.That way, we leave this lady and her baby out of the whole, entire thing.

Harry:Do you completely promise to jump into the canal?I don't want to run out there, come back in 10 minutes and find you fucking hiding in a cupboard.

Ray:I completely promise, Harry.I'm not gonna risk having another little kid die, am I? 

Harry:So, hang on, I go outside,then I go which way, right or left?

Ray:You go right, don't you?You can see it from the doorway! It's a big fucking canal!

Harry:All right. Jesus! I've only just got here, haven't I?Okay. On a count of "one, two, three, go," okay?

Ray:Okay.

Ray:What? Who says it?

Harry:Oh, you say it.

Marie:You guys are crazy.

Ray:Are you ready? 

Harry:Ready.

Ray:Set? 

Harry:Set.

Ray:One, two, three, go!


ON THE CANAL

Ray:Keep driving!

Ray:No way. You're way too far away.


Ray:The little boy.

Harry:That's right, Ray.The little boy.


Harry:Oh.

Harry:I see.

Ray:No, Harry.

Ray:He's not...

Harry:You've got to stick to your principles.


There's a Christmas tree somewhere in London with a bunch of presents underneath it that'll never be opened.And I thought, "If I survive all this,"I'll go to that house, apologize to the mother there,"and accept whatever punishment she chose for me."Prison, death, it didn't matter.Because at least in prison and at least in death, you know,I wouldn't be in fucking Bruges.But then, like a flash, it came to me, and I realized,"Fuck, man, maybe that's what Hell is."The entire rest of eternity spent in fucking Bruges!"And I really, really hoped I wouldn't die.I really, really hoped I wouldn't die.



END




http://www.douban.com/note/24344026/?post=ok#last

</影评>
<有用数>579</有用数>
<没用数>24</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>gee</作者>
<标题>杀手的理想主义</标题><作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2009-04-01 00:21:26</时间>
<影评>
            它被归入“喜剧片”序列，标签有“黑色幽默”、“黑帮片”、“剧情片”、“英式喜剧”……它的情节中确实穿插着一个个英式幽默的桥段，让人不时会心一笑。但到了它出人意表的、有着漫长高潮的结尾，我却哭得肝肠寸断，无法停止。


　　这是一个应该被归入童话的故事，虽然是黑色的。


　　雷和肯是两个合作的杀手，雷年轻，肯年老。雷在一次执行任务中，误杀了一个小孩，从此陷入自责之中，蒙上了沉重的心理负担。这一次，他们俩接到一个任务，去布鲁日，住在定好的一个酒店房间，逛街、等头目哈里的电话。


　　他们逛了，在布鲁日这个童话一般的城市里，欣赏中世纪遗留下来的建筑、梦境一般的雾气、美丽的河道以及徜徉其上的天鹅。肯乐在其中，雷却毫无兴趣。


　　电话终于来了，打给肯，让他杀掉雷，“终止他的负罪感”。而当肯怀着矛盾的心情，准备偷偷执行命令时，却赶上雷因为无法越过内心的负疚，而终于决定饮弹自杀。


　　肯放走了雷，要他去“救一个男孩”来赎自己杀了一个男孩的罪，而他自己则留下来等待头目哈里的惩罚。


　　始终以“要坚持原则”为内心指导的哈里果然来了，在影片接近末尾的时候，他才真正说出他执意要杀雷的原因“一个杀了孩子的人不能不受到惩罚”。他要杀雷，肯要救雷，他们都觉得自己罪孽深重，而要做坚持内心向善的原则的事情，为此肯献出了生命，而哈里惩罚了雷之后，却发现自己误杀了一个男孩——其实是个成年的侏儒——而坚持自己的原则，饮弹自尽。


　　“要坚持原则”，是从片头至片尾，被几个人屡次重复的主题。杀手干的是犯罪的事情，但他们有他们的善恶观——不可以打妇女、不可以杀孩子。他们坚信自己杀的那些人本来就不是什么好人，因此杀人并不让他们负疚，而只有猥琐，才让他们鄙视，让他们忏悔。


　　他们的价值观，是中世纪的价值观。他们是现代意义上的坏人，但他们却彬彬有礼、有骑士风度，坦诚而平等地对待对手。而且他们每个人，都有一颗柔软的心。哈里要杀掉雷，却为他们安排了布鲁日的旅行，因为他小时候来过这里，对这里有美好的印象，他希望雷在临死前能够享受到幸福；肯为了救雷，从高塔顶上跳了下来，而跳之前，为避免砸到无辜者，先扔硬币把游客吓走；雷会为一句冒犯的话打人，却会在公园里看孩子们游戏，会把自己的积蓄给怀孕的旅馆老板娘，让她照顾自己的孩子……最感人的一段在哈里和雷在旅馆决斗的部分，为怕伤及无辜的老板娘，两个人同时选择了离开旅馆的方式。


　　三个“坏人”最后都死了，被杀的、和自戕的。而和这几个坏人比起来，那些所谓的好人却显得猥琐得多。秃头用敲诈的方法抢钱、用告密的方式报自己眼睛被打瞎的仇；加拿大人貌似有教养，却率先出言不逊事后又靠警察主张权利。正是这巨大的反差，让人看到几个坚守原则，内心善良坦荡的杀手一一死去的时候，会为属于中世纪的道德随他们消逝而感到伤痛，会宁愿要这样的“坏人”，而不要那些懦弱猥琐的“好人”。


　　血淋淋的故事，上演在一个童话般的地方，那粼粼的石板街道、傍晚的灯光，那蒸腾在半空的雾气、中世纪的建筑，配着优美的钢琴乐曲，就如同三个杀手身上的中古气质一样，“知道自己清醒着，却感觉好像在梦里”（剧中台词）。景色与时代的反差，正是他们三人的内心与当代人的反差。


　　当肯对哈里说“我爱你，你一直很正直”的时候，我还不能理解这句话。待到他为了旅馆老板娘而放雷一马，又因为以为自己杀了孩子而吞弹的时候，我才终于明了这句话的含义。哈里真是值得他爱的，虽然三个人都是善良而又原则的人，但哈里是他们中间最坚持信念的一个，坚持到了教条的地步。由此也解释了他接到肯的电话，决心亲赴布鲁日杀人的时候，导演安排他温和地与孩子们道别，并为一时的粗暴向妻子道歉的用心。多么好的一个男人，几乎可以称为崇高。而这样的人的逝去，怎么能不让人痛惜呢。


　　饰演哈里的演员，是拉尔夫·费因斯，这个有着贵族气质的整洁的男人，完美地诠释了这个有中世纪情怀的杀手老大。在自杀那一刻，他把枪从嘴里掏出来，重述了一遍“必须要坚持原则”，然后才有塞回去开枪，那很英式，很幽默，却让人笑不出，眼泪不由得掉下来。


　　樊无期为荆轲的义举砍下自己的头颅、高渐离为了朋友弄瞎了自己的眼睛——这些重义轻死的壮举，永远地属于了古代。原来外国，也有同样的感叹。


　　童话一般的地方，童话一般的氛围。这一切的安排，都是在告诉大家：这只是个童话，因为，这样的杀手，在这样一个时代，恐怕根本活不到办这些事的年纪。
      </影评>
<有用数>305</有用数>
<没用数>8</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>瞎子</作者>
<标题>所有中年男都应该看的电影</标题><作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2008-09-06 14:15:34</时间>
<影评>
        这是我在豆瓣记录的第一千部电影，因此迟迟没有看，就是想挑部好的。这个晚上，想了很久，选了一部看着像商业片（中文翻译是《杀手没有假期》，好像一部跟《赶尽杀绝》一样的猛片），但前阵子看个片头就觉得很沉闷的电影，《IN BRUGES》——个人直觉这片子有戏。

果然，耐着性子看完开头三十分钟的缓慢和悠长之后（其实也没觉得难捱，因为配乐是相当得好听），这部片子让我欲罢不能，一直到末了，才怅然地叹口气。

因为我说不出是好笑还是悲伤，在整个播放过程中，我不停地在发笑和难过之间荡来荡去。

怎么说呢，不剧透了，说说它的好处吧：

1.如此正宗如此浓郁的黑色幽默——英伦三岛很很干巴巴又很机灵的黑色幽默——这是推荐中年男的原因之一——在我们的幽默感慢慢被生活沉淀为无趣的时候，此时我们已经不大稀罕少年那种不够含蓄的搞笑滑稽，而需要一种洞察式的讥诮。无数个场景，拎出来就是绝好的冷笑话，我相信不久就会有本片的经典台词语录。

2.很MAN的电影——这是推荐中年男的原因之二——在我们的男人味逐渐磨平成世故的时候，算是给我们残存的灯里添点油，提醒我们依然可以豪气干云，虽然体型已经失控。三个男人的故事，三个没有发达的肱二头肌腹肌胸肌叉腰肌的男人：一个不安静的年轻仔，一个大腹便便的中年男；一个好像得了甲亢的中年男——他们都很MAN。对于一部杀手片来说，这些都太合适不过了……哦，还有一个很坚持原则的胖子文物保护单位管理员，他也很MAN，虽然挨了顿胖揍。

3.非常好听的配乐——这是推荐中年男的原因之三——品位，品位啊。适合一个潮湿阴暗古老偏僻的比利时小镇的钢琴声，忧郁而温柔，配上电影里三个又搞笑又让人起敬的杀手，很好很强大。

4.天衣无缝的剧本——这是推荐中年男的原因之四——智慧啊，一脑门子都是智慧。啥叫无巧不成书，得巧得自然，不露痕迹。每个邂逅的线索都是伏笔，到最后一起涌现出来，让人恍然大悟。

5.很浪漫的电影——这是推荐中年男的原因之五——一见钟情的浪漫，过命交情的浪漫，杀手和杀手之间的惺惺相惜，中年人对年轻人的爱护希望，无一不浪漫头顶，给我们日渐平庸的生活一点梦幻色彩。

6.这个我拿不准是否适合中年男——有N多哈利波特里出现的演员……其实也是适合的，因为这些演员都是演技派，对于喜欢看门道的中年男来说，是一部过瘾的戏，一举一动无不带着精彩。

7.服装——欧式的古典的平整的熨帖的，怎么穿怎么好看，无论男女，无论老少，这算是企图讲究的中年男另一个不大不小的倾心点吧。

总之，各位超过35岁的WS男们，这部电影强烈推荐你们收藏。

另外，由于中年WS男往往是女文青的克星，因此这部电影也适合企图掌握中年男人复杂微妙心理的女文青。
      </影评>
<有用数>234</有用数>
<没用数>58</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>小刺客</作者>
<标题>不知道大家有没有看DELETED SCENES</标题><作者评分>4</作者评分>
<时间>2008-07-05 17:26:32</时间>
<影评>
        也许不看DELETED SCENES的观众不会看到 为什么KEN效忠于HARRY，虽然电影里也提到是因为他的妻子

在那个删掉的SCENE里面，年轻的HARRY来到KEN的妻子的尸体旁，问是谁干的，旁边的一个貌似HOOKER的女的惨笑着所，是“POTTER”.。。。



。。



于是HARRY冲到警察局去 把POTTER的头砍下来了





我突发奇想的猜测 那么多演过HARRY POTTER的人一起又拍电影 是不是在闲暇时经常聊起当时拍哈利波特的旧事。
      </影评>
<有用数>42</有用数>
<没用数>4</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>槑槑</作者>
<标题>优秀，优秀</标题><作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2017-07-23 10:27:58</时间>
<影评>

主打黑色幽默的变格杀手片，俨然成为另一种次类型。杀手们不断被拖离岗位，替换冷酷的是中年危机与救赎，从解决问题的人变成了问题所在。今次的三位杀手，让导演兼编剧的McDonagh玩弄于一连串漫不经心的巧合间，节约利用任何一个伏笔，炮制了最后一场徒劳悲情的虚无救赎。
一个死的徒劳，什么都没能阻止；一个死的讽刺，虚无的原则经不起上帝开玩笑；一个死的遗憾，嗑药涌起的自杀倾向没能挽回他人生最后的三步错棋：杀小孩、打食客、瞎劫匪，都是暴力惹得祸。Bruges原本只是几个英国人的度假圣地，没想到却成了他们的永久天堂。

</影评>
<有用数>32</有用数>
<没用数>3</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>FOW.to.Freedom</作者>
<标题>"In Bruges的5块印象碎片"</标题><作者评分>4</作者评分>
<时间>2008-06-21 23:27:20</时间>
<影评>
        1-----------"In Bruges"鄙视Bruges的唧唧歪歪

   

   Ray感叹Bruges是个"Shithole'的开始...此鄙视态度Ray始终由头至尾地延续着. 甚至到了谢幕,Ray的最后一句遗言:"I really,really hoped I wouldn't die." 也好似在郁闷地抱怨"我真的真的实在不想死在这Fucking Bruges Shithole" 我才想他真心的对Bruges咬牙切齿.再有导演兼编剧Martin  McDonagh也刻意把片名起作"In Bruges". 许多观众觉得那样起是为了表达出置身于Bruges的宗教氛围,以照应其救赎的主旋律.但我偏偏觉得如此取名有一部分原因是出于Ray的对于Bruges的Shithole情结....

   (看过影片,我个人感觉Bruges真是美伦美幻,或许只是纯粹由于我长这么大也没有几次能直接或间接地目睹过歌特建筑群的优雅古朴.至于Ray,正如他解释.从小便在爱尔兰的-都柏林(Dublin)住惯了,索性不感冒)

    而导演为何要在本应当意味深长的结尾,竟以Ray的垂死调侃Bruges做为收场??:

    (表达了对小男孩母亲的歉悔之意...Ray接着说:)

    prison, death,it didn't matter - Because at least in prison and at least in death,you know, - I wouldn't be in fucking Bruges. - But then, like a flash,it came to me, and I realized, - ''Fuck, man, maybe that's what Hell is.'' - ''The entire rest of eternity spent in fucking Bruges!'' - And I really, really hoped I wouldn't die. - I really, really hoped I wouldn't die.

"入狱, 死掉, 这都没什么. 因为就算要进监狱或者就算要去死, 你知道..我都不要选在这他妈B的布鲁日. 但接着, 突然间闪过一个直觉, 我意识到, "我操,这恐怕是最惨的情况了","安详地长眠在这他妈B的布鲁日" 

我真的真的希望我不要死,我真的真的希望我不要死...."


   觉得这样翻译才算贴切(请原谅我为了追求原味而使用了"他妈B的"),其他的翻译,通病都在于把hell与a flash解释为"地狱"和"一道光芒". 而like a flash一定是"闪过,掠过"的意思.如果是"象道光芒"则一定得要写成like a flash of lighting.而maybe that's what Hell is基本上与正式意义上的地狱无关,与who the hell are you?同理,只为了表明情绪态度...


  谢幕的调侃,我只能把这些归结为英国式的黑色幽默,天晓得Bruges究竟与哪些英国人有什么过节,当然这种八成只有英国人才能会心一笑的幽默,非英人士真的不应该过份扯淡. 只求点到为止.


2------------- "In Bruges"的反美情结


   "In Bruges"刚接触我还习惯性的妄想其是好莱坞制造,但看着看着便自然不觉得了.因为身为一号男主角的Ray是个彻头彻尾的反美主义者.他尤其和美利坚过不去可以表现在:先是鄙视了三只来自美国的麦当劳大象,又在餐厅当众打了一个指责他女朋友吸烟的男士和一位向他挥舞致命酒瓶的女士.Ray戏称他们为"Yankee"(美国佬),却在后来发现他们其实是加拿大佬Orz.下一件壮举是借着海洛英的亢奋劲儿用假正经的空手道放倒了一个有严重种族主义倾向的美国侏儒.还要补充的是Ray还为身受美国人所害的越南人和英国披头士乐队主唱列侬抱不平.


3--------------Ray,Ken &amp; Harry


   Ray其角色在影片中最逗最吸引人,一脸蛋忧郁无辜的小样,消极悲观,既犯贱又憨厚的态度,还拌有悲喜无常的歇斯底里,而其处境又让人深感怜悯,有点英国式幽默的韵味.

   Ken则是三人中比较正常的性情中人.喜欢把晚辈视为亲弟弟般照顾,把上司视为长辈般尊敬.至于他在星空下的钟楼里向着Harry郑重的重复了两次"I love u",大家千万不要误解成老男人搞断背.人家老外对于爱情,亲情,友情,兄弟之情,姐妹之情等等等等的感情通用表达式即为"I love u~".对某人的深厚感情,用"I love u"表达,既纯真而直接.(当然一般情况下没必要太深情,不然真的会认为是搞断背的~ )

   Harry我们都知道他不是恶棍,他只是个连孕妇都会迁就的原则崇拜型杀手,也是手下敬爱的模范好老大.虽然有偏爱用"Fucking"当形容词的癖好,有些臭脾气.不过他真的不什么恶棍.可是他出于原则性问题,义无返顾地追杀一号男主角,因而触动了商业片法则,受以反派角色之待遇.当Harry的光荣饮弹谢罪,他却偏偏没意识到这一切只不过是一场有点儿复杂的误会,可怜的Harry此时光荣指数大打折扣,倒霉地在结尾高潮处挂掉了...



4-------------理论上, Ray最后死了.

   

   理论上,Ray最终还是死了,只是我们没能亲眼证实.就如同Ken,是种因果循环.Ken曾毙掉了一个向他挥舞致命酒瓶的好人,其人则是为了保护兄弟而牺牲.Ken也同样为了保护情深意重的Ray而牺牲.所以Ray必然会遭遇子弹穿胸,就象他如此对待那位神父一样.一样得死掉...

   当然,这仅仅是理论上的事儿...

   


5-------------给他四颗~


    我喜欢黑色幽默,因此喜爱"In Bruges".黑色喜剧习惯以黑暗的故事为基调.营造出一种拌有忧伤的黑暗幽默.但毕竟再好也是跳不出商业片这道槛,所以四颗星理所应得.



    


             



  
      </影评>
<有用数>44</有用数>
<没用数>7</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>大人</作者>
<标题>得不到的自由</标题><作者评分>4</作者评分>
<时间>2010-12-05 08:48:02</时间>
<影评>


       两个杀手，血迹斑斑，背负着自身的罪孽在布鲁日度假旅行。年轻的杀手雷忧心忡忡满脸抑郁，年长的杀手肯轻松惬意略带思绪。抑郁也罢，轻松也好，既然已抽身来到古雅的小镇，何不享受一下血腥职业生涯中难得的自由？可剧情陡转直下，虽想悠游自在，“自由”二字却注定和他们无缘，乃是他们为之沦陷的噩梦：肯接到老板哈里的命令，要他杀掉雷，而肯不愿意使命令成为现实，于是大费周章，甚至丢掉性命；雷则一直心神意乱，困扰在误杀孩童的梦魇中脱不开身。影片在二人懒懒散散的神游闲逛中刻画出他们的不自由，一个被迫去做不情愿做的事情，一个因心事而悲苦愁情不得安宁。在布鲁日的冬日阳光下，他们要经历何种的周游，才能摆脱自身的阴霾？


    除去高矮胖瘦，英俊臃肿这些体貌特征，电影用简洁略带情绪化的对话告诉我们，雷和肯的处世心态也不一样。于肯而言，他不相信什么，但相信活着就要做一个好人，要遵循善的规则做事，比如最基本的扶老携幼。雷马上接着说，扶老携幼？在这个世道上，说不定那个你搀扶的老太婆还要怪你把她的东西提坏了呢。他没什么善的观念，也没有什么信仰，也许他只有一个八字眉，永远挂在愁苦的脸上。


    曾有两种自由观念在西方先后出现，古希腊柏拉图一派讲的是，自由关键在于拥有善。人把握住了善，行动就得到了自由。肯杀人，但他认为所杀的都是坏人，除去一个无辜者，那是为救自己兄弟而被肯杀死的男人。在片尾哈里追杀而来，面对欲杀雷的哈里，肯陷入了一个轮回，他现在就成了为保护兄弟雷不被杀而反被杀手残害的人。他之所以要去阻止哈里，那是去做他认为应该做的事，无论是否能够从往日的罪恶中解脱出来，至少在拯救雷的过程中，他能得到自由。


    但这种对自由的看法忽视了这样一个事实：人有可能不清楚什么是善？更有甚者本身就不是为拥有善而行动的，那这些人的行为还能不能得到自由？肯认为自己是持守“善”的，可难道把坏人通通杀掉就能算善？所以肯口中所言的“善”，定义并不清晰，他唯一坚持的不过是他自己给善下的定义。


    片尾另一个相似的轮回更好的阐释出：若有的人所行之事本不以善为主旨，那此类行为将会产生多么可笑又可怕的现实。这发生在哈里和雷之间，哈里认为雷误杀小孩应该死，因为这是拟定好了的规则。而哈里杀雷时，无意间杀死了在场的侏儒，并将侏儒误认为小孩，按照自己所言的规则，他饮弹而亡。当然，哈里的自尽绝非成仁之举，而只是死守被抽掉“善”的观念后徒留下的僵硬条款。这是对失去灵魂的律法规则的绝妙嘲讽，它既不能迎来善，又无法避免恶，只能让彼此深陷在你来我往的同态复仇和冤冤相报中。

    

    从肯到哈里，最糟糕的情况出现了，那就是现实生活中，有些人的确没有认识善和拥有善的能力，他们的行动怎么能称得上是自由？于是便有了善外在于人的观念，这就是基督教的自由观，由神学家奥古斯丁率先写出。他说，我们自身是无法把握住真理和善的，除非代表它们的上帝向我们显现，自由只能在于真理自身的给予，也就是在信仰神的恩典中才能享有自由。


     也许从某种角度来说，在布鲁日即是在基督教中。伯尔曼的恢弘巨著《宗教与革命》中有一章名为“城市法”，在讲述11、12世纪出现的新城市时，特别提到了布鲁日。他说，这些城市不是世界历史上的第一批城市，但与它们完全相同的城市却从来不曾有过。虽然，诸多的历史学家为这样一批城市在当时的出现提出了历史、经济、军事方面的因素，但伯尔曼还是添加上了他自己认为重要的两个因素：“宗教因素”和“法律因素”。因为这些城市的建立都是宗教意义上的联合，是依靠相同的宗教价值和宗教仪式而结合起来的区域组织。这时兴建的城市，无论精神还是特性都源于基督教教会。布鲁日的建立来自于当时腓力伯爵所授予的特许状，在此基础上它建立起了自己的城市法律，甚至这些律法和规则都充满了改革现实和拯救俗世的宗教情怀。

    

    借由伯尔曼的论述，我们来看看两个杀手在假期中游览的布鲁日。两人对于游玩经过短暂争论后，雷跟着肯来到了杀手观光的第一站：“耶稣之血教堂”。在幽暗的教堂中，烛光映射出雷的心事满怀和肯的敬畏虔诚。第一站的用意或许在此：十字军的骑士带回耶稣死亡的血，而耶稣的死亡即所谓的“道成肉身”，在宗教意义上象征着耶稣用肉身代替世上的人承担了罪，而此后的世间众人就用信仰基督教来换取末日审判之时的救赎。接下的画面是一幕幕鲜血淋淋的宗教油画。油画用细腻的笔触展示了，人为其所犯下的罪孽而所要承担的种种痛苦和报应。雷和肯最后在一副油画面前停下，那正是“末日审判”。这一路的游览表现出雷既在自身的经历中纠结折磨，又完全忽视了走出困境应有的道路。他对肃穆的教堂满不在乎正是因为他的救赎观念异常淡薄。当他看到油画的惨烈场景时能激起心中恐惧，可对其中的蕴义则又全然不知。

接下来雷回忆起误杀幼童的场景，编导将其编排的极具宗教意味。杀人的地点安排在教堂，时间布置为告诫之时，被杀者是神父，误杀者是正在祈祷的小孩，总之，一切的一切，都是站在了基督教的极端对立面。雷的不自由，正是因为不懂行善的他忽略了“信仰”。这类自由观念正是强调自由别无他法，只能在宗教信仰中寻求，神的恩典中得救。


    对于信仰，雷似乎天生就是个绝缘体，对于罪过，他又有一步一惊心的敏感。他能在教堂中毫不在意的嘲讽，却又在清晨薄雾中想起犯下的罪孽直掉眼泪；面对肯大谈教堂历史时漫不经心诙谐以对，而看到剥皮割肉的油画却又感到了受刑般的创痛。虽然，在电影中的他喝酒泡妞打架斗殴饮酒吸毒，随性所至无所不做。可一看见他那永远拧上发条的八字眉，任谁都知道，他拥有的是揪心苦闷而不是澄明自由。

    

    在最后中枪的喃喃自语中，雷终于意识到这该死的布鲁日正是他末日审判后的炼狱。当他在教堂中犯下后悔不已的恶行，却来到被宗教包裹一切的城镇里消磨时光，因为自身的罪恶，他在这里所有的际遇都转变成了铭心苦痛的受难与惩罚！怪不得从始至终，他对布鲁日的态度是fuck到底。

    

    在布鲁日，杀手当然没有假期，杀手只能去面壁。在布鲁日，爱情也并非遗忘愧疚往事的途径，金发女郎的美丽与温情掩盖不了她是毒贩和抢劫犯的本质。在布鲁日，想一劳永逸的解脱，自杀却无法成功，因为别人的枪永远比自己的快准狠。在布鲁日，就算坐上逃亡的列车远离，结果仍旧要被阴差阳错的带回。在布鲁日，雷连最后死亡的姿态与场景都是他所犯罪孽的重现。

    

    这如宛如圣城又似鬼域的布鲁日，如此荒诞，如此扯淡，甚至连最后的落幕也是迷惑与茫然。在弥留时刻的雷一边咒骂布鲁日，一边他低语他不想死。这个瞬间，他说他灵光乍现，那是他正开始接近自由呢，还是更加远离了自由？



</影评>
<有用数>35</有用数>
<没用数>2</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>杰西™</作者>
<标题>囧脸没有假期</标题><作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2009-01-19 11:17:43</时间>
<影评>
        其实最开始我一直觉得这是一部喜剧片，后来我却越来越觉得这怎么可能是一部喜剧片？不过每看3分钟我都还是会很确定说这就是一部喜剧片，但是事实上它压根就不是一部喜剧片。


布鲁日是个好地方，历史悠久文化丰富，是很棒的中古城镇，一般来说看到这种环境都会联想到古装魔幻爱情之类的东西，杀手和布鲁日的感觉好像联系不到一起。


所以，其实来到这里的这几个家伙根本就不是杀手。


心怀愧疚的脆弱的喜欢自由自在的囧脸Ray一向倒霉，生气的时候照样大打出手；一本正经重情重义的Ken其实应该去找个博物馆职位，心地善良临死还不忘让广场上的行人当心；Harry言出必行虽然满口爆粪却对自己的原则恪守到傻逼的境界，追杀的时候还掏出地图让大家汗一把。

但是孤独的远去，真枪实弹的追逐和血肉模糊的死亡却俨然一个悲伤的故事。


这个几个家伙其实都不应该是杀手，但是他们是一群爷们儿，他们的世界是爷们儿的世界，只不过更加悲伤、温柔和脆弱一些，混合了枪火与泪水。第二个逗号后面的东西是McDonagh自己说的。


囧脸、硬币、达姆弹。


可是这帮家伙酷毙了。


-----------------------------------------------------------

当然最酷的是达姆弹，虽然有点穿帮。

-----------------------------------------------------------


这样爷们儿的悲情可能让你些许苦闷，那么你还是放下来把它当作喜剧来看吧，至少这个走路遍地踩巧合的剧本还是很喜剧的，你可能会说：我靠！他就那么刚好死在那儿了！


英式幽默的笑点在于你得是个有文化的人，否则你自己才是笑点。英式的恶搞和美式的行为恶搞本质上不同，基本英国电影的开涮文化是文化开涮，譬如加拿大人美国人比利时人的桥段，譬如黑人和白人要开开战了或许是黑矮人和白矮人要开战了的桥段，不过像“中国护送员”那句台词实在是不知道该让人自豪还是让人石化……


本来我想把标题写成《囧脸和他的朋友们》，因为我们就可以看到的每一个有镜头的角色都是有性格的，不会像某些电影里用一个5秒的特写在一个龙套身上直到龙套说完“Ohshit！”之后被怪兽喀嚓干掉，那种只有一个镜头戏份却拥有长达5秒特写的龙套实在让人智商疲软，相比之下一个来自阿姆斯特丹的妓女都有亮点台词。


你看，我甚至还能记得起那个妓女是来自阿姆斯特丹！
      </影评>
<有用数>22</有用数>
<没用数>0</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>店长</作者>
<标题>我误杀小孩嘲笑侏儒殴打游客，但我知道我是个好杀手</标题><作者评分>4</作者评分>
<时间>2019-08-30 11:58:10</时间>
<影评>

《在布鲁日》绝对是部后劲很足的电影。虽然还不至于冲动到马上打开订票软件订一张去布鲁日的机票，但却时不时想起那座大雾笼罩楼梯很窄的塔楼，两张单人床的临河房间，艺术馆里三幅血淋淋的画，河道和广场的小桌，法瑞尔那张忧伤的脸，和他那像迎风乱舞的气球人一样360度扭动的眉毛。

《在布鲁日》也是一部很难定义的电影。有血浆和断肢，枪击，谋杀儿童，迷幻药；有非常越界的黑色幽默和令人不适的笑话，嘲讽"都有自杀倾向的"侏儒、超重美国人、黑人女性；有宗教映射，神性的城市，以“惩罚”为主题的绘画，被枪杀的神父，教堂里保存的圣血；也有黑吃黑，追与逃，有悲剧的宿命论，情绪和情感，父子关系，甚至还有点空间来一段浪漫剧情。
这些过于丰富的类型元素，还有藏在台词中的耍机灵、掉书袋，让《在布鲁日》像四五部影片的集合，牢牢勾住又放大观众的情绪。跳跃在悲剧喜剧甚至闹剧之间，影片带来了一种很新奇又略带割裂的体验，就像Ray游走在悲伤和愤怒之间一样，观众也被迫在情绪之间转换，时哭时笑，时而不适于血腥场面的尺度，时而为自己被政治不正确的笑话逗笑而感到隐秘的内疚。

出身剧院的麦克唐纳，是操纵语言和情绪的高手。他剧作中的台词是出了名地有趣而富有音乐感，常利用人物的音调变化和不断重复，营造出一种有来有回的对峙。比如Ken和Ray谈论之前的一次误杀经历，Ken举例说有可能他误杀的那个lolipop man（引导小朋友们过马路的一种工作）会空手道，那就成了纯粹的自卫行为。两人有了这样一段对话：

Ray: You said he was a lolipop man ?!
Ken: He was a lolipop man.
Ray: What's a lolipop man doing on fucking karate?!
Ken: I'm just saying.
Ray: How old is he ?
Ken: 50.
Ray: What's a 50 years old lolipop man doing in fuckin karate ?! What was he a Chinese lolipop man ?!
读麦克唐纳的剧作集和剧本后才进一步发现，他真的很喜欢用"?!"这个充满惊叹和反讽意味的标点符号。这段对话中Ray通过抬高音调和重复Ken刚说过的话，对Ken不恰当的想象进行无情的拆穿，颇有点日系吐槽的味道。
《在布鲁日》中还有许多这样的片段，比如Ray在餐厅揍完（他以为的）美国人以后大喊“That's for John Lennon, Yankee fucking cunt!“，或是在约会的时候自以为是地调侃比利时的儿童虐杀案，这些以死亡和悲剧为话题的尴尬幽默，和一堆充斥着刻板印象却又被演绎得无比好笑的笑话，构成了麦克唐纳笔下的对话，总是让人当场笑出来，却又马上讪讪地怀疑自己是不是不厚道。
虽然是不可否认的好笑，这大段大段的政治不正确幽默却也为《在布鲁日》招来了大量恶评。诚然这些笑话会让部分人群感到不舒服和被冒犯，然而正如麦克唐纳《枕头人》中主角作家卡图兰发问，“就因为现实世界里真的有小孩被杀，你就不准我在书里写小孩被杀吗”一样，讲故事的人只是在讲故事，他不必为所有听众的不适负责，而我们内心的那部分阴暗面，就留给我们自己在大笑后自省吧。
《在布鲁日》另一被大肆批判的元素，是过于铺张的血腥和暴力。麦克唐纳将主角设置为杀手已经一定程度缓解了一些暴力的无因性，但直到之后的《三块广告牌》时，他才找到了弗兰纳里·奥康纳这把为暴力背书的万能钥匙，将暴力和崇尚暴力真正地合理化，做出了不割裂不拧巴的一部作品。这是一段令人蛮振奋和欣慰的后话。

除开精妙的对话，麦克唐纳也是写人物的高手。虽然Buddy film这样的搭配形式已经太过常见，麦克唐纳却能用充分的银幕时间去细细展现了人物的状态和心理，让Ken和Ray这样一对有点脱线的老少杀手，成为了银幕上继抱盆栽的大叔、穿西装的话痨之后深入人心的杀手形象代言人。
外观像个不太得志的理工科大学讲师的Ken，一下火车就开始了认真的观光。杀手观光客这个身份设置本来就有种反差趣味，而Ken的不苟言笑和要打卡每个景点的那股子坚持，让他显得更加有种格格不入的好笑。而没耐心的Ray，脚一沾到布鲁日的土地就拧着眉毛开始抱怨这是个"shithole"，又在看到电影片场的时候高兴得像个上蹿下跳的孩子。
两个人物初来乍到时的这第一层描写，就已经相当有层次。而对于两人精神状态的进一步观察，在揭示了Ray的心结和Ken的真正任务后逐渐展开，我们才能看到Ken的同理心和纠结，Ray百转千回的痛苦，和两人类似师徒，父子，和玩伴的关系。

杀手老板Harry，在剧情的前三分之二都只活在信件和电话中。但这并不代表他的人物发展被耽搁了，信里满溢的脏字儿，电话里咄咄逼人的口气，都在塑造一个暴戾又原则至上的反派形象。当他的脸顺着电话线出现在景框之中，Harry立马贡献了一段摔电话和安抚孩子的戏码，增添他属于黑帮老大和慈爱父亲的人物厚度。当他驾临布鲁日，我们也能更多看到他的原则，他更人性的情感，和他在紧张追击中拿出一张地图的路痴属性。

麦克唐纳之前的剧作作品常被贴上黑暗的标签，弑父、弑母、虐杀儿童和自杀是反复出现的主题，人物常处于道德困境之中。而《在布鲁日》中，每个人物也都面临着没有正确答案的道德难题，做出了必然的选择，付出了必需的代价。
Ray在第一次出任务时意外射杀了一个正在祈祷的小男孩。还保持着跪姿的男孩手里轻握着一张纸片，上面列着他请求上帝原谅的三条罪孽：容易生气，数学不好，容易悲伤。酿下大错的Ray从此背上了宿命论的诅咒，小男孩的三条罪孽开始生长为Ray的一部分。让他杀一个人他却杀了两个，这当然是数学不好，而在整部影片中，Ray都又生气又悲伤，极度情绪化极度没有安全感，最终企图以自杀的方式寻求救赎。
而Ray或许没意识到的是，他身上还有另外一条诅咒，而这条诅咒的应验，是他自身行为的连环效应带来的必然结果。不计后果的两次打架，让他在快离开布鲁日时被命运的引力拽了回来，最终被困在这个他在地球上最厌恶的地方。我相信影片最后Ray是死去了的，死在他最厌恶的布鲁日，让这个自作自受的宿命链成为一个漂亮的闭环。
Ken面对道德选择时，也经历过一番纠结，最终被Ray的求死意志给动摇了立场。Ken或许相信，当一个人愿意用死来弥补他的错误时，他已经罪不至死了。得出了结论的Ken想必对自己是很满意的，所以当他不得不付出这个坚定选择背后的相应代价时，他几乎没有犹豫。口袋里没花出去的硬币成了开路钱，叮当叮当地落在石板地上，Ken站在大雾中才意识到，Ray或许是对的，那些建筑在地面上就能看得见。
Harry是三人中面对道德困境最坚定的，他已经建立起了一套完整的道德体系，所以矜矜业业亲力亲为地追杀下属，在对自己处刑时也毫不犹豫。但最讽刺的是，在他的标准下他自己本是无罪的，然而整个《在布鲁日》的剧本都在铺垫这最后的一个强力反转，Harry就只能带着他的高贵含笑九泉。
来到剧场之外，麦克唐纳终于有了舞台和聚光灯之外的视觉工具，而他用柔和的光和褪色油画般的色彩去还原了一个神性的布鲁日。这个故事不再只是黑暗的，而是黑暗与温柔并存，血与柔美的河水，夺命追逃和慢速的游船，枪声和那首洗脑的钢琴主题曲，都同时出现在这个巨大的舞台上。

Ken和Ray参观的美术馆中有这样一幅画，法官向代表死神的骷髅递上纸片，那是他在人间最后的一笔债。最后的最后，三个人都为自己的行为和选择付出了代价，Ken洒下了金币，Ray倒在了片场梦幻的雪地，而Harry伦敦家中的那棵圣诞树下，堆着再也不会被打开的礼物。审判日最终谁也逃不过，我们只能祈祷当惩罚到来时，我们能在一个完美的地方，能在布鲁日。

</影评>
<有用数>32</有用数>
<没用数>0</没用数>
</review>
</reviews>
</movie>