<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
<电影名>爱在午夜降临前 Before Midnight</电影名>
<年份>2013</年份>
<评分>8.9</评分>
<封面>https://img1.doubanio.com/view/photo/s_ratio_poster/public/p2074715729.jpg</封面>
<导演>理查德·林克莱特</导演>
<演员>伊桑·霍克 / 朱莉·德尔佩 / 肖姆斯·戴维-菲茨帕特里克 / 詹妮弗·普里尔 / 夏洛特·普里尔 / 仙尼娅·卡洛格罗普卢 / 沃尔特·拉萨利 / 亚里安妮·拉贝德 / 雅尼斯·帕帕多普洛斯 / 阿赛娜·拉海尔·灿加里 / 帕诺斯·科罗尼斯 / 约塔·阿吉罗普卢 / 约翰·斯洛斯</演员>
<简介>被影迷奉为爱情圭臬的《爱在黎明破晓前》、《爱在日落黄昏时》终于迎来了第三部《爱在午夜降临前》。第一部中美国青年杰西（伊桑·霍克 Ethan Hawke 饰）坐火车邂逅法国女孩赛琳（朱莉·德尔佩 Julie Delpy 饰），两人在维也纳度过难忘一晚；9年后的第二部，杰西已成 为作家，他的小说让他和赛琳在巴黎重逢，两人于日落前再续前缘。如今又一个9年过去了，杰西与赛琳已经一起生活并有了一对双胞胎女儿，对人生和爱情也有了更多感悟。《爱在午夜降临前》就是撷取他们在希腊伯罗奔尼撒南部小岛度假的最后一天。
                                    
                                　　导演理查德·林克莱特和两位主演就像与影迷在赴一个每9年的约会，尽管三部曲的制作跨度长达18年，但故事情节几乎可以写在一张纸的背面。电影惯于只用人与人的对话讲述故事，两位主人公或行走在静谧的村落，或悠然坐在露台和餐桌前，不断的讨论着文学、爱情、生活、两性等话题。然而与前两部不同的是，随着他们终于走到一起，爱情的浪漫也开始被生活的日常琐碎和彼此相处的实用性取代，吵架拌嘴也随之而来。如何在“婚姻”的面纱下维持爱情？电影将18年的感情铺开，再徐徐化解那些小小的怨念，呈现爱情最真实动人一面。</简介>
<reviews>
<review>
<作者>Jason Bourne</作者>
<作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2013-06-01 11:44:28</时间>
<影评>
        我今天早晨读到这篇文章，试着翻译了一下。希望各位喜欢这系列影片的朋友们喜欢。这三部曲可以排进我看过的最浪漫的影片之列。也祝福你们都能找到那个陪你絮絮叨叨永远说下去的好朋友兼爱人。（旧约圣经中，描述妻子时，用的一个希伯来文的意思是：平等的、最亲密无间的朋友、伙伴(Prov. 2:17 אַלּוּף)。如果你能和你最好的异性朋友结婚，那就是一个莫大的祝福和美事！）


翻译的不好，欢迎探讨指点！

==============================================

The Real Couple Behind Before Sunrise

《爱在日出之前》背后真正的情侣


By Forrest Wickman

福雷斯特·威克曼

Posted Thursday, May 30, 2013, at 9:02 AM

发表于2013年5月30日，星期四，9:02AM


If you stick around through the closing credits of Before Midnight, the latest film in the trilogy that also includes Before Sunrise and Before Sunset, you’ll see that the movie is dedicated to someone whose name even the most die-hard fans have never heard before: Amy Lehrhaupt. Almost 25 years ago, Lehrhaupt met a young man named Richard Linklater and spent a night with him that he never forgot. Their encounter inspired Linklater to conceive and direct Before Sunrise, the first film in the series. She never saw it, though; unbeknownst to Linklater, by the time that movie came out, Lehrhaupt was dead.

《爱在午夜降临前(Before Midnight)》是包括《爱在日出之前(Before Sunrise)》、《爱在日落之前(Before Sunset)》在内的三部曲之中的最后一部。如果你坚持看完了这部电影结束时的演职员名单的话，你会看到导演将这部电影献给了一个人，而这个人的名字就算是最死忠的影迷也从没有听说过——艾米·赖豪普特（Amy Lehrhaupt）。差不多25年前，艾米·赖豪普特遇见了一个叫做理查德·林克莱特（Richard Linklater）的年轻人，并与之共度一晚，这一晚让他难以忘怀。他们的这次偶遇激发了林克莱特构想并执导《爱在日出之前》的灵感，这也是此三部曲中的第一部。然而，她并没有看到该片，因为林克莱特并不知道，在这部影片上映之前，赖豪普特已经香消玉殒了。


Linklater never mentioned Lehrhaupt by name in the press before promoting Before Midnight—Ethan Hawke has said that the director was uncomfortable mentioning her until “extremely recently”—but he has long made brief references to their encounter. From a number of interviews he’s done over the years, we can now piece together the complete story of how Lehrhaupt helped inspire the series.

在宣传推广《爱在午夜降临前》之前，林克莱特从未在媒体上提及过赖豪普特的名字。伊桑·霍克（Ethan Hawke）曾说过，导演林克莱特直到“非常近的最近”，一直都对提及她感到不自在。但是，林克莱特在很久以前就曾简略的提到过他们的相遇。我们现在则可以从这多年来他参与过的多个采访中拼凑出这个完整的，关于赖豪普特如何激发了这一系列电影创作灵感的故事。 


Linklater met Lehrhaupt in fall 1989, when he was visiting his sister in Philadelphia. He was 29 and had just finished shooting Slacker, and was staying there for one night while passing through on the way home from New York. Lehrhaupt was several years younger, about 20. They met in a toy shop, and ended up spending the whole night together, “from midnight until six in the morning,” “walking around, flirting, doing things you would never do now.” As in Before Sunrise, most of what they did was talk, “about art, science, film, the gamut.” Did they kiss? Yes. Did they have sex? The Times went so far as to ask Linklater in a recent interview, but he said he wants to “leave a little mystery.”

林克莱特与赖豪普特相遇在1989年的秋天，他正在费城拜访他的sister。他时年29岁，刚完成了电影《都市浪人（Slacker）》的拍摄，在从纽约返回家的途中，在那里经停一晚。赖豪普特比他小几岁，大约20岁。他们在一家玩具商店相遇，最后共度了整夜。“从午夜直到凌晨六点”，“四处闲逛、调情、做着那些你现在永远不会去做的事”，就像在《爱在日出之前》一样，他们所做的绝大部分事情就是聊天，“聊艺术、科学、电影，聊所有东西”， 他们接吻了吗？是的。他们做爱了吗？在泰晤士报（The Times）最近采访林克莱特时询问他到这个地步，但他说，他想保留一丝神秘。


Even in the midst of that romantic night, the filmmaker in Linklater couldn’t help but consider its cinematic possibilities. In a 2004 interview with the New York Times, he remembered “walking around [thinking], ‘If I could just capture this feeling I’m having right now,’ instead of actually having that feeling.” On a recent episode of the podcast The Q&amp;A with Jeff Goldsmith, he recalled mentioning the movie idea to Lehrhaupt that night:

即使是在这样一个浪漫的夜晚中，林克莱特身体里电影制作人的身份无法自已的考虑起把它拍摄成电影的可能性。在2004年一次与纽约时报（The New York Times）的采访中他谈到，他记得“四处走动，[思考着]，‘我要能把我现在的感觉捕捉保留下来就好了，而不是只是实实在在的感受到它。’ 在最近某集的播客节目《与杰夫·戈德史密斯（Jeff Goldsmith）一起问与答（The Q&amp;A with Jeff Goldsmith）》中，林克莱特回忆起他在那晚向赖豪普特提起这个拍电影的主意：


    |||Even as that experience was going on … I was like, “I’m gonna make a film about this.” And she was like, “What ‘this’? What’re you talking about?” And I was like, “Just this. This feeling. This thing that’s going on between us.”|||

    |||正当那种体验还在继续的时候，我就说：“我要把它拍成电影。”她说：“‘它’是什么？你在说什么啊？”然后我说：“它就是‘这个’，这个感觉，这个在我们之间流动的东西。”|||


But as the night came to an end, the paths of Linklater and Lehrhaupt began to diverge from the fictional storyline of Jesse (Ethan Hawke) and Céline (Julie Delpy). In fact, on The Q&amp;A, Linklater revealed that the ending of Before Sunrise was in part a response to what happened with him and Lehrhaupt. Unlike Jesse and Céline, who agree to reconvene in six months, the real-life young lovers exchanged numbers and tried to keep in touch while they were away. They called each other a few times, but it was “that long distance thing” that did them in. “It sort of did the fizzle,” he says, “So in the first movie that was a thing, the idea that they would intellectually kind of get beyond that and say ‘Well, we’re on different continents. What are the odds that it’s gonna work. Let’s just commit to this night.’ ”

但是，在那晚结束之后，林克莱特与赖豪普特的人生道路和虚构的故事情节中杰西（Jesse）（伊桑·霍克饰）与赛琳（Céline）（朱莉·德尔佩饰）两人的人生轨迹比起来，变得越来越大相径庭。实际上，在那个问与答播客节目上，林克莱特透露说，《爱在日出之前》的结局部分程度上是对发生在他和赖豪普特身上事情的一个回应。与杰西和赛琳两人约定6个月后再见不同的是，现实中的这两个年轻爱人互相交换了电话号码，并试图在他们分别期间保持联系。他们给对方打过几次电话，但&quot;远距离恋爱&quot;把他们搞的疲惫不堪，“我们的关系慢慢的就虎头蛇尾的结束了，”林克莱特接着说：“所以在第一部电影中也将它反映了出来，他们在理智上越过了它，说‘唉，我们生活在不同的大陆上，这段感情不太可能发展下去，我们就尽情投入这一个夜晚吧。’”


Linklater soon became involved with another woman, who “swept into [his] life ... and took over for about a year or so,” and he and Lehrhaupt never talked again. He did think that maybe “she would show up at a Before Sunrise screening or something.” In Before Sunset, Céline shows up at a reading of Jesse’s book This Time, which is based on their night together. “It would be so weird,” he said, in 2004. But she never did.

林克莱特不久就和另一个女人发展起了亲密的关系，这个女人“使他着迷不已，占据了他的生活……大约一年多，”之后，他和赖豪普特再没有交谈过。他确曾想过，或许“她会出现在《爱在日出之前》的一次放映时，或诸如此类的。”在《爱在日落之前》中，赛琳出现在杰西的书《这一次/这时光（This Time）》的读书会上，而那本书就是依据他们共处的那一晚而写的。“（她若出现在《爱在日出之前》的一次放映时，）那一定会感觉很怪异。”林克莱特在2004年这样说。但是，她从来没有出现过。


Linklater didn’t know then that Lehrhaupt had died in a motorcycle accident on May 9, 1994, before she reached her 25th birthday. Before Sunrise started filming a few weeks later. Linklater only learned of her death three years ago, when a friend of Lehrhaupt’s, who knew about the encounter, put it together and sent him a letter. “It was very sad,” Linklater told the Times. Ethan Hawke was similarly devastated when he heard it, though he reminded Linklater that if he hadn’t met her, then he never would have made these movies or met some of the people who worked on them with him. “Who knows how we reverberate through each other’s lives,” Linklater reflected in another interview, “But she’s an inspiration on this.”

那个时候，林克莱特并不知道赖豪普特已于1994年5月9日死在一场摩托车车祸中，那时还不到她25岁的生日。《爱在日出之前》则于几周后开始拍摄。林克莱特直到3年前才获悉她的死讯，一个知道他们二人那次相遇的赖豪普特的朋友，集合了这些消息，发了一封信给他。林克莱特告诉泰晤士报：“我感到非常悲伤。” 伊桑·霍克获悉这个消息的时候，也同样悲痛万分，不过他还是提醒林克莱特，如果他未曾遇见过她，那他也就不会创作出这些电影，以及遇见一些跟他一起，为这些电影而努力工作的人。林克莱特在另一个采访中深思反省道：“谁也不知道我们怎样在彼此的生命中交织回荡出声响，但她是这回荡声响的灵感。”


In this way, Linklater did find another way to make that feeling, that “thing in the air” they once had between them, last: He turned it into cinema.

就这样，林克莱特，他最终，还真是，找到了另一条创造那感觉的途径，那种他们曾经拥有的，回荡在他们之间的，“漂浮在空气里的东西”——他把它变成了电影。
      </影评>
<有用数>3897</有用数>
<没用数>43</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>银谷</作者>
<作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2013-07-17 21:16:12</时间>
<影评>
        这种话痨片的看点到底在哪里呢？我想这部电影最大的价值就是把我们生活中所期待的浪漫以及现在，将来要面对的所有困惑几乎都在电影的谈话中一一呈现，他们所谈论的，正是我们所期待的，他们所谈论的，也正是我们所困惑的。


当然电影终究不会给你一个明确的答案，就像本片结尾那样，你只有自己自己完完整整活过，爱过，期待过，争吵过，困惑过，痛苦过，只有经历这个过程后，你才会明白自己到底想拥有怎样的生活，才能最终与自己的人生和解。


全片由不同的谈话构成，他们究竟在谈论些什么？

我们一段一段来分析。



——机场的谈话


影片开头从杰西和儿子的谈话开始，几句话就清楚交代了杰西和前妻的关系处理的非常不好，儿子根本不想让他去看的独奏会表演，“为什么不让我来”“因为妈妈特别的恨你”包括后面杰西问儿子的“为什么她如此恨我？”儿子却意外表现的很轻松，只是无奈吐槽了一句，我觉得“她对daniel更加咬牙切齿”这句话很清楚的展现出儿子和她母亲的关系并不怎么样，而且这样一来，她母亲似乎是一个歇斯底里不断和男人关系处理的很糟糕的形象简直呼之欲出，变得立体起来。


当然最关键的是那句儿子拍了拍父亲的肩膀，很淡然的说了句：“你别想了，我自己会想办法的。”儿子虽小，却似乎已经长大成人，一个人能够很好的处理自己的生活，以及处理和母亲的关系。但是杰西看到儿子一个人过安检一个人登机的时候心里不免有些心酸，他感觉到自己似乎对儿子关心的太少了，亏欠太多了。他在思考着的今后和儿子多相处的问题（这直接导致了本片最大的戏剧冲突）




——车里的谈话


之后杰西回到了车上，旁边坐着席琳，后面两个可爱的小女儿正在酣然睡大觉，从谈话中我们知道杰西和席琳已经在一起了，并生了两年女儿，不过他们到底有没有结婚，我们并不清楚，（其实两个人没有结婚，只是在巴黎同居，后面影片才揭晓），席琳在观察着两个可爱的女儿，并用手机拍下她们睡觉时可爱的样子。


这些镜头交代了他们现在似乎“幸福”的生活，这时杰西从“孩子手上夺取食物”，他要了一个苹果，（注意这是一个伏笔）。


“ella,这就是你爸爸从你那儿抢食物的证据”，席琳把这个画面用照片拍了下来，这些举止都表现出他们一家人的其乐融融，温馨的气氛，影片的基调一扫刚才机场送行的苦闷，变得浪漫明快起来。之后两人分别谈论了自己的父母，包括那只叫“埃及艳后”小猫的故事，这些对话让我们觉得他们两人似乎已经是老夫老妻，聊一些自己最亲密的家常里短。


接着，杰西很高兴的和席琳分享儿子那句“这是他度过的最棒的一个夏天”，他以为这是父子共度的美好时光才会使儿子觉得是如此完美的夏天，但从席琳口中了解到是因为他儿子遇上了一个女孩，并且接了吻。


这段对话直接表现了席琳和杰西前妻的儿子的关系处理的比较融洽，也引出了刚才杰西在机场思考的一个问题，他觉得应该花多点时间陪陪儿子，他希望席琳一起去芝加哥，但是席琳显然不愿放弃自己现在的生活，和那个非常不错的工作机会，这点燃了他们关系裂痕的导火索，气氛变得尴尬，两个人争执的语调也开始上升，此时刚才的那个苹果起了作用，女儿醒了，问遗址到了没，席琳回答“等我们回来的时候再去看”，此时她用了“我们”，女儿似乎是他们两个关系的润滑剂，女儿接着问“我的苹果呢？”那只被父亲偷吃的苹果一下子把紧张的气氛变的缓和和温馨起来，但关于去芝加哥的问题还没有解决，这个裂痕已经在两个人心中慢慢变大。




——餐厅里的谈话


这是我除结尾外最喜欢的一段。一群人围坐在一起，一边享受着美食，一边惬意而随性的谈论着生活，这才是此类影片的基调啊。导演在这里安排的不同年龄段的情侣，有40（杰西和席琳）有50岁（对性热衷的男人，豁达的女人），70岁（邀请他们来做客的作家，和他好朋友的妻子，这里两个人的关系没有直接点名，可能是soulmate），20岁（通过年轻人用skype联系，然后讨论到虚拟性爱，再到人类和机器的关系，到有趣的小白鼠实验（讽刺享乐主义，娱乐至死的世界）


接着谈话又转到自我独立意识的确立，以及怎么留住男人？（让自己显得比他们愚蠢），这个地方席琳扮演的很多男人喜欢的那种胸大无脑的女人真是活灵活现，笑死了，台词也非常幽默和讽刺，最后引到隐性大男子主义，也就是前面在车里两个人谈论的不愉快的那部分，关于席琳要放弃一个不错的工作计划，放弃一切，去芝加哥帮他一起带那个孩子。


这是第二次把这个问题点出来，看的出来作为一个非常独立的女性，席琳显然对这个非常耿耿于怀，决裂的种子进一步发芽。此时话题被那个豁达的女人打断进而谈到那个关于男子气和女性特质的护士讯问醒来后病人的故事，讽刺男人的第一意识永远是性和自己，而女人则更多的是关注家庭。


接着那个20岁女生所说的关于她奶奶的故事是我喜欢和认同的：“不要在浪漫的爱情上消耗太多，友谊和工作太能带来更多的快乐。”当然这个故事与前面谈到的自我独立相呼应，强调一个人永远不能失去自我，双方都要学会照顾自己，并拥有自己独立的空间。这是一种最合适的两性关系。但为什么这样说呢？这直接引到了这个餐厅谈话最重要的一个观点，那个老太太的总结性发言：我们出现，我们又消失，我们对一些人是如此的重要，但最终我们都只是经过。所以人生终究是自己的，要了解别人，要从了解自己开始，要爱别人，也要先从爱自己开始。





——去酒店路上的谈话


席琳忽然意识到他们已经好久没这样好好聊天了，他们一直被家庭琐事缠绕着，困扰着，她进一步强调着女性独立意识的重要，强调女人绝不能被一辈子困在家里，（为最后的爆发做铺垫）杰西通过她祖母的去世，通过他们74年的婚姻，谈到他们两人98岁的未来，这几乎是无法想象，无法忍受的漫长过程，当然也是为最后那封穿越回来的信做铺垫。之后，他们来到了一个1000年的老教堂，这里主要是交代他们两人同居但没有结婚的事实，对他们来说，结婚就像一个童话故事，结婚有什么意义，结婚后就能一定像童话故事里的那样幸福吗？


这段谈话的最后他们来到了海边，在黄昏里坐在一起看太阳一点点慢慢消失，这是全片最美的地方，这里最后他们和解的场景是同一个地方，太阳如同他们的爱那样，不停的遭遇琐碎生活的摧残，“还在，还在，还在···最后··消失了？。”不过就像在餐厅里那位老太太说到那样，日落日升，明天太阳又会重新出现，爱不也是那样吗？





——酒店房间里的谈话


这一段超级真是漫长啊，由于那个电话，所有问题全都摊开来说了，席琳变的前所未有的歇斯底里和偏执，正如她说的那句“女人对永恒的探索，存在于自我牺牲的广袤花园中。”她不愿放弃那些希望，她现在原本属于一个人的生活正完完全全的被家庭吞噬，被家庭腐蚀，她不愿做那个被妥协的人。


而杰西也变得非理性了，那么多年了，到现在才明白自己对孩子的缺失吗？现在提出去芝加哥陪孩子的建议显然是没有必要的，孩子已经大了，而且是个不错的孩子，他有自己的生活，以及处理人生中问题的方法，这样冒然去，不仅丢掉了自己幸苦建立的生活，对于孩子来说搞不好也是一种额外的负担。


两个人开始不停的翻老账，纠缠那些已经毫无意义的外遇，揭开不曾和对方说过的被家庭生活折磨的困苦。但最后杰西的那段话还是让我感动的，“我把整个人生都交给了你，我接受了你的全部，疯子的一面和光芒四射的一面，我会对你，对女儿，对我们共同创造的生活，负责到底。这一切都是因为，“我爱你。”




——午夜降临前的那段谈话


这一段真是神来之笔，有趣，浪漫而又温暖。直接把本片或者是整个三部曲拔高了一个层次。一切回到了原点，回到了最初他们相遇的那个1994年夏天，席琳遇见了那个会一路保护她，去亲近，陪伴她，努力逗她笑，忍受她那些脾气的人。那封信最让我感动的部分是当40岁的席琳失落，无奈的坐在那里，认为现在的自己糟糕透了的时候，却有个人对她说“席琳，我现在，再回头看，你正迈入人生最美好的年华，中间这些年，只不过比你12岁时略艰难些。”这一段是多么温暖和善意的鼓励啊。


兜兜转转，当他们经历过那么多后，才发现午夜之前陪伴着自己，坐在身边的依旧是那个人，

或许到这个时候，他们才会明白——生活就是这样，虽然有那么多不完美，但它真实。正因为这些争吵，这些自己曾以为的迈不过去的坎，这些最后的和解，才构成了他们真真切切要面对的有血有肉的生活。


或许此刻他们才懂得，



年轻时的浪漫最终还是会落到那些需要一起陪伴与相守的柴米油盐中。






”你觉得，那个直到80岁还念叨的那晚，会是今夜吗？“


”这个么，我们要迎接的必然是美妙的一夜。“


这个夜晚，也会属于看完电影，散落在世界任何一个角落的你。
      </影评>
<有用数>2319</有用数>
<没用数>24</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>ふふちゃん</作者>
<作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2013-06-28 09:11:19</时间>
<影评>
        本文有剧透

虽然本片没什么“剧情”可谈，但是想要保持新鲜感的话还是慎入吧

凭回忆写，想到哪里，写到哪里

前两部也好久没重温了，有出入的话欢迎指正


关于Jesse的儿子，看的时候腹诽了一下为啥某人不利用自家资源让他家那位小孩来客串，你看人家波兰斯基就把自家小儿子拉出来客串了。。。好吧这个只是个人私心并不重要

在第二部里面Jesse提到儿子的时候，说他的名字叫Hank，然后在末尾的字幕，儿子的名字也叫Hank，但是全片提到儿子的时候，他一直叫Henry •﹏•


一家人在便利店买东西的时候，Celine用法语招呼女儿买东西，然后Jesse状似迷糊的用英文跟Celine确认，这里继续腹诽，Ethan Hawke的法语其实说得很好，而且他说法语的时候声音跟说英语的时候不太一样，有种带着诱惑的性感在里面，导演不给大家福利啊！

Jesse跟另外俩男人坐在院子里说他的书的场景，顺带提到了他写的第二本书，然后被问说他跟Celine是不是真的像书里写的那样很激烈的OOXX了。在第二部里面，Jesse说起他关于维也纳之夜的那本书，说原本的结局是俩人重逢了然后OOXX得昏天黑地然后分手了，但是出版社不喜欢这个结局，Celine说她更喜欢这个。嗯，总之他俩激烈的OOXX了这件事不仅成真了还终于写书出版了

俩人从机场开车回去朋友家，后座俩姑娘睡得昏天黑地错过了遗迹，Celine先嘲笑了一下Jesse说回头去机场的时候再说的借口，回头等俩闺女醒了，又把Jesse的话重复了一遍，这里看得我一口水喷出来，类似的事情一直发生在我爹妈身上，我就是那被爹妈忽悠的闺女

两个人说到初恋，Jesse说是你啊，Celine说得了吧，Jesse说我说的是真爱又不是X经验。这俩95年在维也纳下车跳到轻轨上坐在最后一排，Jesse问的就是Celine的第一次经验，而Celine问的是Jesse有没有爱过，Jesse回答得很随便，并且以描述自己的第一次作结。所以我决定相信Jesse真心相爱的第一个人就是Celine了

饭桌上一对年轻的异地恋情侣说起他们的相遇，说到女生当时在演莎翁的话剧冬日故事，之前Ethan Hawke在伦敦跟Sam Mendez合作Bridge project的时候，演的就是莎翁的冬日故事

还是那对年轻情侣，他们说分开之后靠Skype保持联系。要是94年的时候Skype啦Facebook啦就很流行了，还会有6个月之后的今天在这里重逢这样的约定吗？不同的时代有不同的生活方式，恋爱亦然

Jesse在海边看着孩子玩要他们别漂太远，绝逼本色演出，顺便一提，他说儿子几乎不会玩棒球的时候，这段剧本绝逼也是他写的。真实生活中他会拖家带口的去玩抛接球游戏，他儿子玩的可好了。Jesse说儿子上高中了希望更多的陪陪儿子，Ethan Hawke跟Uma离婚之后为了孩子他俩曾很长一段时间内都住在一条街的一头一尾

Celine说Jesse跟她的前任们一样都想把她变成保姆，04年的巴黎Celine哭着跟Jesse说她的前任们都跟她说谢谢你让我知道了什么是爱情然后跟别人结婚了

Celine全情投入的照顾双胞胎女儿以至于偶尔有点紧张过头，抱怨Jesse这爹当的太容易了基本上没帮什么忙。04年的巴黎Jesse问她有没有结婚生子她开玩笑说自己三天前把孩子忘在了汽车里。顺便一提Ethan Hawke其实很会带孩子但是的确不是那种紧张型的老爹，自家女儿对着镜子cos暮光之城最后从楼梯上摔下去了（当然没受伤就是了）被他当成笑话说了好久。。。

Celine嘲笑Jesse说他OOXX一直是一个套路。04年在巴黎她说他们在维也纳没有OOXX因为Jesse没有带套套（当然了她这是在傲娇）。是说我立刻八卦的怀疑了一下Jesse的。。。嗯，能力。。。

Celine跟Jesse终于有床戏了，虽然林克莱特在半梦半醒之间里面设计了这俩滚床单聊天的场景，哦其实日出里面有一个远景镜头写意的表达了一下来着。说起来好久没看过Julie的裸体了。。。老了啊。。。是说这俩拍OOXX戏份的时候因为太熟所以感觉彼此感觉都很奇怪，都在心里辛苦忍笑orz

饭桌上老太太说她对丈夫的爱，说我们来来往往，成为某个特别的存在，但终究都不过是在这世上的passing through，95年的Celine对Jesse倾诉过她对于相遇的缘分有怎样的感激。曾经imdb上before sunrise的讨论区有一个长贴，叫做the one that gone away，还记得当年一边刷一边哭，好多关于缘分和错失的故事，可以太久远，已经找不到了

Celine说Jesse其实颇大男子主义总想要赢，维也纳的夜晚看手相的吉普赛人让Celine第一次说出了类似的话，说他好像一个没能吃到奶昔的小孩

Jesse装成时间旅者给Celine送了一封信，维也纳的夜晚他们佯装给好朋友打电话互诉情思。Jesse装模作样的念了一封情书，95年的他对于街头诗人的奶昔之诗不置可否。Jesse仍是那个带着几分玩世不恭的美国大男孩，Jesse也是一个懂得放下身段去哄爱人的成熟男人，所以18年过去，我仍是爱他

Jesse说，我给不了你童话，但是真爱，我就放这儿了。维也纳的夜晚，Celine说，午夜钟声敲响，我们都会变回南瓜。看，虽然午夜尚未降临，曾经那对浪漫得不食人间烟火的年轻人，早就陷入了柴米油盐，到头来，也不过是一对普通的中年南瓜。但那又怎样呢？平淡生活中一切的点滴，都是真爱的理由和真爱的结果啊

前两部电影，有好多我喜欢的台词，但是都敌不过第三部里，Jesse一句轻若鸿毛，却足以意味着整个世界的“I love you”，纵使被时光消磨了青春，被生活冲淡了激情，被各种争执疲惫了心灵，他仍然能毫不犹豫的说，我爱你

维也纳，他们且行且吻但不曾说爱。巴黎，他们小心试探更不能说爱。希腊，他们为了芝麻绿豆的小事争吵甚至翻脸，但是Jesse说，我爱你

所以，我相信，他们还会在一起，未来的56年


以下是来自评论的补充

Hank是Henry的昵称

维也纳的夜晚，Celine说她想当一个将军。希腊的小超市，她成为了自己家里真正的将军，而家里军衔最低的，是Jesse【有了孩子之后男人在家里比较没地位神马的。。。


很多人有感于最后Jesse放下身段哄Celine。其实，每次看到男人们苦恼说哄老婆没面子，老婆真的好难哄之类的话，我都很想吐槽，你们这群真蠢货，对于男人来说，哄一个真心爱你的女人，是对你来说最简单的事情之一了！
      </影评>
<有用数>1699</有用数>
<没用数>58</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>七七|烂柯人bot</作者>
<作者评分>4</作者评分>
<时间>2013-07-17 07:59:45</时间>
<影评>
        “十年一觉扬州梦”也好，“荒唐一炮十八年，依旧是不懂爱也不懂情”也罢，话唠爱情三部曲走过九年接一个九年，有人看见慈悲，有人看见残忍。杰西和席琳在维也纳邂逅，在巴黎重逢，在希腊度假争吵；电影外的Ethan Hawke和Julie Delpy走过20、30、40，男主却说“主角并不是我们，而是时间”。 

---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------


同一个导演，同一对男女主角，跨越十八年演绎同一个延续的故事。从圣丹斯电影节首映之后人们就开始的期待林克莱特这部新片《爱在午夜降临前》，准确地说，是期待知道继九年前杰西和席琳在巴黎重逢后怎么样了。

我必须为主创们的勇气鼓掌，顶着狗尾续貂的嫌疑，把故事的背景搬到了希腊，话唠的内容换成了柴米油盐，美男变大叔，文艺女青年也终有了肚腩和大屁股，岁月是把杀猪刀啊——人们趋之若鹜总不能就是为了此番感叹，而是在时光节节败退后，他们还在争吵，也还在相爱：杰西（Jessie）和美国的妻子离了婚，和席琳（Celine）生活在法国，并已育有一对双胞胎女儿；在希腊度过的这个假期，让他们婚姻中积累的矛盾一再浮现。不变的长镜头，不变的简洁流畅配乐，两个人不变的絮叨却大量留在了封闭的汽车内、昏暗的室内，即便是在开阔的希腊庄园里，同座的也有一众人，年轻小情侣坦言结婚了也可能离婚，老妇人说怀念亡夫却也抵挡不住记忆流失，两人听着他们说着的话，像惊见自己的前世今生。十八年前在火车上的相遇，她决定跟他下车，九年后他决定为她误飞机，一切都像是一场人生赌注，现在到了该清算的时候。

杰西曾说，这样想想，跳到十到二十年之后，你结婚了，只是你的婚姻不再有原来的激情，你开始责备你的丈夫，你想起你生活中遇到的所有小伙子，你想如果你当初选择其中一个的话，你现在会怎么样？我就是这些小伙子中的一个。我就在这里。你这样想，你通过时间旅行从那时回到现在，看看你失去的东西。当发现你没有失去任何东西，这对你与你丈夫会是一个极大的安慰。我与他一样是个失败者。没有上进心、无聊透顶。你作了正确的选择，你是幸福的——到如今杰西可能会说，我就知道，若不是你怀念的那个小伙子，我就会是那个你责备不已的丈夫！

席琳曾在情绪失控之下咆哮，可笑啊，我每一个以前的男友，他们都结婚了，之后他们打电话感谢我，教会了他们什么是爱，教会了他们去关心跟尊重女人！你知道吗，我真想杀了他们！他们为什么不向我求婚？我也许会拒绝，但至少他们也应该问我啊！——到如今席琳已经抱怨出口，我就知道，你们都会把我当保姆！

所以说赌注的结果就是输得一败涂地么？如果曾把它当成完美爱情赋予太多想象，大概也只能叹时间残忍。真相就是，艳遇之后还有艳遇，旧情之外还有旧情；真相就是，青年情侣吵完架滚一次床单就重归于好，中年夫妻裤子还没提上就能为一件琐事大打出手；多数担心已经成真，而有些话一再印证。范柳原，结婚了你倒是安稳了，那些情话都留给别人去说了？黄小仙，你从前的睿智都变成了毒舌，嘿你刻薄的样子真丑！席琳也不能免俗地问杰西，现在的你在火车上遇见我，还会叫我下车么——不用解释，我知道你当然不会，我也不会为你下车了嘛！

其实心里都明白吧，不管当初有多天雷动地火，结局无外两种：他日偶遇，唏嘘不已；或是修成正果，柴米油盐。如果不把这三部曲按时间顺序看，第二部在巴黎的重逢可以算前者，第三部中年危机则是后者，到底哪一种更可悲？反正杰西说，“我不想变成那种人，在52岁时离了婚，落着泪，承认从来就没有爱过自己的伴侣，感觉自己的生活好像完全被吸尘器吸走一样，一片空虚”。我相信在影院里哭得一塌糊涂的，大半不是祭奠浪漫爱情消失的，而是在这句话下妥妥中枪的。要什么可笑的完美爱情？导演林克莱特证明，完美的代价只能是在片尾遥遥致谢赖豪普特——那个他在现实里邂逅的女孩，早在第一部《Before Sunrise》开拍前死于一场摩托车事故中。

人们还是宁愿错，也不愿错过。变老很可怕，但至少和那个人在一起，这又是时间的慈悲处。所以两人吵翻了算旧账的时候，知道他们找小三、会旧爱，为家庭放弃理想，为彼此也都忍了下来，所以当席琳第三次摔门而去，抛下一句“我想我已经不爱你了”的时候，杰西还是在海边找到了她，用一封“来自未来陌生人”的信平抚了她：“我在努力逗你笑，如果你想要真正的爱情，这就是了。这是现实生活，不完美，但真实。”海浪轻轻拍打着脚下的岸，卷起岁月的浮沫，这就是人生吧，来不及保留就变了个样，没办法让时间停留在，某个最美的时刻，可杰西还肯编拙劣的童话，席琳也肯陪着一起入戏，像身后点点灯光，执着地照亮黑夜。

拿青春赌过明天之后，是用持久的理解和忍耐换来的一生。只要你心里还明白，年轻的时候我们站在当下设想未来的种种可能，年老的时候我们回到从前设想现在不同的生活，不过都是一种病。别当真。大胆承认长夜浪漫有尽时，激情褪去不如努力经营亲情，你如此脚踏实地，上帝会慷慨判决你拥有凡夫俗子的悲喜。


</影评>
<有用数>818</有用数>
<没用数>17</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>davekozg</作者>
<作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2012-11-04 03:30:18</时间>
<影评>
        USC Cinematic School Pre-Screening 05/13/2013 07:00PM映场后的Update



十八年，生活是不矫情的念想


一部原本可能只是略带实验性质的话唠电影系列却一不小心以九年一部的速度来到了18年后的今年。今年圣丹斯电影节后充满期待的五星电影《午夜之前》，在USC的点映看过之后，甚至超越了之前的期待，在这个看似窠臼话唠主题中完美地讲了一个满意可爱的故事。


十八年之后的Jessie和Celine这回来到希腊度过夏天的假期。两人已有了女儿，而Jessie和前妻的儿子都已经14岁。电影开始的长镜头里，身为父亲的Jessie异常窘迫地对在机场要登上回到芝加哥飞机的儿子Hank问这问那，不自然地不像一个四十多岁的父亲。回到车里，他告诉Celine，我觉得身为一个父亲，我没有在他从小长大的一段时间里完完全全地陪着他，他上了高中，上了大学之后就完全离开我了。就这样Jessie和Celine一路开车到了希腊的小镇，开始了他们的夏天之旅。


之所以不再继续讲述剧情，是因为作为这个系列的第三部，《午夜之前》很好地继承了前两部作品的风格，还是一部长镜头接着长镜头，背景配乐简单到极致却又恰到好处，风格不急不缓推进的舒服的话痨片，更多的值得玩味之处在对话和台词。十八年后，Celine由当年的non-for profit的公益工作开始考虑要不要去为政府工作，因为这次可能不一样（This one might be differnet），Jessie离了婚和Celine了女儿却一直觉得没能尽到一个好父亲的责任，没能够多在芝加哥陪陪自己的儿子Hank。这其实倒不见得是“向生活投降”这么简答的结论，而是可能随着年龄增长，他们和我们都学会了以更平和沉稳的态度去对待身边的人和事情。


比如在餐桌上和希腊有人们的对话的场景非常有趣。小年轻们说“不管怎么说，我们最终都是会break up，结了婚的最后还是会divorce的对吧？”，大家听后很无奈“你们太现实了吧”。Jessie和Celine就讲起了当年的相遇的故事（Celine这个地方的表演非常好玩）。而真正打动人的，是老奶奶讲得最后的故事：“我的丈夫已经去世了。当他还在的时候，睡觉时他总是把胳膊放在我的胸前，有时候我都没法顺利呼吸了，但我感到内心很平静很满足很安全”。他去世了我了之后，我觉得他真的就一点点消失掉了，我努力想要记着她的眼睛的颜色、嘴唇的形状、皮肤的触感，他的一切。但最后还是消失了。但时不时的他又出现在那里。有时候我抬头看天空中的云，突然一片散开了，他的脸出现了，随后又消失了。生活大概也是这个样子，我们一边出现，一边消失。我们对一些人很重要，但我们也匆匆而过（We appear and we disappear, and we&apos;re important to some, but we&apos;re just passing through）。


影片中的别具慧心的小段子比比皆是，而且这次完全不像前两部的讨论那么拘谨和认真，很值得观众慢慢细想。比如还是聚餐上讨论的中年女子说的小段子：“我的祖母是一个护士，专门在重症昏迷病人恢复醒来后告诉他们，你现在没事儿了，一切都会好的。所有的女患者醒来后第一反应就是问：我的丈夫儿子朋友们都还好么？所有的男患者，所有的，无一例外，问的都是：我的cock还好么？”。


如果说刚开始看这个片子，看到Jessie和Celine在十八年后衰老的样子还不禁有些伤感的话，随着情节对话的展开，观众还是能够慢慢自然接受时间留下的印记而心平气和地和剧中的他们一样接受时间带给他们的平静和淡定。影片结尾更加精妙，冲突大吵之后的两人坐在夜色下海边的桌椅边沮丧地争吵之后，生活变成了原来的样子，依然有趣，依然耐人寻味。


终于，时间最后留下的不再是让我们唏嘘的感慨，而是让我们心平气和坦然生活的动力。


PS：最后，Julie在这部片子里表演的尺度非常大。这片子起码PG13的rating了......(写完了之后几周查了一下，这片子评级居然是Rated R......)










————————————————————————————

圣丹斯电影节之后USC 05/13/2013点映之前的原评论

————————————————————————————



十年一觉扬州梦，说不上矫情的念想


话痨片1995年的《Before Sunrise》（《爱在黎明破晓前》）和2004年的《Before Sunset》（《爱在黄昏日落时》）系列，已经在希腊拍完第三部《Before Midnight》（《爱在午夜降临前》）。预计2013年上映，一个九年再加一个九年。的确至今已是八年。像这种一共两个演员，不停说话撑90分钟的片子，全看编剧的功力。结果前两部片子不少人的评价是“年轻时候看得汗毛都竖起来了......句句台词都让你觉得“我也是这么想”的电影”。这就有点儿像是这么多年来陪着你一起长大的朋友，和你慢慢变老。看着这种电影，听那些台词里面的想法，也是看自己这么些年的变化。1995年《Before Sunrise》上映的时候，Ethan Hawke时年25岁，Julie Delpy那时26岁。2004年的时候，分别是34岁和35岁，到现在43岁和44岁的两位又该说些什么，很是期待。


前两部的电影内容是“偷得浮生半日，换取相知一世”这样的情节，只是面对时间，好像多说什么都未免显得矫情与做作。欢愉短暂，快乐来临之时，你便知道很快消失，于是很努力认真地过着快乐时每一秒。结束之后，或者不再念想，或者偶尔拿出来自己看着笑笑。经年之前的无数美好和痛苦，每每觉得自己好像已经忘了，或者一个梦境，或者一个场景，或者一个声音一种味道，总是各种各样熟悉地提醒自己经历过的不论开心还是难过的一切。


王国维写《人间词话》，高中一年级的时候书店买了一本，书非常薄，小小一本，其中一句印象深刻“最是世间留不住，朱颜辞镜花辞树”，那时只觉优美对仗有意境，多年后再看，却只觉悲凉可惜。杜拉斯写的小说《情人》中的开篇如是写道：“我已经老了，有一天，在一处公共场所的大厅里，有一个男人向我走来。他主动介绍自己，他对我说：“我认识你，永远记得你。那时候你还很年轻，人人都说你美，现在，我是特为来告诉你，对我来说，我觉得现在你比年轻的时候更美，那时你是年轻女人，与你那时的面貌相比，我更爱你现在备受摧残的面容”。一位同学语&quot;所有的一切经历都是自己当初选择的结果，无论好坏，无论如何，怎样的结果，都是自己选择的结果。不管生活往下的展开如何，也都是自己的选择，自己都一并承担&quot;，这话挺不卑不亢，在时间面前刚刚好，人总是难抵抗生活的不仁慈，结果并非“也只能这样”随波逐流。


《Before Sunrise》片中Julie Delpy印象深刻的一段台词：“你之前提到过以后几年的光景，一对夫妻会开始厌恶对方，对彼此的一举一动都了如指掌因此而感到厌烦，我想我会有相反的发展，我对一个人越是了解就越是能真正的去爱他，他会梳某种头发，他会穿哪件T恤，他在某种场合一定会讲的故事，我相信那会是我爱一个人最真实的境界”


十年一觉扬州梦，梦境再美好或者再恐怖，醒了之后，总还是要接着走的。



______________________________________
      </影评>
<有用数>603</有用数>
<没用数>33</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>前夕</作者>
<作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2013-07-17 23:20:04</时间>
<影评>
        很喜歡那位老太太的獨白，錄于此：


Well, when I think of Corpileas, what I missed most about him is, the way he used to lie down next to me at night. 

Sometimes his arms would stretch along my chest and I could’t move, I even held my breath. 

But I felt safe, complete. 

And I miss the way he was whistling walking down the street. 

And every time I do something I think of what he would say: well it’s cold today, wear a scarf. 

But lately, I’ve been forgetting little things, it’s sort of fading... And... I’m starting to forget him. And it’s like...like losing him again. 

So sometimes I made myself remember him every detail of his face, the exact color of his eyes, his lips, his teeth; the texture of his skin, his hair. But it was all gone by the time he went. 

And sometimes...not always but sometimes, I can actually see him. 

It’s as if a cloud moves away and there he is, I could almost touch him. But then, Doria, well, rushes in and he vanishes again. 

Well I did this every morning, when the sun was not too bright outside. The sun, somehow makes him vanish. 

Yes he appears, he disappears, like...sunrise, or sunset, or anything so ephemeral. 

Just like our life, hmm? We appear, and we disappear, and we are so important to some, but we are just... passing through.


...To passing through.
      </影评>
<有用数>572</有用数>
<没用数>5</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>望潮</作者>
<作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2013-05-14 17:34:45</时间>
<影评>
              《爱在日落黄昏时》的最后一幕，杰西盯着动情地弹吉他唱歌的塞丽娜时的那种眼神，我就知道他们只能在一起。They belong to each other.


       虽然我很爱看电影，但我不爱重复看电影，特别是当我还记得情节时。这次为了看《爱在午夜降临前》，我翻出很早以前看的《爱在黎明破晓前》和《爱在日落黄昏时》来看。一直知道周围很多朋友特别喜欢，但记忆中之前我对这两部电影没有特殊的印象，事实证明有些电影真的是要到了一定的年龄，或者有了一定的生活阅历会更容易获得共鸣。这三部《爱在》系列就是值得一看再看的电影，人生的不同阶段能看出不同的心情、不同的收获。

      《爱在午夜降临前》承袭了前两部的风格，长镜头、多对白、朴实而生动无比的表演、大特写的喜怒哀乐，像罗杰伊伯特评论的那样非常贴近真实生活，仿佛用无形的镜头记录下每时每刻的点点滴滴。我觉得这个系列电影之所以受那么多人的喜欢，是不是因为在你的生活中，都或多或少都说过和片中相同的对白，或者主角走过欧洲大街小巷时偶然谈论起了那些你花大把时间思考过，但还未来得及与任何人交流过的命题？除了这些，我最喜欢听杰西讲他构想的小说中的人物，无论如何天马行空，都有其现实意义，是某些世间凡夫的夸张版——持续经历déjà vu的女人，有人脸识别障碍的男人，有过目不忘人脸能力的人…他们的故事都可以拍成一部电影。

       男女主角的表演依旧那么自然，像极了相处了十几年的夫妻。他们并肩走着的时候，塞琳娜随手一指路边的山羊那一幕让我突然就想起《爱在黎明破晓前》里她也是随手一指草地里的小兔，如此生活化，但一举一动又个性化标签明显。朱丽·德尔比太惹人喜爱了，几次戏中戏实在精彩，还奉献了大尺度表演，很诧异为什么她一直没有得到一些有分量的表演奖提名呢。杰西的儿子也打了一手好酱油，我依稀还能看见他可爱的表情。

       从台词到情节，可回味的太多，可反复琢磨的也太多，每个人都能在影片中找到最喜欢、最能引发感慨的台词。看《爱在午夜降临前》时，虽然很多人在观影过程中不断大笑，但在我眼中，这个故事就是人间悲剧。不是伤感、悲观的那一种，而是相对于偶然的人间喜剧来说的一种永恒的挣扎和我们都必须生活其中的现实。影片所谓的高潮部分的争吵，是我在大银幕上看到过的最真实琐碎又趣意盎然的争吵了。但要说起争吵结局，有人可能会说导致俩人争吵的问题根本没有解决，但这个问题解决了还会有别的问题出现。两个人在一起，就算再浪漫，再两情相悦、再如何默契都还是会在生活的各个层面上出现分歧，所谓男权主义、女权主义，你的误解，我的责任……永远不会出现一个圆满的大结局。到这里，或许并不需要一个解决方案——留在巴黎还是搬回芝加哥，只要爱情还在。在希腊的爱琴海边，看着塞丽娜再次顽皮地向杰西询问时光机是如何运作地，我开始相信或许并不是每一份爱都会随着时光和现实的复杂而消磨殆尽；我也相信就像她在第一部电影里说的那样，随着年龄的增长，自己的真性情其实不会改变。

       从故事结构上看，《爱在午夜降临前》其实是和前两部非常不一样的电影。如果你连着看这三部的话，会很有意思的发现杰西和塞琳娜谈论的很多东西都成为了现实，害怕发生的事无法避免，暧昧不在，浪漫减淡，你会忍不住去想现在还只是在一起了十八年，再往后呢？那就看演员还愿不愿意拍了，故事肯定是有得讲的，而我们观众是肯定会买帐的。无论如何，十年二十年后，我还要一遍遍地看《爱在午夜降临前》，相信到时候会更加有共鸣，更能欣赏台词中的美。影片风格如此真实又戏剧化，这种结合到底是怎么做到的？
      </影评>
<有用数>342</有用数>
<没用数>11</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>寒谭鹤影</作者>
<作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2012-11-07 01:46:33</时间>
<影评>
        爱在日落余晖时 Before Sunset 中英文剧本



你认为这本书算自传式的吗？

Do you consider the bookto be autobiographical?



这个...

Well, I mean...



...isn&apos;t everything autobiographical?

...什么书不是自传式的呢？



I mean, we all see the worldthrough our own tiny keyhole, right?

我们都是通过自己那小小的钥匙孔看外面的世界，对吧？



I mean, I always thinkof Thomas Wolfe.

我是说，我总想起汤玛斯·沃尔夫说的



Have you ever seen that littleone-page &quot; Note to Reader&quot;...

你看过“天使望故乡”那本书前面那短短一页的“致读者”吗？



...in the frontof Look Homeward, Angel?

你知道我在说什么吧？


Well, you know what I&apos;m talking about?



Anyway, he says that we are the sumof all the moments of our lives...

总之，他说我们的生命就是由点点滴滴集合而成的



...而任何人坐下来，写出来的都不过是自己生命中的体验...

...and that anybody who sits down to writewill use the clay of their own life...



...that you can&apos;t avoid that.

...谁都无法回避



So when I look at my own life,you konw I have to admit, right, that l--

所以当我审视我的人生，我必须得承认，我发现...



I&apos;ve never been around a bunch of gunsor violence, you know, not really.

我从来没有经历过枪林弹雨或是暴力事件，起码没真正体验过



No political intrigueor a helicopter crash, right?

没有什么政治阴谋，也没什么直升机失事



But my life, from my own point of view,has been full of drama, right?

但是我的人生，从我个人观点来看仍然是富有戏剧性的



And so I thought,if I could write a book...

于是我想也许我也能写本书...



...记录下我见到某人时的感觉

...that could capture what it&apos;s liketo really meet somebody--



One of the most exciting thingsthat&apos;s happened to me...

我是说，我经历过的最刺激的事情之一



...就是真正和某人见面，让两个人心灵相通

...is to meet somebody,make that connection.



而如果我能把它表现出来你明白吗，抓住那一刻的感觉...

And if I could make that valuable,you know, to capture that...



...那就是我的写作意图了，亦或者....

...that would be the attempt, or....



你满意我的回答吗？

Did I answer your question?



我干脆就直说吧...

I&apos;ll try to be more specific.



我在火车上遇见一个年轻的法国女郎

Was there ever a French young womanon a train you met...



...and spent an evening with?

并和她共度良宵



See, to me, that.... I mean...

这个，对我来说...我是说...



-...that&apos;s not important, you know?-So that&apos;s a yes?

- ...这并不重要，你懂吗？- 就是说的确有了？



All right, since I&apos;m in France and thisis the last stop of my book tour, yes.

好吧，既然我人在法国，这又是我签名售书的最后一站，那就算有吧



Thank you.

谢谢



Mr. Wallace, the book endson an ambiguous note.

华莱士先生，这本书的结尾给我们留下了悬念



我们不知道

We don&apos;t know.



Do you think they get back togetherin six months...

你认为他们六个月之后会重聚吗？



...Iike they promise each other?

就像他们彼此承诺的那样？



Like they promised?

像他们保证的？



I think how you answer that,you know, is....

我认为这个问题实际上是，是个....



It&apos;s a good test, right,if you&apos;re a romantic or a cynic.

是个很好的测试，看看你到底是喜欢浪漫还是对它嗤之以鼻



Right? I mean, you thinkthey get back together, right?

我是说，你认为他们会重聚的，对吧？



-You don&apos;t, for sure.-No.

- 显然你并不这么认为- 是的



And you hope they do,but you&apos;re not sure.

还是你希望他们会不过你无法肯定



-That&apos;s why you&apos;re asking the question.-Do you think they get back together?

- 所以你才问这个问题- 你认为他们会重聚吗？



I mean, did you in real life?

我是说你们重聚了吗？在现实生活中？



现实生活中...？

Did I in real--?



Look, in the wordsof my grandfather, okay:

要用我祖父的话来说啊



天晓得会不会

&quot;To answer that would takethe piss out of the whole thing.&quot;



我们的时间只够问最后一个问题了

We just have the timefor one last question.



你下一本书将是什么？

What is your next book?



我不知道，老兄，我真的不知道...

I don&apos;t know, man. I don&apos;t know.



I&apos;ve been....I&apos;ve been thinking about this....

我一直...一直在考虑这个构思...



我总是想写本书...

Well, I always kind of wantedto write a book...



...that all took placewithin the space of a pop song.

...一切都发生在一首流行歌曲那么长时间内



总共大概3到4分钟吧

Like three or four minutes long,the whole thing.



整个故事大概是说有个男人...

The story, the idea,is that there&apos;s this guy, right...



...他非常的沮丧，因为...

...and he&apos;s totally depressed.



他最大的梦想就是拥有一段轰轰烈烈的爱情，一次冒险...

His great dream was to be a lover,an adventurer, you know...



...riding motorcyclesthrough South America.

...比如开着摩托周游南美



但是事实上他只是坐在大理石桌前吃着龙虾

And instead he&apos;s sittingat a marble table eating lobster.



他有份不错的工作，妻子也很漂亮

He&apos;s got a good job anda beautiful wife, right, but that--



他应有尽有，但是这并不是他真正想要的...

Everything that he needs.But that doesn&apos;t matter...



...because what he wantsis to fight for meaning.

...因为他真正想要的是为某种理想而战



你明白吗，快乐来自于过程

You know? Happinessis in the doing, right?



而不是因为你得到了你想要的东西

Not in the getting what you want.



总之，他坐在那里，突然间...

So he&apos;s sitting there,and just that second...



...his little 5-year-old daughterhops up on the table.

...他五岁的小女儿跳上了桌子



And he knows that she shouldget down, because she could get hurt.

他知道她该下来，因为她可能会受伤



But she&apos;s dancing to this pop songin a summer dress.

但是她正穿着夏日的裙子随着那首歌翩翩起舞



And he looks down...

然后一晃眼



...and all of a sudden, he&apos;s 1 6.

...突然间，他回到了十六岁



他的高中女友正送他回家

And his high-school sweetheartis dropping him off at home.



And they just lost their virginity,and she loves him...

而他们刚刚度过了他们的初夜她很爱他...



...而汽车收音机里里播放着的是同样的一首曲子

...and the same song is playingon the car radio.



然后她爬上了车顶，开始在那里跳舞

And she climbs up and starts dancingon the roof of the car.



这一下，他开始很担心她！

And now he&apos;s worried about her.



她很美，表情也竟然和她女儿一模一样

And she&apos;s beautiful, with a facialexpression just like his daughter&apos;s.



In fact, maybe that&apos;s whyhe even likes her.

事实上，这可能就是他为什么会喜欢她的原因



你懂吗，他知道他并不是身处回忆之中...

You see, he knows he&apos;s notremembering this dance...



...he&apos;s there. He&apos;s there,in both moments, simultaneously.

...而是他就在那里，他同时出现在人生的两个场景之中



And just for an instant,all his life is just folding in on itself.

就在这一瞬间，他全部的人生好像都交汇到了一起



对他来说，时间明显是个谎言

And it&apos;s obvious to himthat time is a lie.



因为那一刻将一直延伸下去...

That it&apos;s all happening all the time...



..而且.每个时刻之内都包含着另一个时刻...

...and inside every momentis another moment...



...all happening simultaneously.

...一切的一切，都发生在同一瞬间



总之，这就是我大概的想法，总之

Anyway, that&apos;s kind of the idea.Anyway.



我们的作者很快就得去机场了...

Our author has to be goingto the airport soon...



...那么，谢谢各位今天下午光临

...so thank you all very muchfor coming over this afternoon.



And a special thanks to Mr. Wallacefor being with us.

尤其要感谢华莱士先生和我们共度了这么美好的一个下午



谢谢，谢谢

Thank you. Thank you.



希望你出下本书的时候我们还能在这见到你！

We hope to see you here againwith your next book.



Merci a toutes et a tousqu&apos;etre venus.

（法语）感谢大家光临


Comme vous voyez y a du champagne,y a des petites choses a gagnoter,


（法语）我们为大家准备了香槟和一些小点心


donc servez vous.


（法语）请尽情享受吧

谢谢各位，我必须在几点之前去机场？


Thank you all. How much longerbefore I have to go to the airport?




哦，你必须在七点半之前离开？

Oh, you should leave at 7:30--



- 最迟七点半！- 好

-Seven-thirty at the very latest.-Okay.



-Hi.-Hello.

- 嗨- 你好



-How are you?-Good, and you?

- 你还好吗？- 很好，你呢？



I&apos;m good, yeah, I&apos;m great. I&apos;m....

挺好，是的，我很好，我...



你愿意...我是说...去喝杯咖啡什么的吗？

Do you wanna, maybe,get a cup of coffee?



Didn&apos;t he just sayyou have a plane to catch?

他不是说你要赶飞机吗？



Yeah. But, I mean, I have a little time.

是啊...不过时间还早



-Okay.-Yeah? All right, well, let me....

- 那好吧- 好吗？好，那，让我....



I&apos;ll meet you outside. Okay.

我在外面等你



我出去一下，喝杯咖啡

Excuse me. I&apos;m just gonna goget a cup of coffee.



- 我七点一刻回来- 这些书你都签了名吗？

-I&apos;ll be back at 7:1 5.-Did you sign all these?



- 是的，我肯定签了- 拿着你的司机菲利普的名片...

-Yeah, I sure did.-Get your driver Philippe&apos;s card...



...so you can call his cellif you&apos;re running late.

...这样你要是晚了，就用手机给他打电话



We&apos;ll put your bags in the carso you&apos;re not late.

我们会把你的包放在车里这样你就不会晚了



-All right, thanks for everything.-Thank you.

- 好的，谢谢你- （法语）非常感谢



谁是菲利普？

Which one&apos;s Philippe?


Philippe, passe lui ta carte pourqu&apos;il forme ta numero portable.

（法语）菲利普，把你的名片给他，上面有你的手机号码



Merci.


（法语）谢谢



-I can&apos;t believe you&apos;re here.-I live here in Paris.

- 真难以置信你会在这里- 我就住在巴黎



Are you sure you don&apos;t have to stay?You&apos;re not supposed to talk more?

你真的不用多呆几天吗？你不用再和谁谈什么了吗？



不，他们都开始烦我了我昨晚整夜都在这里

They&apos;re sick of me.I spent the night here.



- 哦，真的吗？- 是啊，他们楼上有间阁楼

-You did?-Yeah, they got a loft upstairs.



- 你怎么样？这感觉真奇怪- 我很好

-How are you? This is so weird.-I&apos;m fine.



- 见到你真高兴！- 见到你真高兴！

-It&apos;s good to see you.-It&apos;s good to see you.



-So you want to go to a cafe?-Yeah.

- 那你想去喝杯咖啡吗？- 哦，当然



那好，那边不远有一家很不错

Okay. There&apos;s one a little furtherthat I like.



I thought I was gonna totally lose itin there when I first saw you.

我刚才见到你的时候我都快傻了



How did you knowI was gonna be here?

你怎么会知道我会来这的呢？



It&apos;s my favorite bookstore in Paris.You can sit down for hours and read.

这是我在巴黎最喜欢的书店了你可以坐在那里看一天书



I love it. There&apos;s fleas,but, you know....

我很喜欢这样，那儿是有跳蚤，不过，你知道的....



我知道，我简直感觉昨晚有只猫睡在我头上

I know. I think a cat slepton my head last night.



I saw your picture on the calendarabout a month ago...

我一个月前就书店日历上看到你的照片



...and that you were goingto be here.

知道你会来这里



It&apos;s funny, because I read an articleon your book...

有意思的是，我读了你的书，一小段而已



- 我有种朦朦胧胧的的亲切感- 朦朦胧胧？是吗？

-...and it sounded vaguely familiar.-Vaguely? Yeah.



是的，只不过是在见到你的照片之后才有的，所以...

But I didn&apos;t put it all togetheruntil I saw your photo. So....



你看过那书了吗？

Did you have a chance to read it?



Yes, l....

是的，我....



I was really, really surprised,as you can imagine.

你的书让我感到惊喜，你应该体会得到的



I mean, I had to read it twice, actually.

我是说，我对它爱不释手



-Yeah?-Yeah.

- 是吗？- 是的



Comme ci comme ca?

（法语）写得马马虎虎？


No, I liked it. It&apos;s very romantic.


不，我很喜欢，非常浪漫！



我平时不爱看类似的书但是你写的真好

I usually don&apos;t like that,but it&apos;s really well-written.



- 写的非常好，祝贺你！- 好吧，谢谢

-It&apos;s well-written. Congratulations.-All right. Thank you.



- 等等- 怎么啦？

-Wait.-What?



在我们出发前，我得问你...

Before we go anywhere,I have to ask you....



没问题，什么事？

Sure. What?



那年十二月，你去维也纳了吗？

Did you show up in Viennathat December?



- 呃，你去了吗？- 没有，我没能去成，但是...你去了吗？

-Did you?-No, I couldn&apos;t. But did you?



-I need to know. It&apos;s important to me.-Why, if you didn&apos;t?

- 我必须要知道，这对我很重要！- 为什么，既然你都没去？



Well, did you?

那，你去了吗？



No.

没有



哦，谢天谢地你没去！

Thank God you didn&apos;t.



- 哦，天啊- 谢天谢地你没去

-Oh, my God.-Thank God you didn&apos;t.



我是说，幸亏我没去，你也没去要是我们两个只有一个人去了...

Thank God I didn&apos;t and you didn&apos;t.If one of us had showed up alone...



-...that would have sucked.-I was so concerned.

- ...那简直是糟透了- 我知道，我知道，我一直担心这个



I felt horrible about not being there,but I couldn&apos;t. My grandma died...

我一直因为没去而内疚，但是我确实没法！我祖母那之前几天过世了



那天是她下葬的日子，十二月十六日

...and she was buried that day,December 1 6th.



- 她过世了？就是布达佩斯的那一位？- 是的，你还记得？

-The one in Budapest?-Yes. You remember that?



- 当然，我什么都记得- 噢，对了，你书中还提到了

-I remember everything.-Of course, it was in your book.



But anyway, I was about tofly to Vienna, you know...

总之，我的确想过去维也纳的



...and we heard the news about her,and of course I had to go to the funeral.

但是噩耗突然传来，我只能去参加葬礼了



Yeah, I&apos;m sorry to hear that.

是啊，听到这个真让人难过



I know. But you weren&apos;t there anyway.

我知道，反正你也没去...



Wait. Why weren&apos;t you there?

等等，你为什么没去？



I would have been thereif I could have. I made plans....

我要是能去的话一定会去的我定了计划，而且我...



你最好能找到个好一点的理由！

You better have a good reason.



怎么了？

What?



Oh, no.

哦，不！



No, you were there, weren&apos;t you?

你去那了，是吗？



Oh, no, that&apos;s terrible!

哦，不，真糟糕！



我知道，我笑了，不过我不是有意的！

I&apos;m laughing, but I don&apos;t mean it.



Did you hate me?You must&apos;ve hated me.

你当时生我气了吧，一定是的



- 你一直都在生我的气吧？一定是的- 没有

-Have you been hating me all this time?You have.-No.



-Yes, you have.-No.

- 有，你生我气了- 没有



But you can&apos;t hate me now, right?

但你现在不生气了，对吧？



- 我是说，我祖母...- 我没生你的气，又不是什么大事

-I mean, my grandma---I don&apos;t hate you. It&apos;s no big deal.



我大老远飞过去，你却放我的鸽子

I flew all the way over there,you blew the thing off.



于是我的人生自此一蹶不振不过，这又算什么呢

My life&apos;s been a big nosedive since,but it&apos;s not a problem.



- 我只是开玩笑，开玩笑- 别这么说，我真无法相信

-No, I&apos;m kidding.-Don&apos;t say that. I can&apos;t believe it.



You must have been so angrywith me. I&apos;m so sorry.

我一定是把你气疯了，我真抱歉



我真的很想去的，没什么比这个更重要了！

I really wanted to be there,more than anything in the world.



- 不开玩笑了，我发誓...- 你不能生气啊，我祖母...

-Honestly, I swear---You can&apos;t be angry, my grandmother--



我懂，我真的想到了，你大概就是被这种事情缠住了

I know. I honestly thought that somethinglike that might have happened.



I was definitely bummed, but....

我确实是非常失望，不过...



我感到最遗憾的还是因为我们没有交换电话号码，或者任何其他个人信息

Mostly I was mad we hadn&apos;t exchangedany phone numbers or any information.



That was so stupid.No way to get in touch.

瞧瞧我们干的傻事，没法彼此联系



-Nothing to go on.-I didn&apos;t know your last name.

- 对啊，没法继续下去了- 我甚至不知道你姓什么



Remember, we were both afraidif we started writing and calling...

记得吗，我们都担心如果我们开始通信，打电话...



- ...感觉会不会慢慢的就变淡了- 是啊，而且肯定不会慢慢变淡

-...that it would slowly fade out.-lt definitely wasn&apos;t a slow fade.



No, it sure wasn&apos;t.

肯定不会



We wanted to pick upwhere we left off.

我们都怀念曾经拥有的感觉



Which would have been fineif it had worked. Oh, well.

如果这份感觉可以永存的话那就再好不过了



So....

那么....



- 你在维也纳待了多久？- 就几天

-How long were you in Vienna, then?-Just a couple days.



Did you meet another girl?

你碰到其他女孩了吗？



Yeah, her name was Gretchenand she was amazing.

啊，是啊，她叫格蕾岑，她棒极了



The book&apos;s really a compositeof the two of you.

- 真的？- 是啊，事实上，那书是写你们两个的



真的吗？

No, I&apos;m kidding. You wouldn&apos;t believe--I even went back to the train station.


没这回事，我只是开玩笑！你不会相信的，我甚至还回到火车站过



I put up signs of my numberin the hotel in case you&apos;d been delayed.

我支了个牌子，写了我旅馆的电话号码，以免你来晚了找不到



- 我真是个笨蛋- 我们这边走，有人打电话给你吗？

-I was a total dork.-Let&apos;s go this way. Did you get any calls?



有几个妓女，拉皮条的

Just a couple hookerslooking for a gig.



哦，那真是糟，我是说，你指望让我说什么呢

No, it was awful, I mean,what do you want me to say?



哦，太让人伤心了，我真抱歉！

It&apos;s so sad. I&apos;m so sorry.



I walked around for a couple days.Eventually, I flew home.

我就那么转悠了几天，最后，就飞回去了



I owed my dad 2000 bucks...

还欠了我爸2000块



他可是警告我不要碰法国鸡

...who had warned meabout French chicks.



他怎么对你形容法国女人的？

What did he tell youabout French women?



没什么，他，他从来没有遇见过法国女人

Nothing. He&apos;s never metany French women.



He&apos;s never beeneast of the Mississippi.

他从来没有去过比密西西比河更东的地方



那你干嘛不加上一句，“六个月过去了，那个法国婊子还是没出现”

Why didn&apos;t you put, &quot;Six months later,the French bitch didn&apos;t show up&quot;?



不，可是我差点这么做了

No, but I did, I did.



- 你真的想过？- 是的，我是说，我让它看起来更有悬念

-You did?-Yeah. No. I made it more hopeful.



I wrote this fictional versionwhere you do show up.

我写了一段虚构的情节，说你最后出现了



- 哦，你怎么写的？- 呃...

-Oh, what happens?-Well....



What?

怎么了？



呃，我们整整做了十天爱，这还没完

We make love for about 1 0 days straight,that&apos;s one part of it.



-lnteresting. So the French slut, right?-Yeah, exactly.

- 哦，真有意思，一个法国荡妇...- 没错



It&apos;s just then they getto know each other better...

从那以后，他们开始了解对方



...and realize they don&apos;tget along at all.

然后他们意识到彼此并不合适



-I like that. It&apos;s more real.-My editor didn&apos;t think that way.

- 我喜欢这样，看起来更真实- 我的编辑可不这么想



谁都想相信爱情，为了畅销嘛，对吧？

Everyone wants to believe in love.It sells.



是啊，就是如此，所以...

Yeah, exactly, so....



就是说你一切都好，对吧？

So things are going well for you,right? I mean....



- 我是说，你的书是美国畅销书...- 只是本小小的畅销书

-Your book is a bestseller in the U.S.-It&apos;s a tiny bestseller.



- 哦，别谦虚啦...- 好吧，没错，理论上说，是的

-Oh, come on.-All right. Officially, yes.



Most people haven&apos;t read Moby Dick.Why should they read my book?

可大多数人连莫比·迪克的书都没读过又怎么会来读我的？



我也没读过莫比·迪克的书可是我就喜欢你的书，所以...

I haven&apos;t read Moby Dickand I liked your book.



-Thanks.-Even though...

- 谢谢- 即使...



...I thought you idealizedthe night of it.

我觉得你把那一晚描绘得太完美了



Come on, it&apos;s officially a fiction, right?

嘿，我说，这可是小说



- 我本来就得...- 我知道，我知道

-I&apos;m supposed to---I know, I know.



I know. I thought there were timeswhere you made me....

你知道，有些时候，你让我看起来...



呃，我是说她，不，还是我...算啦，管她是谁

Well, I mean, her, right?No, me. Okay, whatever.



-A little bit neurotic.-You are a bit like that, aren&apos;t you?

- 总之有点神经质！- 你确实有点啊，不是吗？



-You think I&apos;m neurotic?-No, no, no. Come on, I&apos;m kidding.

- 你认为我神经质？- 没有，这是个玩笑而已！



Where did I do that? I didn&apos;t do that.

我哪那么写了，我才没有呢



我这人就是这样的，你知道的...

Oh, maybe it&apos;s just me, you know....



读到一个故事，知道故事是根据自己来写的

Reading something, knowingthe character is storied based on you...



这既让人受宠若惊，也让人心神不宁

...it&apos;s both flattering and disturbingat the same time.



怎么会让人心神不宁的？

How is it disturbing?



I don&apos;t know. Just being partof someone else&apos;s memory.

我不知道，只是...成为他人记忆中的一部分



透过你的眼看到我自己

Seeing myself through your eyes.



你写了多久？

How long did it take you to write it?



Three or four years, on and off.

呃，三四年吧，时断时续的



Wow, that&apos;s a really long timeto be writing about one night.

哇，你花了那么长时间就为了写一个晚上发生的事情？



Yeah, I know. Tell you about it.

是啊，我知道，你说的没错



我总是认为你已经忘记我了

I always assumedyou had forgotten me.



没有，我心目中你的印象非常清晰

No, I had a pretty clear pictureof you in my mind.



-I have to tell you something. I just....-What?

- 我得告诉你件事情，我...- 怎么了？



I&apos;ve wanted to talk to you for so longthat now-- It&apos;s just surreal, you know?

这么久以来，我一直想和你聊天你知道吗，而现在...


- 是啊，我也是- 现在梦想成真了


我却觉得不知道该说什么了


I feel like everything should be--



How long do we have?Twenty minutes and 30 seconds?

我懂，我懂，我们还有多长时间？20分钟又30秒？



不，我们有的是时间我想多和你聊聊

We got more than that.I wanna know about you.



告诉我你在做什么？

Tell me, what are you doing?What are you up to?



Where to start? I work for Green Cross.It&apos;s an environmental organization.

呃，从哪开始呢...我为绿十字会工作，那是个环保组织



What are they all about?

他们是干嘛的？



这个嘛，基本上来说，我们会关注一些环境问题

We basically work on differentenvironment issues...



...from clean water todisarmament of chemical weapons.

比如净化水质，或者销毁化学武器什么的



International laws that dealwith the environment.

你懂吗，涉及环境的国际法什么的



- 那，你为他们做什么？- 我们走这边

-What do you do for them?-We&apos;re going this way.



很多事了

Different things.



比如去年，我在印度待了一阵在一间水处理工厂工作

Like, last year I was in lndia for quite a while,working on a water-treatment plant.



那里的棉纺工业是主要的污染源，所以...

Well, the cotton industry thereis a major source of pollution, so....



我是说，听起来你的确做了一些有意义的事情

I mean, it sounds like you&apos;re actuallydoing something.



Most people, myself included,just sit around and bitch.

大多数人，也包括我，只是...你知道吗，无所事事



You know, how America&apos;s consumingall the world&apos;s resources, SUVs suck...

美国消耗了世界上大多数资源，箱式轿车尤其如此



...global warming is real--

全球也在变暖...



很高兴你不是那种狂妄自大的美国人

I&apos;m relieved to hear you&apos;re not oneof those &quot;freedom fries&quot; Americans.



不过，你是怎么会去做这个的呢？

Hey, you know....But how&apos;d you get into that?



啊，我政治系毕了业那时我希望为政府工作

I came out of political science,hoping to work for the government.



- 而我确实也替他们干了一阵，哎，太糟了！- 不好吗？

-And I did for a little while. Terrible.-Not good?



是的，不好，我们这边走总之，我烦透了...

Yeah, no. anyway, I got really tired--Let&apos;s go this way.



Having this endless conversationwith friends...

... 与朋友无休止的讨论...



...about how the worldwas falling to pieces.

关于世界怎么会分裂成这样的问题



所以我意识到我真正想要做的

So I decided what I reallywanted to do was...



就是找到一些可以做好的事情，然后努力做好它们

...to find things that could be fixedand try to fix them, you know?



You know, I always thought you&apos;d bedoing something cool like that. I did.

我一直觉得你会做这种超酷的事情的



谢谢！不过我真的很幸运，能找到份自己喜欢的工作

Thanks. I just feel really, really luckyto be doing a job I like, you know?



Yeah.

是啊



你知道吗，事实上我曾经非常彷徨一会儿认为这个世界已经没救了...

I actually alternate in between thinkingeverything is irrevocably screwed up...



一会儿又认为很多时候还是有转机的

...and things might begetting better in ways.



转机？为什么要这么悲观呢？

Better? How could youpossibly say that?



这个嘛，我只是说，你明白吗，比如...

Well, I just mean, you know, like....



I know it sounds weird, but there arethings to be optimistic about.

我知道这听起来很奇怪，不过有些事情还是要从好的方面来看



Okay.... I know your book is selling,which is great, I&apos;m very happy for you.

好啦，我知道你的书畅销这非常好，我为你感到高兴，不过...



But let me break the news to you:The world is a mess right now.

让我告诉你真实的世界，好吗？世界现在是一团糟！



从西方世界的观点来看来说，世界的确在变好

From a Western view,things are getting a bit better.



我们正把工业重心转移到发展中国家那里我们能获得便宜的劳动力...

We&apos;re moving industry to developingnations where we can get cheap labor...



...而不去管任何环保法律军火工业蓬勃发展

...free of any environmental laws.The weapon industry is booming.



Five million people die a yearfrom preventable water disease.

每年有五百万人因为水质污染而死去而这些本来是可以避免的



告诉我，这样的世界还不够糟糕马？我没有生气，我没有生气

How is the world getting better?I&apos;m not angry, I&apos;m not angry.



不过，说吧，我想知道，我很有兴趣！

But come on, I want to know.I&apos;m interested.



好吧，我知道世界上有很多严重的问题

I realize that there are a lotof serious problems in the world.



-Okay. Thank you.-I mean, I don&apos;t even have...

- 太好了，谢谢你！- 我的意思是说



- 我在亚洲根本找不到出版商出我的书- 好啦

-...one publisher in the Asian market.-Okay. All right.



-Say stop.-What? Stop.

- 说“住嘴”！- 怎么啦？住嘴



Look, all I&apos;m saying is there&apos;s moreawareness. People are gonna fight back.

听我说，我想说的只是更多的人意识到这一点了，人们正在反击！



The world might be getting betterbecause people like you...

世界还是有可能变得更好的，因为更多像你这样的人...



...学会了说出自己的想法

...are educated and speaking out.



最起码的，那些环保问题

Even the very notion of conservation,environmental issues...



...weren&apos;t in the vocabularytill fairly recently.

最近才出现在词典里



而现在他们已经成了规范了，而最后他们都可能被实现

And they&apos;re becoming the norm andeventually might be what&apos;s expected.



我同意你的看法但是同时，这也很危险！

I agree with what you&apos;re saying,but at the same time it&apos;s dangerous.



An imperialist country can usethat kind of thinking...

帝国主义国家会用你这种观点...



...to justify their economic greed.

...来为他们经济上的巧取豪夺找到依据



Is there any particular imperialist countryyou have in mind, there, Frenchie?

你是在针对某一个帝国主义国家吧，法国佬？



- 没，没有- 没有吗？

-No, not really.-No?


-（法语）晚上好-（法语）晚上好


Bonsoir!


- 你愿意坐那边吗？- 当然，这真不错


-So you wanna sit over there?-Yeah, this is perfect.



哦，哇，可能我想说的只是...

Oh, wow. Maybe what I&apos;m saying is...



...世界的命运就像一个人的命运一样

...the world might be evolvingthe way a person evolves.



Like, I mean, me, for example.Am I getting worse?

我是说，比如我，我在退步了吗？



Am I improving? I don&apos;t know.When I was younger, I was healthier...

我在进步吗？我也不知道！当我更年轻的时候，我也更健康...



...but I was wracked with insecurity,you know?

...但是我充满了危机感，你懂吗？



Now I&apos;m older and my problemsare deeper...

现在，我变老了，遇到的问题也更复杂了



...but I&apos;m more equippedto handle them.

但是我也更知道怎么来处理它们了



So, what are your problems?

那么，你碰到什么问题了 ？



Right now I don&apos;t have any.I don&apos;t, you know? I&apos;m just...

现在？没事我没事，我只是...



...damn happy to be here.

...我真他妈高兴能在这！



我也一样

Me too.



那，你在巴黎待了多久了？

So how long have you been in Paris?



I got in last night.I&apos;ve done 1 0 cities in 1 2 days.

我昨晚才来12天之内我跑了10个城市



我累极了，所以我很高兴一切都结束了

I&apos;m wrecked. I&apos;m so glad it&apos;s over,you know?



I&apos;m tired of being a huckster.

我已经厌倦了这种推销



-Hi.-Hello.

- 嗨- 你好


（法语）请问您想要点什么？


Qu&apos;est que je vous sers?


What do you want?


你要点什么？



一杯咖啡...

A cup of coffee.



Un cafe et un citron presse,s&apos;il vous plait.

（法语）请给我来一杯咖啡和一片柠檬

天，我爱死这家咖啡馆了，我真希望美国也有这样的地方


God, I love this cafe. I wish they hadplaces like this in the U.S.




是啊，当我住那边的时候，我可想念咖啡馆了

Yeah, I missed cafeswhen I was living over there.



我是说，我是找到了一些我喜欢的地方，但是那...

I mean, I find a few placesI really liked, but there was--



- 你...你在美国呆过？- 是的，从...96年到99年

-You were living in the U.S.?-Yes, from &apos;96 to &apos;99.



我那时在纽约州立大学上学

I was studying at NYU.



Oh, God, don&apos;t tell me that, Celine.

哦，天啊，真难以相信，塞琳！



- 怎么了？- 没什么，只是...

-What?-No, it&apos;s just--



-Nothing, I mean, l---What?

- 没什么， 我是说我...- 怎么了



我从98年起就住在纽约了你懂吗，我们那时都在那里！

I&apos;ve been living in New York since &apos;98.We were there at the same time.



-ln New York?-Yeah.

- 纽约？- 是的



奇怪的是，事实上有几次我想到过可能会遇见你，

That&apos;s weird. It actually crossed my minda few times that I might run into you...



...but the odds are so slim, right? So....

...但是几率太低了，对吧？而且...



我那时都不知道你住哪个城市

I didn&apos;t even knowwhat city you were in.



- 你不是住德克萨斯吗？- 是的，没错，正是如此，我只是...

-Weren&apos;t you somewhere in Texas?-Yeah, yeah, definitely. I just--



我在那住了很久，我只是...你明白吗，到纽约换换环境

I was for a long time. I just,you know, wanted to try New York.



What brought you back here?

那你为什么回来了呢？



一是我读完了硕士

I had finished my master&apos;s, for one...



再来，我的签证到期了

...and no visa, no more visa.



And I was starting to get paranoid.All the violence in the medias:

而且，不算这些，我也开始有点妄想狂了媒体上那么多的暴力事件



黑帮啦，谋杀啦...尤其是那连环杀手

Gang violence, murders,especially serial killers....



而最后决定性的原因是...

But the final straw was...



...one night I heard some noiseon my fire escape...

..有天晚上我听到外面消防通道上有些动静



...so I called 91 1,and the cops came eventually.

于是我打了911，最后警察终于来了



- 大概三小时以后吧- 是啊，那时候我已经被先奸后杀了

-Like three hours later.-Yeah, after I had been raped and killed.



没有啦，来的只是一个男一女两个警察

No, but it was a manand a woman officer.



I was explaining what I had heard...

当那个女警到楼下挪警车的时候



...when the woman hadto go move the police car.

我向他解释我听到的声音



那时只有那个男警察和我一起

I was left alone with the male cop.



而他立刻问我是不是有枪...我说没有，我当然没有了

Right away he asked me if I had a gun,and I said, &quot;No, of course not.&quot;



And he told me, &quot;Well, you betterthink about getting one.

然后他对我说：“是吗，你最好考虑去买一把”



This is america, not France. Okay? &quot;

“这里是美国，不是法国”



And I said to him, &quot;l have no ideahow to shoot a gun...

然后我对他说，我完全不懂怎么开枪



...and I have no interestin firearms whatsoever.&quot;

而且，我对枪支也没有兴趣



于是他抽出他的枪，就像这样，然后他说：

And that&apos;s when he pulled out his gun,like this, and he went:



“总有一天，你会碰到这么个东西指着你的脸”

&quot;Well, one day, you&apos;re gonna havesomething like this in your face...



“如果你想活的长久点”

...and if you wanna have a long life...



...you&apos;re gonna have to choosebetween you or them.&quot;

“你就必须决定是不是要干掉他们”



然后他们就走了，而第二天早上，我就打电话申请持有枪支

And then they left. And the next morningI called for an application to get a gun.



让我拿把枪！我是说，那可真可怕...

Me with a gun.I mean, that&apos;s really scary.



但是然后我意识到有些事不对劲

But then I realizedsomething was wrong.



The way that cop had pulled his gun out,and everything, right?

那警察拔枪的举动，还有其他的事...



于是我取消了对枪的预订

So I canceled my demandfor the gun...



然后我打电话给警察局，想要对那个警察的行为进行申诉，但是...

...and I called the police and triedto complain about that cop.



- 发生什么事了？- 要填太多表了

-What happened with that?-lt was so much paperwork...



...and then I got scared,with my shitty student visa--

然后我就怕了，就凭我这种学生签证...



-Thought you&apos;d get deported?-Exactly. I gave up...

- 你认为你会被遣送出境- 没错！于是我放弃了...



...and forgot about the whole thing.

然后就忘记了整件事



-Well, I guess I never forgot.-Obviously.

- 其实，我想我永远也不会忘记的- 当然了



但是，我真的还是喜欢在那里的日子

But still, you know,I really enjoyed being there.



- 我怀念美国的很多事- 是吗，比如？

-There&apos;s lots of things I miss in the U.S.-Yeah? Like what?



恩...

Well....



The overall good moodpeople have there.

那里的人们通常都有好心情



比如，你知道的，即使有的时候胡乱问候

Like, even if it can bebullshit sometimes.



Like, &quot;How you doing? &quot; &quot;Great.&quot;&quot;How you doing? &quot; &quot;Great!&quot;

比如“你好吗？”“很好！”“你好吗？”“很好！”



&quot;Have a great day!&quot;

“祝你今天愉快！”



我也不知道，巴黎人的脾气可不好，你发现了吗？

I don&apos;t know. Parisians can beso grumpy. Have you noticed?



没有啊，每个人在我看来都很高兴啊

No, everybody seemspretty happy to me.



-They&apos;re not happy. No.-They&apos;re not happy?

- 他们总是不高兴...- 他们总是不高兴？



No, they are. I don&apos;t know. I justmean French men. They drive me nuts.

不是，他们也高兴，我不知道我说的只是法国男人，他们快把我逼疯了！



怎么回事？他们怎么了？

What is it? What about them?



Well, they&apos;re very nice.They&apos;re great, you know, to be around.

恩，他们很好，不深入接触的话非常好



They love food, wine,they&apos;re great cooks.

他们喜欢食物，酒他们做东西很好吃...



But I&apos;ve had really bad luck with them.

但是，不知道，可能我只是运气不好



怎么这么说？什么意思？

Why? What do you mean?



-Well, I guess they&apos;re not as---What?

- 我想他们不是那么...- 怎么？



What&apos;s the word?

怎么说呢



- 好色？他们不那么好色...- 好色？

-Horny? They&apos;re not as horny.-Horny?



等等，听我这么说怎样，对此，我以身为美国人而骄傲

Wait, listen to me on this one. In thatregard, I am proud to be an american.



And you should be.In that regard only.

你确实应该如此，仅对此一点



Merci.

（法语）谢谢


Have you ever spent timein Eastern Europe?


你去过东欧吗？



东欧？没，没有...谢谢

Eastern-- No, I don&apos;t.Thank you.



I remember as a teenagerI went to Warsaw...

我记得当我十多岁的时候我去过华沙



那时它还是共产主义的那一套

...when it was stilla strict communist regime.



-Which I don&apos;t approve of at all.-Sure you don&apos;t.

- 对此我是一点也不支持- 当然...



-No, I don&apos;t.-I&apos;m just kidding.

- 不是，我才没有...- 好啦，我只是开玩笑！



但是，不管怎样，我发现待在那里是件很有意思的事

But anyway, something aboutbeing there was very interesting.



仅仅几个星期之后我就有了改变

After a couple of weeks,something changed in me.



那座城市又阴郁又灰暗...

The city was quite gloomy and gray...



但是过了一阵以后，我头脑变的更清醒了

...but after a while,my brain seemed clearer.



我在日记上记录了更多的东西

I was writing morein my journal...



-...ideas I&apos;d never thought of before---Communist ideas?

- 很多我以前从来没有过的想法- 共产主义的想法？



- 听着，我可不是...- 对不起，我...

-Listen, I&apos;m not---I&apos;m sorry, l--



- 好吧- 继续！

-Okay.-Go on.



以后我要送你去俄国古拉格集中营

Okay. I&apos;ll send you to a gulag later.



No. But it took me a while to figure outwhy I felt so different.

只是，那花了我好一阵时间才搞清楚为什么那里让人感觉那么不同



One day, as I was walkingthrough the Jewish cemetery...

然后有一天，当我穿过一个犹太墓地的时候



我没想通为什么，但是我真的有所改变

...I don&apos;t know why,but it occurred to me there...



...I realized that I had spent the lasttwo weeks away from most of my habits.

我意识到过去的两个星期中我改掉了以前的大多数习惯



电视里说的是我听不懂的语言

TV was in a languageI didn&apos;t understand...



没什么好买的，也没什么广告

...there was nothing to buy,no advertisements anywhere...



所以，我能做的只有...

...so all I&apos;d been doing was...



到处逛，思考，然后写下来我的大脑好像在休息

...walk around, think, and write.My brain felt like it was at rest...



...free from the consuming frenzy.It was almost like a natural high.

没有了那种强烈的情绪就好像是自然的高潮一样



I felt so peaceful inside.No strange urge to be somewhere else...

我感觉内心格外平和没有什么奇怪的冲动要去什么地方



...to shop....

购物什么的



It could have seemedlike boredom at first...

一开始这样可能看起来很无聊



...but it became very, very soulful.

但是很快这就让人感到内心非常非常的充实



It was interesting, you know?

非常有意思，你知道吗？



Can you believe it was nine years agowe were walking around Vienna?

你能相信我们上一次漫步在维也纳是9年前的事吗？



- 九年？真难以想象- 对我来说就好像是两个月之前的事

-Nine years? No, that&apos;s impossible.-No, it was. It feels like two months.



但是那是94年夏天了

But it was summer &apos;94.



Do I look any different?

我看起来有什么不同吗？



有？

I do?



我得看你一丝不挂的样子才知道

I&apos;d have to see you naked.



-What?-I know, I&apos;m sorry.

- 什么？- 对不起...



你的发型变了，那时...

Your hair was different back then.It was like--



-It&apos;s the same-- Oh, down.-Yeah, take it down.

- 什么，一样的啊...- 把头发放下来，让我看看！



Down. Okay, it was down. Okay.

放下来，好吧，放下来了



好了

Well? Voila.



So?

怎么样？



Okay, come on. Tell me.

快点，告诉我



Skinnier, I think. A little thinner.

瘦了，我觉得，苗条了



你觉得我以前很胖？

Did you think I was fat before?



- 不是- 你肯定觉得我那时很胖

-No....-Yeah, you thought I was a fatty.



No, you thought I was a fatty. Youwrote a book about a fat French girl.

没错，你觉得我很胖，你的书写的是个法国胖妞！



-No, listen.-Oh, no.

- 哦，不要！- 好啦，说真的



你看起来漂亮极了！

Seriously, all right? You look beautiful.



Do I look any different?

那你觉得我有什么变化吗？



No. Not at all.Actually, you have this line.

没有什么...哦，事实上你这多了道皱纹



- 我知道- 看起来好像疤

-I know.-It&apos;s like a scar.



-A scar? Like a gunshot wound?-No, no, no. I like it. I&apos;m sorry.

- 疤？看起来像被枪打得吧？- 没有，没有，我挺喜欢的，对不起啦



有天我做了个有趣的...呃，不，恐怖的梦

I had this funny--Well, horrible dream the other day.



I was having this awful nightmarethat I was 32.

我做恶梦，梦见我有32岁了



And then I woke up,and I was 23. So relieved.

然后当我醒来的时候，我才只有23！我就放心了...



And then I woke up for real,and I was 32.

但是后来我真的从梦里醒来，发现我确实32了



-Shit, man. It happens.-Scary.

- 好可怕！- 是会有这种事的



Time goes faster and faster.Apparently, it&apos;s because...

时间越走越快，看上去，是因为...



...we don&apos;t renew synapses afterour 20s, so it&apos;s downhill from then on.

从20岁以后我们身体里的神经键就不再更新了于是，从那以后我们就开始走下坡路了



我喜欢变老，你懂吗，会感觉生活更...

I like getting older, you know?Life feels....



我不知道，好像感觉更直接好像我能欣赏更多东西了

I don&apos;t know, it feels more immediate.Like I can appreciate things more.



其实我也一样，我很喜欢

No, me too, actually. I really love it.



I was once...

我曾经是...



...a drummer in a band.

一个乐队里的鼓手



-You were?-Yeah. We were pretty good, actually.

- 真的？- 是啊，我们当时真的很棒



But the lead-singer guy, he was just soobsessed with us getting a record deal.

不过那个主唱，他整天就想着让我们能出唱片



我们整天谈的，想的就是参加更大的演出

It&apos;s all we talked about, thought about,getting bigger shows.



每时每刻都是为了将来的发展，而现在...

Everything was just focused onthe future all the time. And now...



...the band doesn&apos;t even exist anymore.

...乐队却已经不存在了



现在回顾那些我们参加了的表演

And looking backat the shows we did play...



...even rehearsing, it was justso much fun.

甚至哪怕只是排练都觉得那么有意思！



I just-- Now I&apos;d enjoy every minute of it.Could I have a drag of that?

现在我终于能享受那每一分钟了我能抽一口吗？



你的书出版了，这事不算小了

Well, your book has been published.That&apos;s a pretty big deal.



You&apos;ve been all around Europe.Are you enjoying every minute of it?

而且你巡回了整个欧洲来卖它你觉得能享受其中的每一分钟吗？



- 不太行...- 不太行？

-Not really.-Not really?



不行

No.



- 你还有烟吗？- 当然有

-Do you have another one of those?-Yes, of course.



给你

Here.



在我这行里，我见到很多人...哦，对不起...

In my field, I see these people that--Oh, sorry.



Come into it with big,idealist visions...

过于理想，好高骛远



...of becoming the new leaderthat will create a better world.

想要成为新的领袖，来创建更美好的世界



They enjoy the goal,but not the process.

他们乐于见到目标被实现，却对过程没兴趣！



-Right.-But the reality of it is...

- 是啊- 但事实上...



真正能改善世界的工作是日复一日的点滴进步

...the true work of improving thingsis in the little achievements.



-That&apos;s what you need to enjoy.-What do you mean, exactly?

- 这才是应该享受的事- 你具体指什么呢？



比如，我为一个组织工作这个组织在墨西哥帮助那里的村民

I was working for this organizationthat helped villages in Mexico.



他们关心的是怎么把铅笔

And their concerns was howto get the pencils...



...sent to the kidin those little country schools.

送到那些乡村小学的孩子手中



那不是什么重大的革命性的想法仅仅是铅笔而已！

It was not about big,revolutionary ideas. It was about pencils.



I see the people that do the real work,and what&apos;s really sad is that...

我见到过那些做实事的人很不幸的是...



...the people that arethe most giving, hardworking...

...那些最慷慨的，最勤劳的...



...也是最能让这个世界变得更好的人...

...and capable of makingthis world better...



...往往没什么野心不想成为什么领袖

...usually don&apos;t have the egoand ambition to be a leader.



They don&apos;t see any interestin superficial rewards.

他们对那些形式上的奖励没有兴趣



他们也不在乎自己的名字能不能上报纸

They don&apos;t care if their nameever appear in the press.



They actually enjoy the processof helping others.

他们只是享受着帮助人的那种过程



-They&apos;re in the moment.-Yeah, but that&apos;s so hard...

- 他们自得其乐- 是啊，不过那很难啊！



自得其乐，我是说，我感觉我好像...

...you know, to be in the moment.I mean, I feel like I&apos;m...



是被设计成那种对什么都不很满意的类型...

...designed to be slightly dissatisfiedwith everything, you know?



It&apos;s like always tryingto better my situation.

你懂吗，我是说，好像永远都在试图改善自己的现状一样



我满足了一种欲望就会刺激另一种欲望，懂吗？

I satisfy one desire,and it just agitates another.



然后我就想：都去他妈的吧欲望是生活的动力

And then I think, to hell with it, right?Desire&apos;s the fuel of life.



You know? Do you think it&apos;s true...

你认为这是真的吗？



...that if we never wanted anything,we&apos;d never be unhappy?

如果我们没有欲望，我们就会永远快乐？



我不知道，没有欲望，这难道不是抑郁症的一种表现吗？

I don&apos;t know. Not wanting anything,isn&apos;t that a symptom of depression?



没错，就是的，对吧？我是说，有欲望是种健康的表现，对吧？

Yeah, that is, right?I mean, it&apos;s healthy to desire, right?



Yeah. I don&apos;t know. It&apos;s what allthose Buddhist guys say, right?

是啊，我不知道，不过那些佛教徒都那么说，对吧？



从欲望中解脱出来，你就会发现...

Liberate yourself from desire,and you&apos;ll find...



- 你已经拥有你需要的一切- 是啊，不过当我想要拥有...

-...you already have everything you need.-But I feel alive...



...when I want something morethan basic survival needs.

那些不算基本生存需要的东西的时候我能感觉到自己是真实存活的



我是说，不管哪种欲望，比如想和谁亲热

Wanting, whether it&apos;s intimacywith another person...



...or a pair of shoes, is beautiful.

或是想要双新鞋，都很美...



我喜欢我们拥有无止境的欲望

I like that we have thoseever-renewing desires, you know?



Maybe it&apos;s this senseof entitlement.

也许那是一种有权享用的感觉



你懂吗，好像什么时候你觉得你配穿双新鞋

You know, like whenever you feel likeyou deserve that new pair of shoes?



It&apos;s okay to want things, as long as youaren&apos;t pissed off if you don&apos;t get them.

欲望本身不是坏事，只要你不要太在意得失就好



生活很辛苦，这也是顺理成章的事

Life&apos;s hard. It&apos;s supposed to be.



吃一堑，长一智，对吗？

If we didn&apos;t suffer, we wouldn&apos;tlearn a thing, you know?



So, what, are you Buddhist,or something?

那，你是佛教徒吗？



- 不是- 不是？为什么不是？

-No.-No? Why not?



I don&apos;t know. The same reason I don&apos;treally consider myself anything, really.

我不知道，出于同一原因，我不会让自己完全相信任何信仰



I decided a long time ago thatI was gonna be open to everything...

很久前我就决定我可以接受任何信念...



...but not buy into any oneand only belief system.

但是不会执迷于一种信仰



数年前，我曾经去过一所苦修派修道院

I went to this Trappist monasterya couple years ago.



- 苦修派？- 是的，天主教西多教派的

-Trappist?-Yeah, they&apos;re Catholic. Cistercian.



-Why did you do that?-Why? I&apos;d been doing some reading.

- 你为什么要去那- 为什么？可能就是去读些书吧



我觉得那很酷，你曾经和修士和修女生活在一起过吗？

Thought it&apos;d be cool. Have you everspent any time with monks or nuns?



-No. It&apos;s not really my style.-No?

- 没有，我可不想那样- 没有？



Well, I expected them to be allglowering and stern, but they weren&apos;t.

我本来以为他们都是神情肃穆严厉苛刻的，但是他们不是



They were quick to laugh,really easy to be around.

他们很容易就笑，非常好相处



Seriously, very attuned to everything,they were just--

真的，他们对一切都不排斥他们只是...



You know, they weren&apos;t tryingto hustle anybody.

你懂吗，他们不会打扰任何人



他们只是想平静的信奉天主生存，然后死去

They&apos;re trying to live and diein peace with God...



也或者他们信奉的是其他什么他们觉得永恒的东西

...or whatever part of themthey feel is eternal.



但是身处其间真的很舒服

It was just so refreshing to be around.



You realize that mostof the people that you meet...

你懂吗，你会发现你遇到的绝大多数人



都是想要过的更好

...are tryingto get somewhere better.



赚更多的钱啦赢得更多的尊敬啊，

They&apos;re trying to make more cash,get a little more respect...



让人们崇拜自己啊之类的太累了！

...have more people admire them.It&apos;s exhausting.



-No kidding.-And it&apos;s exhausting to be one yourself.

- 没错- 要是你自己也成为这样的人，真是太累了



There I am, right, you know,all greedy to be more spiritual.

我是说，我就是这样的，精神上很贪婪



我想变得更好，懂吗，这是你逃不脱的！

&quot;l want to be a better person,&quot;you know? You can&apos;t escape.



I had this boyfriend of mine many yearsago that wanted to be a Buddhist.

好多年前，我有个男友想做佛教徒



然后他去了亚洲，去瞻仰那里的寺院

So he went to Asia to visit someof those monasteries.



- 是啊，我也想过去那些地方- 那你应该去，我告诉你为什么

-I&apos;ve thought about doing that too.-Yeah, you should. I&apos;ll tell you why.



啊，他长得很帅每次他去那些寺院的时候

He was good-looking, and each timehe went to one of the monasteries...



都会有僧侣愿意替他口交

...a monk offered to suck his cock.



True story.

真的



好吧，最后都会变成这样，对吧？

It all comes down to that, doesn&apos;t it?



That&apos;s why I really admirewhat you&apos;re doing.

我是说，这就是为什么我很崇拜你做的事



-You know?-What do you mean? Sucking cock?

你什么意思，口交？



-No.-No? Wrong answer.

- 啊，不...- 不是？我猜错了？



No, I was gonna sayyou&apos;re not detached from life.

不是，我想说的是，你不是那种超然的人



You&apos;re putting your passion into action.

你做事很有激情



Well, I&apos;ll try.

这个嘛，起码我努力这样做



You know something?I&apos;m gonna be on planes...

你知道吗，我接下来8个小时会在机场



以及飞机上度过

...and in an airportfor the next eight hours....



I&apos;d just love to seea little bit more of Paris.

我很想再看看巴黎



- 我们能出去走走...- 好啊，好啊，我们走吧！

-Would you walk with me?-Yeah.



- 你介意吗？- 怎么会呢，很好啊！

-Do you mind?-That&apos;s great.



-Do you want to?-Let&apos;s do that. Yeah.

- 你想去吗？- 当然！



我们该付多少？4块5...

What do we owe here?Four-fifty?



No, I got it, I got a littleper diem going on here.

不用，不用，我有，我有



-This good, for a tip?-Yeah, that&apos;s fine.

- 这够付小费的了吗？- 恩，够了



- 只多不少！- 这个也留下吧

-That&apos;s more than enough.-Throw that in too.



- 好啦，周围有什么值得逛的吗？- 今天是减价日！

-ls there anywhere to go around here?-It&apos;s sales day today.



- 什么意思？- 今天巴黎什么东西都会减价

-What&apos;s that?-It&apos;s when everything&apos;s &quot;en solde&quot; in Paris.



It&apos;s twice a year.

每年两次



Au revoir!Merci!

（法语）再见，谢谢


Au revoir!


（法语）再见


All right, let&apos;s go shopping.


好啊，那我们去购物吧！



不，不，这主意不好我不想让你这样

No, no, no. That&apos;s a bad idea.I don&apos;t wanna inflict that on you.



那简直疯了，我们就去那个花园逛逛吧，那真的不错的

It&apos;s madness. Let&apos;s just goto this garden path. It&apos;s really nice.



All right. That soundsbetter than shopping, actually.

好啊，听起来其实比购物要好



Not that I wouldn&apos;t dowhatever you wanted.

我是说，我并不是不想陪你做你喜欢的事



Sometimes I don&apos;t even needto buy anything. I just get high...

其实有的时候我也不是需要什么东西



...on trying onand looking at things.

我只是想试穿，还有看那些商品，这让我很兴奋



这个嘛，苦修派僧侣会对你说...我们往这边走？

Is this where we&apos;re going?



-Yeah.-A therapist will tell you that&apos;s good.

- 是的！- 苦修派僧侣会对你说这很好



-Really? Are you ever in therapy?-Oh, no.

- 真的？ 你节食过吗？- 没有！



-Do I seem like I&apos;m in therapy?-I&apos;m kidding.

- 我看起来像在节食吗？- 我只是开玩笑



- 这对你的性障碍有帮助吗？- 我的性障碍？

-Does it help your sex problems?-My sex problems?



- 没有啦，我只是开玩笑- 比如呢？跟我说实话

-I&apos;m kidding.-Tell me the truth.



- 那天晚上我们不是挺好的？- 不，我是在开玩笑

-We didn&apos;t have any problems.-No, I&apos;m kidding.



- 我们根本就没有做爱- 这是个玩笑，对吧？

-We didn&apos;t even have sex.-That&apos;s a joke, right?



不是，我们确实没做爱！就是这么回事

No, we didn&apos;t.I mean, that was the whole thing.



- 可我们确实做了啊！- 没有，没有，我们没做！

-Of course we did.-No, no, no, we didn&apos;t.



你没有安全套，而我没有安全套从来不做爱

You didn&apos;t have a condomand I never have sex without one.



尤其是一夜情那种，我是说，我对于自己的健康非常在意，我不可能...

I&apos;m extremely paranoid.There&apos;s no way--



I find it scary that you don&apos;tremember what happened.

我觉得这太可怕了，你竟然不记得我们之间发生过什么



不，听我说

No, listen...



...I didn&apos;t write an entire book,but I kept a journal...

...我从来没写过一整本书但是我记日记...



...and I wrote the whole night in it.That&apos;s what I meant, you idealizing it.


好啦，听我说！我甚至记得我们用过的安全套是什么牌子的

All right, listen, I even rememberwhat brand of condom we used.



好啦，这太恶心啦，我不想听！

That&apos;s disgusting.I don&apos;t wanna hear it.



- 这有什么恶心的...- 没有啦

-That&apos;s not disgusting.-No.



好啦，等我回家，我会查我94年的日记不过我知道我是对的！

Okay, when I get home I&apos;ll check myjournal from &apos;94, but I know I&apos;m right.



-Wait a minute.-What?

- 等等...- 怎么了？



-Was it in the cemetery?-No.

- 那是在一个墓地发生的吗？- 不是...



不是的，我们是下午去那个墓地的

No, we went to the cemeteryin the afternoon.



It was in the park, very late at night.

应该是在一个公园里，深夜时分



-ln the park?-Wait a minute, wait a minute.

- 在公园里！- 等等...



I can&apos;t-- I can&apos;t....

我真不能...我没法...



Is it that forgettable? You reallydon&apos;t remember? In the park?

这事这么容易忘记吗？你真的不记得了？在公园里！



Okay. Wait a minute,I think you might be right--

好的，等等我想你可能是对的...



行啦，你在和我胡扯是不是

You&apos;re messing with me now.



- 没有- 你在和我胡扯吗？

-No.-Are you messing with me?



不是的，对不起！我觉得你...我是说，你是对的，这样可以了吧？

Okay. No, I&apos;m sorry. I think--I mean, you&apos;re right, okay?



有时我就是忘事

Sometimes I put things in drawersinside my head and forget about it.



It&apos;s less painful to put thingsaway than live with it.

我想有时忘记会让人少些痛苦！



What, so that night was, like,a sad memory for you?

什么，就是说那夜对你来说是段很难过的回忆罗？



I didn&apos;t mean that nightin particular.

不，我不是针对那一夜



I meant certain thingsare better forgotten.

我只是说有些事情还是忘了好



I remember that nightbetter than I do entire years.

那夜是我那一整年记的最清楚的一天



-Me too.-Really?

- 我也是- 真的吗？



Well, I thought I did.

呃，我觉得我是...



不过，可能我...可能我忘记那事是因为...

But maybe l-- Maybe I put it awaybecause of the fact that...



...my grandmother&apos;s funeral wasthe day we were supposed to meet.

...我祖母葬礼的那天就是我们约好再见的那天



对我来说那天挺难熬不过对你来说大概更糟

It was a tough day for me,but it must&apos;ve been worse for you.



It was unreal. I remember lookingat her dead body in the coffin...

感觉好像不真实，我还记得我看见她的遗体躺在棺材里



...at her beautiful hands, so warm,so sweet, that used to hold me...

她曾经总是用她美丽的手抱着我那么温暖，那么亲切...



但是棺材里的她和我记忆中的一点都不一样

...but nothing in that coffin resembledwhat I remembered of her.



All the warmth was gone.

所有的温暖都消逝了



然后我开始哭...我感觉很困惑，不知道

And then I was crying,so confused if I was crying...



...because I was never gonna see heragain or never gonna see you again....

我哭是因为不能再见到她了还是因为不能再见到你了



I&apos;m sorry. I&apos;m sorry to go on like this.I&apos;ve been a little down this week.

对不起， 我竟然变成这样这个星期我情绪都有点低落，我不知道...



- 为什么？- 我不知道，没什么，只是...

-Why?-I don&apos;t know. Nothing bad, just....



可能是因为读了你的书？

Reading your book, maybe?



No, but-- Thinking of how hopefulI was that summer and fall...

也不是，不过...想想那个夏天和秋天，我充满了希望



而自从那以后，好像就有点...

...and since then it&apos;s been kind of a....



I don&apos;t know.

我也不知道



回忆本来是非常美好的只要你能让过去的都过去

Memory is a wonderful thing ifyou don&apos;t have to deal with the past.



回忆本来是非常美好的只要你能让过去的都过去

&quot;Memory is wonderful if you don&apos;thave to deal with the past.&quot;



我能把这话贴到我车牌上吗？

Can I put thaton a bumper sticker?



If you wrote a book about our night,that&apos;s a good title.

你知道吗？要是你写一本关于我们的一夜情的书这是个不错的书名！



- 可能会是本完全不同的书- 是啊，不会涉及色情

-And it could be a total different book.-Yeah, there&apos;d be no sex scenes.



- 不过你知道吗？- 恩？

-But you know what?-What?



既然现在我们又见面了

Now that we&apos;ve met again...



我们可以改变我们那个12月16日的回忆

...we can change our memoryof that December 16.



那回忆将不再有是以悲剧结尾了，因为我们又见面了

It no longer has that sad endingof us never seeing each other again.



没错，我想回忆永远可以更改只要你还活着...

Right. I mean, I guess a memory&apos;snever finished as long as you&apos;re alive.



是啊，我知道，我有一段童年的回忆

Yeah, I know. I have this memoryfrom my childhood...



- 但是我最近意识到，这段回忆其实从未发生过- 是什么？

-...I realized recently never happened.-What?



Well, when I was 8 or 9,my mom was so paranoid...

这个，当我八九岁的时候我妈妈很担心



...when I was walking homefrom my piano lesson at night...

...怕我上完钢琴课以后一个人走回家会出事...



...她总是让我当心色迷迷的的老头给我糖果...

...she&apos;d warn me about dirty old mengiving me candies...



...然后给我看他们的鸡鸡

...and then showing me their pee-pees.



她总是这么说然后后来，你懂吗，我...

She was so obsessed with it that,later in life, you know...



...I had this image in my headthat this really happened.

...我头脑中就真的觉得这曾经发生过！



我甚至把做爱和回家联系到一起了

To the point that I even associated sexwith that walk home.



I mean, and sometimes,even now, when I&apos;m....

我是说，有时候，甚至是现在，当我...



When I&apos;m having sex, I see myselfwalking down that street.

当我做爱的时候，我都好像看见我自己在那街上走



I swear. It&apos;s so weird, right?

我发誓！非常奇怪，对吧？



-ls that street nearby? I mean, could--?-Could we? No.

- 呃，那条街离这近吗？我是说，能...- 不行



Very far.

非常远



你小的时候记日记吗？

Did you ever keep a journalwhen you were a kid?



恩，算是吧，有时记

Yeah. On and off, I guess.



很有意思的是，我有天读了...

It&apos;s funny, I read one of mine...



-...from &apos;83 the other day.-Yeah?

- 我83年的一本日记- 怎么了



And what really surprised me is...

让我惊奇的是



我那时的人生观和现在一样

...that I was dealing with lifethe same way I am now.



当然我那时更天真，更充满希望

I was much more hopeful and naive...



...不过内心深处对事情的感觉是完全一样的！

...but the core, and the way I wasfeeling things, is exactly the same.



It made me realizeI haven&apos;t changed much at all.

这让我意识到我其实没怎么变



I don&apos;t think anybody does.

是啊，谁不是这样的呢？



People don&apos;t want to admit it, but it&apos;slike we have these innate set points...

尽管人们都不愿意承认，但事实上我们...我们很多个性都是天生的



很少有什么后天发生的事能改变我们的性情

...and nothing much that happens to uschanges our disposition.



- 你是这么想的？- 是的

-You believe that?-I think so.



我曾经读过一些研究报告是关于那些赢了彩票的人...

I read this study where they followedpeople who&apos;d won the lottery...



...和截瘫的人的心态

...and people who&apos;d become paraplegics.



你会认为前一件事能让你欣喜若狂，后一件则让你简直想自杀

You&apos;d think one extreme is gonna makeyou euphoric and the other suicidal.



但是研究却表明，大概六个月之后

But the study shows that,after about six months...



只要人们习惯了他们的新处境

...as soon as people had gotten used totheir new situation...



-...they were, more or less, the same.-The same?

- 他们就和以前差不多一样了- 一样？



Yeah. Like, if they were basicallyan optimistic, jovial person...

恩，是的，如果他们本质上是乐观开朗的人



...they&apos;re now an optimistic, jovialperson in a wheelchair.

即使他们现在坐在了轮椅上，他们还是乐天派



If they&apos;re a petty, miserable asshole...

如果他们是见识短浅的笨家伙



就算他们有了卡迪拉克轿车，大房子游艇，他们还是见识短浅的笨蛋

...they&apos;re a petty, miserable assholewith a new Cadillac, a house and a boat.



就是说，哪怕有再多的幸运降临他们还是难以得到满足？

So I&apos;ll be forever depressedno matter what great things happen?



- 没错！- 好吧

-Definitely.-Great.



别开玩笑了，你现在郁闷吗？

No, come on, are you depressed now?



No, no, I&apos;m not depressed.

不，不，我不郁闷



不过有的时候我会担心当我走到生命尽头的时候...

But sometimes I worryI&apos;ll get to the end of my life...



-...feeling I haven&apos;t done all I wanted to.-Well, what do you want to do?

-...我会发现我想要做的事还没都做过- 哦，那你想要做什么？



I....

我....



I want to paint more,I want to play my guitar every day.

我想画更多的画我想每天弹吉他



I want to learn Chinese.I want to write more songs.

我想学中文我想写更多的歌...



There&apos;s so many things I want to do,and I end up doing not much.

我想做的事太多了但是最后却只干了没多少



All right, well, let me ask you this:Do you believe in ghosts or spirits?

好吧，那，让我问你这个问题：你相信，恩，比如鬼或者灵魂什么的吗？



呃，不信

No.



-No?-No.

- 不信？- 不信



-Okay, what about reincarnation?-Not at all.

- 好，那投胎呢？- 一点不信



-God?-No.

- 上帝呢？- 不信



- 好吧- 听起来挺惨的吧

-All right.-That sounds terrible. No, no, no.



But I don&apos;t want to be one of thosepeople that don&apos;t believe in any magic.

不过，同时呢，我不想变成那种不相信任何魔力的人



-So then, astrology?-Yes, of course!

- 你相信占星术- 没错！



-There we go.-That makes sense, right?

- 总算找到一样了- 我是说，这很有道理，对吧？



You&apos;re a Scorpio,I&apos;m a Sag, we get along.

你是天蝎，我是射手，所以我们合得来



No, no, no.

没有啦



There&apos;s an Einstein quoteI really, really like.

爱因斯坦说过一段话，我真的很喜欢



He said, &quot;lf you don&apos;t believein any kind of magic or mystery...

他说：“如果你不相信任何魔法和神话的话



-...you&apos;re basically as good as dead.&quot;-Yeah, I like that.

- 那你就和死人差不多了”- 是啊，我也喜欢这话



I&apos;ve always felt there was some kind ofmystical core to the universe.

我总是觉得茫茫宇宙中有些神秘的和谐



But, more recently, I&apos;ve started to thinkthat, me, my personality, whatever--

最近我在想有关我啊，我的性格之类的



我不能永远待在这里

That I don&apos;t have any permanentplace here, you know.



我们不会长生不老

In eternity or whatever, you know.



And the more I think that, I can&apos;t gothrough life saying this is no big deal.

我越想到这个，就越觉得不能浪费人生



This is it. This is actually happening.What do you think is interesting?

因为生命仅此一次任何事情，不管是有趣的



还是好笑的或者是重要的

What do you think is funny?What is important?



You know, every day&apos;s our last.

懂吗，每天都有可能是我们的最后一天



When I feel that way, I usuallycall my mom to tell her I love her.

我一想到这个，我就会打电话给我的妈妈说我有多爱她



- 是吗- 然后她就总问

-Yeah?-And she&apos;s always:



“你还好吧”“你不会得了癌症吧？你会去自杀吗？”

&quot;Are you okay? Do you have cancer?Are you gonna commit suicide? &quot;



不至于吧

It&apos;s almost not worth it.



那我们呢

So, what about us?



- 我们？- 我是说

-What about us?-No, what I mean is...



-...if we were both going to die tonight---Like the apocalypse was coming?

- 如果我们今晚就要死了- 你是说世界末日来临？



No, that&apos;s too dramatic-- But what ifjust the two of us were going to die?

不，没有那么恐怖 ，不过，如果只有我们两个要死了



I mean, would we talkabout your book?

我们还会谈论你的书吗？



-The environment? Or....-lf today was our last day?

- 或者环境问题吗？- 如果今天是我们的最后一天？



没错，我们会谈什么，你会跟我说什么？

Yeah, what would we talk about?What would you tell me?



- 恩- 很难回答？

-Well....-That&apos;s hard, huh?



- 不不，我在想呢- 好吧

-No, no, I&apos;ll do it.-Okay.



我一定不会再讨论我的书了

I definitely wouldstop talking about my book.



-I would probably drop the environment.-Okay.

- 我得承认我大概也不会谈环境问题了- 好



不过我仍然想要谈谈那些魔法啊，宇宙什么的

But I would still want to talk about,you know, the magic in the universe.



- 只是我希望做这些的时候我是在一个...．- 什么？

-I&apos;d just want to do it from a...-What?



...一个旅馆房间里...

...a hotel room, you know...



...in between sessions of uswildly fucking until we die.

...在我们每个疯狂做爱的间隙直到我们死去



Wow. Well, why waste timewith an hotel room?

哇！何必要浪费时间去旅馆呢？



Why not do it right there on a bench?

为什么不在这儿？在这张长椅上？



- 不- 来，过来

Come here, come here, come here.



Okay. We&apos;re not gonna die tonight.

好啦，我们不会今晚就死的



All right. Too bad. I&apos;m sorry.

好吧，我太激动了，对不起



That was an extreme example.

我举的只是一个极端的例子



- 对不起- 没事

-I&apos;m sorry.-Okay.



我想要说的是...

What l-- My point was, you know...



我很难和别人深层次地沟通

...to truly communicate withpeople is very hard to do.



我懂，不像日常的交流...

No, I know, most of ourday-to-day exchanges--



我知道，我是说...

Yeah, no, I mean...



- 不要把什么都跟性扯上关系- 为什么不呢？

-...not to bring everything back to sex---But why not?



不，举个例子来说吧，我的一个女朋友

No, this example, this friend of mine,she was talking about--



- 她曾和我说起她跟她男朋友在床上的问题- 然后呢

-She and her boyfriend-- Problems in bed.-Right.



And how when they had been datingfor a year she started telling him...

她说他们交往一年之后，她开始告诉他...



...怎样才能让她获得更多的快感而这让她男友非常生气！

...what he could do to please her more,and it freaked him out.



- 为什么？- 他很生气

-Why?-Totally.



他觉得这是说自己做得不好

He thought it meanthe was a bad lover....



也许她不该等这么久才说

Maybe she shouldn&apos;t havewaited so long.



-After a year....-But men are so easily offended.

- 你知道，一年以后...- 没错，不过男人也太容易被激怒了！



- 你觉得比女人还容易？- 当然了，在这一点上毫无疑问！

-What, more than women?-Definitely on that subject.



-You think so?-Yeah, yeah.

- 你这么觉得？- 没错



也许这是因为

Well, maybe it&apos;s because, you know...



-...men are easier to-- To please.-To please?

- 男人比较容易获得满足- 获得满足？



-Well, I don&apos;t know.-Yeah, they are. They&apos;re definitely.

- 我不知道- 没错，他们绝对是的



Anyway, this friend,she was telling me...

总之我的朋友对我说



...next time she dates a man,she&apos;s gonna make a little questionnaire...

...下次她再交男朋友她会给他做一个问卷...



-...about what they like and dislike---What, written down, or out loud?

- 问明什么是他们喜欢的和不喜欢的- 你是说写下来还是大声问？



当然是写下来

Yeah, mostly written down.



不过答案不仅仅是“是”或“否”应该要更详细一点

But it wouldn&apos;t be just yes or no.It would be a bit more complex than that.



Like, for example, if the question is:&quot;Are you into S &amp; M? &quot;

打个比方，如果问题是“你喜欢性虐待吗？”



答案可以是: “不，但是偶尔为之也不错”

The answer could be: &quot;No, but a goodspanking once in a while doesn&apos;t hurt.&quot;



- 怎么样？- 好，或者是“你喜欢在做爱时讲一些激发情欲的话吗？”

Right, or like:&quot;Do you like talking dirty in bed? &quot;



- 类似这种问题？- 对，不过不只是这么泛泛的

-That kind of thing?-Yeah, but not just like any dirty talk.



Just &quot;What specific wordwould you like to hear? &quot;

要说：“你喜欢听什么样的词”？



-What, me?-Well, yeah.

- 你是问我吗？- 恩，是啊



For example what specific wordwould you like to hear?

比如你喜欢听什么样的话？



我不知道

I don&apos;t know.



What do you feel about the word&quot;pussy&quot;?

你觉得“小蜜桃”这词怎样？



我很喜欢

I love it.



很好

Good.



没想到九年之后我们都变得这么现实了

It&apos;s amazing what perverts we&apos;vebecome in the past nine years.



至少我们现不用把每次新的性体验...

At least now we don&apos;t have to pretendeach new sexual experience...



...都当作是是改变我们人生的大事

...is, like, a life-altering event.



我知道，你已经有过了那么多次感情经历现在都快失去激情了

I know. By now, you&apos;ve stuck it inso many places it&apos;s about to fall off.



And I can&apos;t realistically expect you&apos;vebecome anything but a total ho.

我也没指望你会一直想着我



-Yeah, thank you.-No, I&apos;m s--

- 哦，谢谢- 不，我很抱（歉）...



-That&apos;s true. What can you do?-What can you do?

- 没错阿，你该怎样呢？- 我该...



对了，你平时都写些什么歌？我还不知道你会写歌呢

So, what kind of songs do you write?I didn&apos;t know you did that.



-What kind?-Yeah, sure.

- 什么类型的？- 是啊



-I don&apos;t know, just songs.-Like?

- 我不知道，只是歌而已- 比如



比如有些是有关人的

Like, some are about,you know, people.



恩，或是各种爱恨情仇...还有一首是写我的猫猫的！

Relationships. One&apos;s about my cat.



-Sing one.-No, I can&apos;t. I don&apos;t have a guitar.

- 唱首听听！- 不行，我没有吉他



- 来吧，清唱一首- 不行，不行

-Come on. A cappella.-No, no, no.



I&apos;m not singing a song without a guitar.You&apos;re nuts.

没有吉他伴奏我唱不了歌你太过分了！



为什么？

Why not?



-No, okay. Not now. No.-One.

- 好吧，至少不是现在- 就一首



If not now, when? You want to meethere in six months with a guitar?

如果不是现在，还有什么时候呢？你想六个月后在这儿见面吗？带着吉他？



I&apos;ll fly all the way over here.

我会飞过来的



-You may or may not make the Metro.-Okay, that&apos;s funny.

- 但你不一定能赶上地铁- 好啦，这不好笑



- 我们该回书店了！- 没事的

-We&apos;ve got to get back.-We&apos;ll be all right.



-You&apos;re gonna miss your flight.-All right.

- 你会错过你的航班的，快点！- 好吧



We can walk down La Seine.It&apos;s nice.

我们可以沿塞纳河走走，很漂亮的



Okay.

好吧



- 那你是要飞回纽约吗？- 是的

-So you&apos;re flying back to New York?-Yeah, yeah.



我在文章中读到你结婚了，还有了一个孩子，真是太好了！

So I read in that article thatyou&apos;re married with a kid. That&apos;s great.



没错，他已经...他已经四岁了

Yeah, he&apos;s-- He&apos;s 4.



- 他叫什么？- 亨利，小汉克

-What&apos;s his name?-Henry. Little Hank.



-He&apos;s so much fun.-Oh, wow, I&apos;m sure.

- 他很可爱- 当然了



-Your wife, what does she do?-She teaches elementary school.

- 你的太太呢？她是做什么的？- 她在小学教书



-Do you have kids?-Yes, two-- Shit!

- 你有孩子吗？- 是的，有两个。糟了！



-What?-I left them in the car!

- 怎么了？- 我把他们落在车上了！



窗关得死死的，快有六个月了...他们会有事吗？

With the windows up, six months ago!Think they&apos;re okay?



No, I&apos;m kidding.No, but I want to have kids someday.

没有啦，我开玩笑的不过我很想要小孩



-I&apos;m just not ready yet.-No?

- 只是还没做好准备- 没有吗？



- 不过我现在正在认真谈恋爱- 噢是吗？这很好啊

-I&apos;m in a good relationship, though.-Oh yeah? That&apos;s good.



- 他是做什么的？- 他是个摄影记者

-What&apos;s he do?-He&apos;s a photojournalist.



专门做战地新闻

He does war coverage.



他经常出差，不过从某种角度对我来说是一件好事，因为我实在是太忙了

He&apos;s away a lot, which is goodbecause I&apos;m so busy.



不过那不是很危险吗？我是说，不是有很多人在战争中丧生吗？

But isn&apos;t that dangerous? Aren&apos;t a lot ofthose guys getting killed these days?



他向我保证不会太冒险的不过我还是会经常担心

He promises me he doesn&apos;t take risks,but I often worry.



他一拿起相机就什么都不顾了

He goes in this trance whenhe photographs something.



- 什么意思？- 有一次我们在新德里

-What do you mean?-Well, once we were in New Delhi...



见到一个流浪汉，他躺在人行道上

...and we passed a bum on the--



- 炸弹（谐音）？- 流浪汉！无家可归的人

-A bomb?-A bum. A homeless.



哦，流浪汉

All right, right.



总之他看起来需要帮助，但是我男朋友的第一个反应就是拿起相机！

He looked like he needed help, but hisfirst reaction was to photograph him.



他凑到离那个人的脸非常近的地方整理他的衣领，让他看起来显得更精神

He went really close to his face,fixing his collar...



他似乎完全不在乎那个人

...totally detached from the person.



不过要做好工作不就得这样吗？

But don&apos;t you have to be like thatto be good at that job?



Yeah, I mean, I&apos;m not....

是啊，我知道啊，我不是...



I&apos;m not judging him.What he does is essential and incredible.

我不是由此来看他的为人他的工作是重要的也是高尚的



All I&apos;m saying is thatI could never do it.

我只是说这是我自己永远做不到的



Let&apos;s get on that boat. Come on.

我们上那船吧！快！



-No!-Come on, it&apos;ll be fun.

- 不！- 快，很有趣的！



-You don&apos;t have time!-They&apos;re about to take off.

- 你没时间了！我们得走了- 它就要开了



I&apos;ve got 1 5 more minutes.Do you have a cell phone?

我还有15分钟呢你有手机吗？



-Yeah.-All right, I&apos;ve got that driver&apos;s number.

- 有- 那就好，我有那个司机的号码



I can call him to pick us upat the next stop.

我可以打电话给他让他在下一站停船的地方接我们



I&apos;ve never been on those boats.It&apos;s for tourists, it&apos;s embarrassing.

好吧，可我从来没上过那船，这是给游客的，太丢脸了



Okay. All right.

好啦，没事的



- Uhm, c&apos;est bon?Pouvons-nous entrer?- Bien sur!

（法语）- 唔，我们可以上船了吗？- 当然


- Deux tickets, s&apos;il vous plait!- No, I&apos;ll get it, I&apos;ll get it.


- （法语）请给我两张票！- 不，让我来，让我来


- No, no, c&apos;est bon.- All right. All right, all right.


- （法语）不，不，还是我来吧- 好吧，好吧，好吧



- C&apos;est ou qu&apos;il s&apos;arrete au prochain arret?- C&apos;est au Quai Henry IV.

谢谢


Thank you.



- 那你现在是跟他沉浸在爱河里咯？- 谁？

-So are you in love with that guy?-What guy?



-The war photographer.-Yes, of course.

- 那个战地摄影师- 哦，当然！



- Vous pouvez y aller.- Merci.

（法语）- 你们可以进去了- 谢谢


So do you have that cell phone?


对不起，你的手机...



Oh, yeah.

哦，对



-Okay, let&apos;s see....-Okay.

- 好，让我看看他的号码....- 好



我该怎么跟他说呢？

What do I tell him?



让他在亨利四世码头等着

Tell him to pick you up atQuai Henri Quatre.



Oh, shit. Quai...?

哦，见鬼，什么码头？



亨利四世，亨利四世码头

Henri Quatre. Quai Henri Quatre.



亨利四世

Henri Quatre.



你怎么了？不对，你要我来说吗？亨利四世

What&apos;s wrong with you? No, do youwant me to--? Henri Quatre.



-Henry Four?-Yes!

- 亨利四世？- 没错！



- 那你为什么不直接说？- 对不起！

-Come on, why didn&apos;t you say so?-I&apos;m sorry. Okay.



Yeah, is this Philippe?

你好，是菲利普吗？



菲利普，我是杰西·华莱士

Yeah. Philippe, this is Jesse Wallace.



Yeah.

对



呃，听我说，我现在在一条游船上

Well, listen, I&apos;m onone of those boats, right?



我们将会在亨利四世码头下船

And we&apos;re gonna arrive at Henry Four.



亨利四号码头你知道在哪儿吗？

At Port Henry Four.You know what that is?



All right, great.And you have my bags, right?

很好，你带着我的行李吧？



Yeah, so we&apos;ll be there in--I don&apos;t know, it&apos;s the next stop.

我们再过...总之下一站就到了



Okay. Au revoir.

好，再见



- 安排好了？- 恩

-It&apos;s okay?-Yeah, yeah.



Oh, wow.

哇！



-Notre Dame, man. Check that out.-Oh, wow.

- 看这边啊，巴黎圣母院！- 哇



I heard this story once about whenthe Germans were occupying Paris...

我听过一个故事说的是占领巴黎的德军



...撤出的时候

...and they had to retreat back.



他们在巴黎圣母院埋了很多炸药

They wired Notre Dame to blow...



...but they had to leave one guyin charge of hitting the switch.

...但他们得留一个人来按爆破的按钮



And the guy, the soldier,he couldn&apos;t do it.

但那个人，那个士兵他却下不了手！



他只是呆呆地坐着惊叹这地方的美妙

He just sat there, knocked outby how beautiful the place was.



当盟军部队到达的时候

Then, when the Allied troopscame in...



...they found all the explosiveslying there and the switch unturned...

他们发现炸药还在那里但按钮没人碰过



同样的情景还发生在圣心堂，埃菲尔铁塔...

...and they found the same thingat the Sacre-Coeur, Eiffel Tower...



...couple other places, I think.

...很多地方



这是真的吗？

Is that true?



我不知道不过我一直很喜欢这个故事

I don&apos;t know.I always liked the story, though.



没错，很震撼的一个故事

Yeah, that&apos;s a great story.



你相信巴黎圣母院有一天会消失吗？

But you have to think that Notre Damewill be gone one day.



这里曾经是另一座教堂，就在这

There used to be another churchat the Seine, right there.



-What, right in the same spot?-Yeah.

- 什么，同一个地方？- 是的



这样好舒服，我从来没有试过！

You know, this is great.I&apos;ve never done this.



-Yeah.-I forget about how beautiful Paris is.

- 是啊- 我已经忘了巴黎有多美



It&apos;s not so bad, being a tourist.

其实当个游客也不错



-Thanks for getting me on the boat.-You&apos;re welcome.

- 谢谢你带我上这船- 不用客气



I think that book that I wrotewas like building something...

我觉得我在写那本书的时候就好像在造什么东西



...so that I wouldn&apos;t forget the detailsof the time that we spent together.

以免我忘记我们经历过点点滴滴



你懂吗，就好像一个备忘录告诉我我们的确见过面

You know, like, just as a reminder,that once, we really did meet.



You know, that this was real,this happened.

你懂吗，那是真的，真的发生过



我很高兴你这么说，因为...

I&apos;m happy you&apos;re saying that,because....



I mean, I always feel like a freak becauseI&apos;m never able to move on like this:

我是说，我觉得自己很没用，因为我从来不能这么洒脱



People just have an affair,or even entire relationships...

人们只是随意留情，甚至即使是认真的感情



...they break up and they forget.

...人们也会分手，然后忘记



They move on like they would havechanged brand of cereals.

就像换另一个牌子的麦片一样简单



I feel I was never able to forgetanyone I&apos;ve been with...

可我觉得我永远忘不了跟我交往过的每一个人



...because each person had their ownspecific qualities.

..因为他们每个人都有很不一样的特质



你不能取代任何人失去的就失去了

You can never replace anyone.What is lost is lost.



每段感情结束的时候我都很受伤我从来没有完全恢复过

Each relationship, when it ends,really damages me. I never fully recover.



That&apos;s why I&apos;m very carefulwith getting involved...

所以我尽量避免介入感情



...because it hurts too much.

..因为那种痛真的是太深了！



即使是做爱！其实我不喜欢那样

Even getting laid,I actually don&apos;t do that...



...because I will miss of the personthe most mundane things.

因为我会很怀念一个人很平常的东西



好比那些细节

Like I&apos;m obsessed with little things.



Maybe I&apos;m crazy,but when I was a little girl...

或者也许我有点神经质但当我小的时候...



...my mom told methat I was always late to school.

妈妈告诉我，我上学经常迟到



One day she followed me to see why.

有一天她跟着我想知道为什么



我正看着栗子从树上掉下来，滚到便道上

I was looking at chestnuts falling fromthe trees, rolling on the sidewalk...



...或者是蚂蚁过马路，叶子在树干上的映出的倒影

...or ants crossing the road, the waya leaf casts a shadow on a tree trunk.



种种小事

Little things.



I think it&apos;s the same with people.

我想对人也是一样



我看到的是他们的细节，很细微

I see in them little details,so specific to each of them...



...那些能感动我的细节，然后我就会想念他们，一直想念

...that move me and that I missand will always miss.



You can never replace anyone...

你不能取代任何人



...because everyone is made of suchbeautiful, specific details.

因为每个人都有他那种美丽的，独特的细微之处



就好像我记得，你的胡子上有一点红色

Like, I remember the way your beardhas a bit of red in it...



...我记得你离开的那天早上...

...and how the sunwas making it glow...



...朝阳是怎样照的它闪闪亮

...that morning right before you left.



我一直记着，我非常怀念

I remembered that, and I missed it.



很神经质，对吧？

Really crazy, right?



Now I know for sure. You wannaknow why I wrote that stupid book?

现在我明白了，你想知道为什么我写了那本烂书吗？



-Why?-So you&apos;d come to a reading in Paris...

- 为什么？- 因为这样你就会参加巴黎的一场读者见面会



...而我就可以走过去，问你：“你到底去哪里了？”

...and I could walk up to you and ask,&quot;Where the fuck were you? &quot;



你真的觉得我今天会来？

No-- You think I&apos;d be here today?



I&apos;m serious. I think I wrote it,in a way, to try to find you.

真的，我之所以写这本书，从某种意义来讲就是为了能找到你



Okay, that&apos;s-- I know that&apos;s not true...

好啦，这....我知道这不是真的



- 不过听了还是很高兴- 我觉得这是真的

-...but that&apos;s sweet of you.-I think it is true.



我们还有机会再见面吗？

What were the chancesof us ever meeting again?



过了那个十二月，我想机率基本就是零了吧

After that December,I&apos;d say almost zero.



不过反正我们也不是来真的，对吗？

But we&apos;re not real anyway, right?



We&apos;re just charactersin that old lady&apos;s dream.

我们只不过是那个老妇人梦中的角色



她在她的病床上回忆年轻时的故事

She&apos;s on her deathbed,fantasizing about her youth.



So of course we had to meet again.

所以我们当然会见面！



Oh, God. Why weren&apos;t you therein Vienna?

天哪！你为什么那天没有出现在维也纳？



- 我告诉过你了！- 我知道，但是...

-I told you why.-I know why, I just....



I wish you would have been.

我真的希望你去了！



我们的生活可能会完全不一样！

Our lives might have beenso much different.



你真这么觉得？

You think so?



I actually do.

没错



也许不会呢，也许最后我们会憎恨对方呢

Maybe not. Maybe we would havehated each other eventually.



是吗，就像现在我们这样憎恨对方？

What, like we hate each other now?



You know, maybe we&apos;re--We&apos;re only good at brief encounters...

你知道的，可能我们...我们只适合那种偶遇...



...在温暖的天气里漫步在欧洲的街头

...walking around in European cities,in warm climate.



天哪，为什么我们没有交换电话号码呢？

Oh, God. Why didn&apos;t weexchange phone numbers and stuff?



为什么？

Why didn&apos;t we do that?



Because we were young and stupid.

因为那时我们太年轻，不成熟？



你觉得我们现在还是如此吗？

Do you think we still are?



I guess when you&apos;re youngyou just believe...

我觉得，当你年轻的时候你会相信...



...there&apos;ll be many peopleyou&apos;ll connect with.

...你会认识很多人



Later in life you realizeit only happens a few times.

但后来你才会发现能交流的人其实很少



And you can screw it up, you know.Misconnect.

何况你又不能保证和他们好好相处就这样，失去联系了



过去的就让它过去吧事情本来就是这样的

The past is the past.It was meant to be that way.



You really believe that?That everything&apos;s fated?

你真的相信吗？任何事情都是注定的？



这个嘛，你明白吗，世界也许没有我们想的那么多变

Well, you know, the world might beless free than we think.



Yeah?

是吗？



When given these exact circumstances,that&apos;s what will happen every time.

如果给定了特定的条件就总会发生一样的结果



Two part hydrogen, one part oxygen,you&apos;ll get water every time.

两份氢，一份氧，获得的总是水



No, I mean, what if your grandmotherhad lived a week longer, you know?

不， 我是说如果你祖母晚去世一个礼拜呢？



或者是早一个礼拜去世？甚至是几天？

Or passed away a week earlier?Days, even?



事情都可能完全不一样！我坚信这一点！

Things might have been different.



-You can&apos;t think like that, it&apos;s---You shouldn&apos;t on most things, but....

- 不，你不能这样想，那只是...- 我知道对于大多数事情来说的确是注定的



It&apos;s just, on this one, it seemed likesomething was off, you know.

但是，只是这件事，我觉得这事很不对劲



In the months leading up to my wedding,I was thinking about you all the time.

你知道吗，在我结婚前的那个月我一直都在想着你



Even on my way there, I&apos;m in the car, abuddy of mine is driving me downtown...

即使在去婚礼的路上，我坐在车里我的一个朋友送我进城



...and I&apos;m staring out the windowand I think I see you...

...我看着窗户觉得我看到你了



...离教堂不远...

...not far from the church, right...



...folding up an umbrellaand walking into a deli...

...收起一把雨伞，走进一家熟食店...



...就在百老汇和十三街的交汇处

...on the corner of 13th and Broadway.



那时我觉得我快要发疯了你知道吗？但现在我觉得这也许就是你

And I thought I was going crazy.But now I think it probably was you.



I lived on 11 th and Broadway.

我住在百老汇和十一街的交汇处



You see?

你看！



那，结婚的感觉怎样，你还没说呢

So, what is it like to be married?You haven&apos;t talked much about that.



我没有吗？真奇怪

I haven&apos;t? How weird.



I don&apos;t know. We met, you know,when I was in college.

我不知道怎么说，我们是在上大学的时候认识的



And we broke up and got back togetherfor a period of years, and then....

有几年，我们分分合合，然后...



怎么来着？我们好像又在一起了然后她就怀孕了...

What? We were sort of back togetherand she was pregnant...



...so marriage.

所以就结婚咯



她怎么样？

What is she like?



她是个好老师，好妈妈

She&apos;s a great teacher, a good mom.



她很聪明，很漂亮

She&apos;s smart, pretty, you know.



I remember thinking at the time...

我记得那时我想...



...很多我所崇拜的人..

...that so many of the menthat I admired most...



...that their lives were dedicated tosomething greater than themselves.

...他们的生命都奉献给了比自己更重要的东西



So you got married becausemen you admired were married?

所以你结婚是因为你崇拜的人都结婚了？



不，不... 准确来说是...我内心中有种对自我的完美期许

No, no. It&apos;s more like I had this--This idea of my best self, you know?



And I wanted to pursue that...

你懂吗？我想去追求那种自我



...even if it might have beenoverriding my honest self.

即使代价是失去真实的自我！



你懂我的意思吗？

You know what I&apos;m saying?



In the moment, I remember thinkingit didn&apos;t much matter, the who of it all.

我记得在那个时候我并不觉得和“谁”结婚这个问题很重要



一个人并不是你生命的全部

I mean, that nobody is gonna beeverything to you...



...到头来这只是一种负责的表现...

...and that it&apos;s just the actionof committing yourself...



...you know, meetingyour responsibilities, that matters.

...就是说，负担起你的责任来，这才是最重要的



我是说，爱是什么？如果它不是尊敬，信赖和钦佩的话？

I mean, what is love, right,if it&apos;s not respect, trust, admiration?



而我当时都感觉到了啊

And l-- I felt all those things.



Cut to the present,and I feel like I&apos;m running a nursery...

谈到现在，我感觉我好像在办一个托儿所



...跟一个我曾经约会过的人

...with somebody I used to date,you know.



我是说，我就像一个修道士

I mean, I&apos;m like a monk, you know.



我在过去的4年中做爱还不到10次

I mean, I&apos;ve had sex less than 10 timesin the last four years.



- 干嘛，干嘛？你笑我？- 没有

-What, what? You laughing at me?-No.



-lt sounds pathetic?-What monastery do monks have sex--?

- 听起来很可悲吗？- 你看到过有修道士做过10次爱的吗？



Okay, you&apos;re right, I&apos;m doing betterthan most monks.

好，你是对的，我比一般的修道士强，可以了吧？



But I do, I feel like if somebodywere to touch me...

但是我的确觉得，如果现在有人碰我的话



...I would dissolve into molecules.

我就会马上融化的了



好啦，我们到了，该走了，快

Well, we&apos;re here. We&apos;ve gotta go.Come on.



Shit.

该死



- （法语）晚上好- （法语）晚上好


- 我很遗憾听到那些- 什么？

-I&apos;m sorry to hear that, you know.-What?



You&apos;re not that happywith your marriage.

你对你的婚姻好像不怎么满意



-This friend of mine, she&apos;s a shrink---How&apos;s she doing?

- 我刚才说到的那个朋友，她是神经科医生- 她怎么了？



She&apos;s a mess, but....

她的生活很糟，不过...



她告诉我她遇过很多夫妻...

No, she said she&apos;s been dealingwith couples that are breaking up...



-...for the same reason.-What reason is that?

- 为了同样的理由而分开- 什么理由？



They all expected, after a fewyears of living together...

他们都期望，在共同生活了几年以后



...for the passion, that desire,to be the same.

...他们的热情，欲望还和当初一样



-Yeah, right.-It&apos;s impossible.

- 这是不可能的！- 是啊，没错



而且谢天谢地...

And thank God...



...如果我们一直保持激情的话我们会得动脉瘤的

...we&apos;d end up with aneurysms in thatconstant state of excitement, right?



我们一生将一事无成

We&apos;d do nothing at allwith our lives.



如果你每5分钟就做一次爱你还能写完你的书吗？

Would you have finished your bookif you were fucking every five minutes?



I might have welcomed the challenge,I mean....

我很乐意接受这个挑战



It&apos;s natural for your wifeafter the birth of your son...

但是，你懂吗，很自然的当你太太生了小孩以后



-...to give all her love to the little one.-Of course.

- 她就会把她的爱转移到小孩身上- 当然



If she was obsessed with sex,riding you like a wildcat....

想想看如果她执迷于性爱，像野猫一样不停挑逗你



这不合情理，对吧？

That wouldn&apos;t make any sense, right?



不是这样的，你说得都很有道理但这不是性的问题

Everything you&apos;re saying makes sense.It&apos;s not about sex.



No, I know. It&apos;s obvious.

是啊，我知道，很明显不是



I....

我...



你知道，现在的夫妻感情很复杂

You know, couplesare so confused lately.



I think it must be that...

我觉得肯定是因为...



...男人总想让人觉得他们很重要但事实已不是这样了

...men need to feel essentialand they don&apos;t anymore.



多年以来，这种观念深植于他们脑海之中...

It&apos;s been imprinted in their headfor so many years...



...好像他们就必须要是家里的顶梁柱

...that they had to be the provider.



比如，我在工作中就是一个坚强，独立的女性

Like, I&apos;m a strong, independent womanin my professional life.



I don&apos;t need a man to feed me...

我不需要一个男人养我



...but I still need a man to love meand that I could love.

...但我仍要一个男人爱我，而我也爱他



-So your driver&apos;s here.-Yeah.

- 好啦，我看到你的司机了- 是的



Well, I guess this is goodbye.

那，我想我该告别了



- 你最好把你的...- 不

-You better give me your---No, no.



我们不如送你回家吧

Why don&apos;t we justgive you a ride home?



- 这个嘛，我可以搭地铁，我没事- 不，我...

-Well, I can take the Metro. I&apos;m fine.-No, l--



我的飞机要10点才飞我会提前两个钟头去

My flight&apos;s not until 10.I&apos;ll be arriving two hours early.



这样我们就可以继续谈了

This way we can keep talking.



- 先生，能...？- 那不顺路的

-Monsieur, can--?-It&apos;s not on the way.



Ca vous arrive me deposer au passageDix Rue des petits ecuries?

（法语）您能把我带到马场附近的十号路吗？


Oui, oui.


（法语）当然可以


Allons-y!


- （法语）我们走吧- （法语）麻烦您了


Ca peut etre trop tard?



No, no, ce n&apos;est pas de probleme!

（法语）不，不，没问题


Vous pouvez me laisser au metro...au metro Chateau d&apos;Eau.


（法语）您就把我带到“水塔”地铁站附近就行了


- Ca ira tres bien.- Entendu!


- （法语）好吗？- （法语）好的，没问题


Merci!


（法语）谢谢

你把你的住址什么的都告诉他了？


You told him where you areand all that?




是的

Yeah.



-He knows where he&apos;s going?-Yes.

- 他知道他要去哪了？- 是的



太好了

Glad somebody does.



-But this is better than the Metro, right?-Definitely.

- 这比搭地铁好，对吧？- 当然



我在想，对我来说，还是不要把事情想得太浪漫比较好

I was thinking, for me it&apos;s better I don&apos;tromanticize things as much anymore.



I was suffering so much all the time.

我一直都吃这个亏



我仍旧有很多梦想，但它们都与我的感情生活无关

I still have lots of dreams,but they&apos;re not in regard to my love life.



It doesn&apos;t make me sad,it&apos;s just the way it is.

这样并不会让我不开心，因为事情本来就是这样的



这就是你为什么要和一个不常见面的人发生感情吗？

Is that why you&apos;re in a relationshipwith somebody who&apos;s never around?



当然，我应付不了那种天天见面的感情

Yes, obviously I can&apos;t deal withthe day-to-day life of a relationship.



Yeah, we have thisexciting time together...

我们相聚的时候可以充满激情



...and he leaves and I miss him,but at least I&apos;m not dying inside.

...然后他离去了，我会很想他不过我起码不会痛不欲生



如果有人一直在我身边我会觉得窒息！

When someone&apos;s always around me,I&apos;m suffocating.



等等，可是你刚说你想要爱和被爱

No, wait, you just saidthat you need to love and be loved.



没错，但是当我的确这么做时，这马上会让我恶心！

Yeah, but when I do,it quickly makes me nauseous.



真是个灾难

It&apos;s a disaster.



我是说，我只有一个人独处的时候才会真正开心

I mean, I&apos;m really happyonly when I&apos;m on my own.



Even being alone, it&apos;s better than sittingnext to a lover and feeling lonely.

即使是一个人，也比坐在情人边上却心不在焉要来的好



浪漫对我来说并不是一件容易的事

It&apos;s not so easy for meto be a romantic.



你开始的时候可能会这么做，不过当你受过几次伤以后...

You start off that way, and afteryou&apos;ve been screwed over a few times...



...you forget about your delusional ideasand you take what comes into your life.

..你就会拒绝那些虚幻的想法接受生活中的现实



其实这也不见得对我并没受过几次伤...

That&apos;s not even true.I haven&apos;t been screwed over...



...I&apos;ve just had too manyblah relationships.

...我只是有太多平庸的感情了



他们不是对我不好，他们都很关心我...

They weren&apos;t mean,they cared for me...



...但是我们却没有那种心灵上的沟通或是发自心底的兴奋

...but there were no real connectionor excitement.



起码我这边是这么感觉的

At least, not from my side.



天哪，真遗憾，有这么糟糕吗？

God, I&apos;m sorry, is it really that bad?



It&apos;s not, right?

没有吧，对吗？



You know, it&apos;s not even that.I was....

你知道吗，其实也不是这样的我...



我本来是好好的，直到我读到你那本该死的书

I was fine until I readyour fucking book.



It stirred shit up, you know?

它把陈年往事又翻起来了，你知道吗？



它让我想起了，我曾经真正的浪漫过

It reminded me howgenuinely romantic I was...



...我对于世界有过多少希望...

...how I had so much hope in things...



...and now it&apos;s like I don&apos;t believein anything that relates to love.

...而我现在已经完全不相信任何爱情了



I don&apos;t feel things for people anymore.

我已经感觉不到人之间的感情了



从某种意义上来说，我所有的浪漫都在一夜之间消耗光了...

In a way, I put all my romanticisminto that one night...



...而我将永远不可能再有那种感觉了

...and I was never able to feelall this again.



就好像，那一夜不知道怎么引发了我的全部感情...

Like, somehow this nighttook things away from me...



...而我把这些感情都向你倾诉出来而你却把它们都从我身边带走了

...and I expressed them to you,and you took them with you.



It made me feel cold,like love wasn&apos;t for me.

这让我感到孤独！好像爱情再也不属于我一样！



I don&apos;t believe that.I don&apos;t believe that.

我不相信，我不相信



You know what? Reality and loveare almost contradictory for me.

你知道吗？ 对我来说，现实和爱基本就是矛盾的



It&apos;s funny, every single of my exes,they&apos;re now married.

非常可笑，我每一个以前的男友他们都结婚了



男人约我出去，然后我们分手然后他们就结婚了.

Men go out with me, we break up,and then they get married.



之后之后他们打电话感谢我教会了他们什么是爱

And later they call me to thank mefor teaching them what love is...



...教会了他们去关心跟尊重女人！

...and that I taught them to careand respect women.



- 我想我也是那些男人中的一个- 你知道吗，我真想杀了他们！

-I think I&apos;m one of those.-I want to kill them!



他们为什么不向我求婚？我也许会拒绝，但至少他们也应该问我啊！

Why didn&apos;t they ask me? I would havesaid no, but they could have asked!



但我知道这是我的错因为我总觉得他们不是我的如意郎君

I know it&apos;s my fault becauseI never felt it was the right man.



Never. But what does it mean,the right man, the love of your life?

从来没有，但如意的人又是什么呢？你的真爱？



这种想法简直可笑，说什么我们只有找到了另一半人生才是完整的

The concept is absurd. We can only becomplete with another person.



-It&apos;s evil, right?-Can I talk?

- 这太可恶了，不是吗？- 我能说两句吗？



我想我是伤心过太多次了然后又恢复了

I guess I&apos;ve been heartbrokentoo many times and then I recovered.



So now, you know, from the starts,I make no effort.

于是现在，从一开始，我就不愿意付出努力



- 因为我知道一定不能成功- 你不能这样

-I know it&apos;s not gonna work out.-You can&apos;t do that.



你不可以只是为了避免受伤害

You can&apos;t live trying to avoid pain...



-...at the expense---Those are words.

- 就付出...- 好啦，我决定了



我要离你远远的

I&apos;ve gotta get away from you.



- 停车，我要下车！- 不，别下车

-Stop the car, I wanna get out.-No, don&apos;t--



- 你知道在你身边...- 请继续讲...

-Keep talking.-It&apos;s being around you.



Don&apos;t touch me, you know.I want to get on a cab.

别碰我！你知道吗，我要叫辆计程车...



Monsieur, aretes vous!

（法语）请停车，先生


Non, non, c&apos;est bon, aux feux-la!


（法语）过了红绿灯您就停，我去坐地铁


No, don&apos;t. No, no, keep going.


别，别停，继续开...



Listen, I&apos;m just so happy--Thank you, just keep going.

听我说，我真的很高兴...谢谢你，请继续开...



好啦

All right.



Look, I&apos;m just so happy,all right, to be with you.

听我说，我真得很高兴能跟你在一起



I am. I&apos;m so glad you didn&apos;tforget about me, okay?

我真得很高兴你没有忘记我



是的，我没有，而这吓坏我了，知道吗？

No, I didn&apos;t.And it pisses me off, okay?



你到巴黎来，给我带来浪漫，但却结了婚

You come here to Paris,all romantic, and married.



Okay? Screw you.

去死吧你！



Don&apos;t get me wrong,I&apos;m not trying to get you.

不要误会我，我并没有想要占有你



我只不过想把自己嫁出去

I mean, all I need is a married man.



这个问题很复杂这甚至不仅仅是关于你

There&apos;s been so much water underthe bridge, it&apos;s not even about you.



还有那段过去的时光，那段永远不会再回来的时光！

It&apos;s about that moment in timethat&apos;s forever gone.



You say that, but you didn&apos;teven remember having sex, so....

你说了这么多，但你却根本不记得我们做过爱



Of course I remembered.

我当然记得



-You did?-Yes.

- 你记得？- 没错！



-Women pretend things like that.-They do?

- 女人总喜欢这么掩饰自己- 是吗？



我应该说什么呢？说我记得公园里的红酒...

What was I supposed to say?That I remember the wine in the park...



...and us looking up at the stars fadingaway as the sun came up?

...说我们我们一起看着星星落下太阳升起！



我们做了两次爱，你这混蛋！

We had sex twice, you idiot!



好啦，你知道吗我真得很高兴看到你

All right, you know what,I&apos;m just happy to see you.



即使你已变得易怒和神经质

Even if you&apos;ve become an angry,manic-depressive activist...



...I still like you,I still enjoy being around you.

我还是很喜欢你我还是愿意跟你待在一起！



And I feel the same. I&apos;m sorry.I don&apos;t know what happened, I just....

我也是，对不起，我不知道怎么了，我只是...



- 我需要发泄，我...- 没事

-I had to let it all out.-Don&apos;t worry about it.



我的感情生活太不顺利了

I&apos;m so miserable in my love life,in my relationship.



所以我总是装作...好像我不在意它

I always act as--Like, you know, I&apos;m detached.



But I&apos;m dying inside.I&apos;m dying because I&apos;m so numb.

但我真得痛不欲生因为麻木而痛不欲生



我不能感受到伤心和兴奋我也不会感到苦涩，我只是...

I don&apos;t feel pain or excitement,I&apos;m not even bitter, I&apos;m just....



你以为只有你痛不欲生吗？

You think you&apos;re the onedying inside?



My life is 24/7 bad.

我的生活每时每刻全像是地狱



-I&apos;m sorry.-No, no.

- 对不起...- 不要...



I mean, the only happiness I getis when I&apos;m out with my son.

我唯一的快乐就是跟我儿子出去



我去找了婚姻咨询

I&apos;ve been to marriage counseling...



...I&apos;ve done things I never thoughtI would have to do.

我做了我从来没想过我会做的事



I&apos;ve lit candles,bought self-help books, lingerie.

我点了蜡烛，买了自助读物，女性内衣...



-Did the candles help?-Hell, no.

- 蜡烛有用吗？- 有个鬼用！



我没法用她想要的方式爱她

I don&apos;t love her the wayshe needs to be loved...



...我甚至根本看不到我们的未来但当我看到我的小儿子

...and I don&apos;t even see a future for us,but then I look at my little boy...



...坐在桌子的对面我就觉得我愿意承受一切折磨...

...sitting across from me,and I think I&apos;d suffer any torture...



...to be with him forall the minutes of his life.

...只要能跟他一起度过他生命中的每一刻



我一刻也不想缺

I don&apos;t want to miss out on one.



But then, there&apos;s no joy or laughterin my home, you know?

但是我的家里没有欢笑，没有快乐



-I don&apos;t want him growing up in that.-No laughter? That&apos;s terrible.

- 我不希望他在这样的环境中长大- 没有欢笑？那可太糟了



我的父母在一起已经有35年了

My parents have beentogether 35 years...



而即使他们吵架之后，他们还会笑得一样开心

...and even when they fightthey end up laughing.



我不想变成那种人在52岁时离了婚...

I don&apos;t want to be one of those peoplewho are getting divorced at 52...



...落着泪，承认从来就没有爱过自己的伴侣...

...and falling down into tears, admittingthey never really loved their spouse...



...and they feel their life has beensucked up into a vacuum cleaner.

...感觉自己的生活好像完全被吸尘器吸走一样，一片空虚



我也想拥有美好的生活我也希望她拥有美好的生活

You know, I want a great life.I want her to have a great life...



这是她应得的！

...she deserves that.



但现在我们只是假装维系着婚姻，责任

But we&apos;re just living in the pretenseof a marriage, responsibility...



...过着那种人们觉得你该过的日子

...you know, all these ideasof how people are supposed to live.



然后，我...我做了一个梦

But then l-- I have these dreams....



什么梦？

What dreams?



我做了一个梦

I have these dreams,you know, that...



...梦见我站在月台上

...I&apos;m standing on a platform...



...而你不停的坐火车经过

...and you keep going by on a train...



...你就是不停的经过，经过，经过

...and you go by, and you go by,and you go by, you go by.



And I wake up withthe fucking sweats.

然后我被吓醒，浑身冷汗



And then I have this other dream...

然后我又做了一个梦...



...where you&apos;re pregnant in bedbeside me naked...

...梦见你怀孕了，在床上躺在我身边，一丝不挂...



...and I want so badly to touch you, butyou tell me not to and you look away.

...而我非常非常想要抚摸你，但你跟我说不要，然后你就把头别过去



And l-- And I touch you anyway...

然后我... 我还是抚摸了你...



...摸你的脚踝那里，你的皮肤是那样的柔软使得我在哭泣中醒来

...right on your ankle, and your skin isso soft that I wake up in sobs, all right?



我的妻子就坐在那里，看着我我却觉得她离我万里之遥

My wife is there looking at me,and I feel I&apos;m a million miles from her.



And I know that there&apos;ssomething wrong, that l--

我知道那不对劲，我...



God, that I can&apos;t keep living like this...

天啊！我不能再这样活下去了...



...that there&apos;s gotta be more to lovethan commitment.

...爱的意义一定不仅仅是责任



But then I think thatI might have given up...

但然后我又想也许我已经不相信...



...on the whole idea of romantic love.

...浪漫的爱情了



我可能早已经不信了

That I might have put itto bed that--



That day when you weren&apos;t there.

自从那天我在那里没有见你



我想，我可能就开始消沉了

You know, I think I mighthave done that.



你为什么要和我说这些？

Why are you telling me all this?



对不起，我不知道我...我应该...

I&apos;m sorry. I don&apos;t know.I&apos;m-- I should....



我不应该说的

I shouldn&apos;t have.



你知道，太奇怪了

You know, it&apos;s so weird.



People think they are the only onegoing through tough times.

人们总是觉得自己是唯一痛苦的人



当我读那些文章的时候我觉得你的生活是完美的

I mean, when I read the article,I thought your life was perfect.



有太太，孩子，出版了自己的作品

A wife, a kid, published author.



But your personal lifeis more of a mess than mine.

现在看来你的生活比我还糟！



I&apos;m sorry.

对不起！



起码有些方面还过得去

Well, I&apos;m glad it&apos;s good for something.


Oh, monsieur, c&apos;est la!


（法语）噢，先生，就是那儿！



Rentrez dans la passe-la.

（法语）把车停到那个通道里就行了

- 这里就是你住的地方？- 没错


-This is where you live?-Yeah.




那现在看到看到我的生活比你还糟觉得舒服点了吧？

So you&apos;re just relieved that I&apos;min even more deep shit than you are?



是的，你让我感觉好多了

Yes, you&apos;ve made me feel better.



Oh, good, I&apos;m glad.

哦，那就好，我很高兴...



No, I really wish you the best.

不，我真的希望你的生活可以更好



It&apos;s not because I&apos;m incapable of havinga good relationship or a family...

我不会因为自己无法有良好的感情或是美好的家庭



...that I wish everyone to bedoomed like me.

就想要别人也跟我一样不开心



I&apos;m sure you&apos;d make-- Bea great mom someday.

我知道你总有一天会成为...一个伟大的母亲的！



- 真的？你真的这么认为？- 没错

-Really? You think so?-Yeah...



...a few antidepressants, you know,you&apos;ll do great.

只要服一些抗忧郁药，你就行了！



- 喊停！- 停！

-Okay, say stop.-Stop.



- 好啦- 准备好了吗？好啦

-Okay.-You ready? Okay.



-So I want to try something.-What?

- 我想试一下- 什么？



我想看看你是会保持原样还是会融化

I want to see if you stay togetheror if you dissolve into molecules.



我融化了吗？

How am I doing?



保持原样！

Still here.



很好，我喜欢住在这儿

Good. I like being here.



Is this your apartment?

这是你的公寓吗？



不，我住在那里

No, I live down there.



- 那里？- 是的

-Down there?-Yeah.



先生，我想送她进家门

Monsieur, I&apos;m gonna walk herto her door.



Il va m&apos;accompagner...a la porte.

（法语）他要送我进家门



This is incredible.

太不可思议了！



-This is where you live?-Yeah.

- 这就是你住的地方？- 是的



-How long have you been here?-Four years.

- 你搬来这里多久了？- 四年了



- 那告诉我....- 什么？

-So tell me....-What?



你讲的那些你的梦，是真的吗？

Is it all true about your dreams...



...or did you say that to hopefullyget in my pants?

还是只是为了骗我上床？



当然只是骗你上床啦！

I said that to get in your pants.



- 这是我的惯用伎俩- 哦，有用吗？

-I use that all the time.-Oh, okay. Does it work?



You know. Sometimes.

恩，有时候



这是我的猫咪，哦，太可爱了看看它

Here&apos;s my kitty. Oh, so cute.Look at him.



You know what I loveabout this cat?

你知道我喜欢他的什么吗？



Every morning I bring himto the courtyard...

每天早上我带他下来



...and every single morning he looksat everything like it was the first time.

...每一个早晨，他都会像是第一次来到这个院子一样！



Every corner, every tree, every plant.

每个角落，每棵树，每棵植物



都用他可爱的小鼻子去闻闻

Smells everythingwith his little cute nose.



Oh, I love my kitty. I love my kitty.

我太喜欢他了！



-What&apos;s his name?-Che.

- 他叫什么？- 奇



奇？

Che?



-What?-Commie.

- 怎么了？- 听起来像共产党员



No, &quot;che&quot; in argentina means &quot;hey.&quot;

不，“奇”在阿根廷是用来打招呼用的！



- 真的？- 是的

-Okay.-Yes.



哦，宝贝，哦，好啊，好啊

Oh, baby. Oh, yes, yes, yes.



We&apos;re having a little party.It&apos;s so much fun.

我们晚上有个聚餐！超好玩的！



Qu&apos;est-ce que vous avezfait bon pour ce soir?

（法语）你为晚餐准备了什么好东西？


Un taboule!


（法语）塔布雷色拉


Je vais descendre dans cinq minutes!


（法语）我过五分钟下来


Salut!


（法语）你好

（法语）你好


- 那....- 那

-So....-So.





C&apos;est qui celui-la? Il est mignon!

（法语）这是谁？帅哥啊！


- Il mange avec nous?- Non, il prend l&apos;avion.


- （法语）他和我们共进晚餐吗？- （法语）不，他要赶飞机


Tant pis! Il ne goutera pasmes paton pois chiches.


（法语）可惜他尝不到我的拿手菜了


Pour-quo&apos;il ne mange pas avec nous?


（法语）他为什么不留下吃晚饭？


Il n&apos;aime pas ton short!


（法语）他不喜欢你的短裤！



你知道吗？我在想你可以唱一首你的歌给我听吗？

You know what? I was thinking,would you play me one of your songs?



-You&apos;re gonna miss your flight.-I won&apos;t.

- 你会错过你的班机的！- 不，不会的！



我坐在候机厅也只不过是读一个小时的报纸

I&apos;m gonna be in the airport forover an hour, reading...



...wishing you&apos;d played meone of your songs.

...所以还是听你唱一首歌给我听吧



一首？ 好吧，不过很短的

One song? Okay, but quickly.



Okay.

好的



我太喜欢这老楼梯了

God, I love these old staircases.



- 拿着！- 什么，让我来？

-Hold this.-What, for me?



Hey there, buddy.

嘿，小家伙



Che.

奇



-Would you like some tea?-Yeah, sure.

- 你想喝点茶吗？- 好啊



Wow.

哇



-ls chamomile okay?-Yeah. Great.

- 甘菊茶好吗？- 恩，很好



-Merci.-Messy?

- （法语）谢谢！- 乱？（谐音）



-You think my apartment is messy?-No, no. Merci.

- 你觉得我的房间很乱？- 不不不，我是说谢谢



-Merci beaucoup.-Ah, merci.

- （法语）非常感谢- 哦，谢谢



我想告诉你，你的法语进步很多

I meant to tell you,your French has improved a lot.



- 真的吗？- 没错！

-Really?-Yeah.



你已经完全掌握这门语言了

Yeah, you&apos;ve reallymastered the language.



好吧，那你想要唱哪首歌？

All right, all right, what songare you gonna play me?



不行，我唱不了，这太丢人了

No, I can&apos;t. It&apos;s too embarrassing.It&apos;s been--



Whoa. No way. No way. I came up here,you cannot crap out on me now.

哇！不行！我这么费劲上来就是为了这个，你不能这样坑我



就一首，随便那首都行

One song. Anything will be great.



But listen, you&apos;re gonna laugh at me.

但你会笑我的



- 你这么觉得？- 是的！

-You think so?-Yes.



I doubt it.

放心，我不会的



Okay.

好吧



What do you want to hear? I have....

你想听什么？我有...



我有三首英文歌

I have three songs in English.



一首是唱我的猫的

One&apos;s about my cat...



...one&apos;s about my ex-boyfriend--Well, ex-ex-boyfriend...

...一首是唱我的前男友，呃，前前男友...



...还有一首是....

...and there&apos;s one about....



是首华尔兹

Well, it&apos;s just a little waltz.



A waltz? Yeah.

华尔兹？



-Play the waltz.-Right.

- 那就唱华尔兹吧- 好吧



我已经很久没弹吉他了，你确定你想听吗？

I haven&apos;t played it in a while.You sure?



Okay.

当然



All right, the waltz.

好吧，华尔兹



Let me sing you a waltz

让我唱首华尔兹



无从讲起，从我的心底

Out of nowhere, out of my thoughts



Let me sing you a waltz

让我唱首华尔兹



About this one-night stand

唱那次一夜缠绵



You were, for me, that night

那晚，你是我的



你是我生命中的全部梦想

Everything I always dreamt of in life



但你已经不在了

But now you&apos;re gone



你去了很远的地方

You are far-gone



All the way to your island of rain

你那的雨中小岛



对你来说，那只是一夜情

It was, for you, just a one-night thing



But you were much more to me

对我来说却远远不止



Just so you know

我想让你知道



我不管别人怎样说

I don &apos;t care what they say



I know what you meantFor me that day

我知道你对我的意义



我只想再来一次

I just want another try



我只想再来一夜

I just want another night



Even if it doesn &apos;t seem quite right

即使这看起来毫无意义



但你对我来说

You meant, for me, much more



Than anyone I&apos;ve met before

要比任何人都更重要



和你共度的一夜啊，小杰西

One single night with you, little Jesse



比得上和他人的一千个夜晚

Is worth a thousand with anybody



I have no bitterness, my sweet

我没有痛苦，亲亲



我永远不会忘记这一夜缠绵

I&apos;ll never forget this one-night thing



Even tomorrow, in other arms

即使明天我在他人怀中



My heart will stay yours until I die

我的心还会随你而去，直到生命尽头



Let me sing you a waltz

让我唱一首华尔兹



无从讲起，从我的心底

Out of nowhere, out of my blues



Let me sing you a waltz

让我唱一首华尔兹



About this lovely one-night stand

唱那可爱的一夜情



-No, one more! Please, please.-No! It was our deal.

- 不要停，再来一首，求你了- 不行，说好了的！



一首，就一首，别，别

One-- One song. No, no, no.



You can have your tea and then....

你可以喝完你的茶再...



-All right, let me ask you one question.-What?

- 好吧，我问你个问题- 什么？



Do you just plug that name infor every guy that comes up here?

你是不是每次不管谁来就在歌词里换个名字？



当然了

Yes, of course.



你以为呢？我是写给你的？你疯了吗？

What do you think, that I wrotethe song about you? Are you nuts?



这是你吗？小对眼塞琳？

Is this you? Little cross-eyed Celine?



- 是的，那张很好笑- 可爱

-Yes. That&apos;s funny.-Cute.



-ls that your grandmother?-Yeah.

- 这就是你的祖母？- 是的



哇

Oh, wow.



-You want some honey?-Yeah, sure.

- 你要加点蜂蜜吗？- 好的



Did you ever see Nina Simonein concert?

你听过尼娜·西蒙的演唱会吗？



No, I never did.I can&apos;t believe she&apos;s gone.

没有，不敢相信她已经不在了



我知道，太让人伤心了

I know, it&apos;s so sad.



Thanks.

谢谢



It&apos;s hot.

真热



I saw her twice in concert.

我听过她两次演唱会



她真棒！

She was so great.



这是她的歌里我最喜欢的几首之一

That&apos;s one of my favorite songs of hers.



她太棒了！

She was so great.



She was so funny in concert too.

她在演唱会里太有趣了



她会...她会在一首歌唱到一半时的时候

She would-- She would beright in the middle of a song and then...



...you know, stop...

...你知道吗，停下来...



...and walk from the piano all the wayto the edge of the stage.

...从钢琴边起身，一直走到舞台边上



像这样，非常慢的

Like, really slowly.



然后她开始对观众中的某人说话

And she&apos;d start talking to someonein the audience.



哦，耶，哦，耶

&quot;Oh, yeah, baby. Oh, yeah.



我也爱你

I love you too.&quot;



然后她又走回去，不急不忙的，

And then she&apos;d walk back.Take her time, no hurry, you know.



She had that big, cute ass.

她的大屁股真可爱



She would move.

她就这么慢慢挪着



And then she would go back to the pianoand play some more, you know.

然后就走回钢琴旁再唱一段



And then she would, I don&apos;t know...

然后她会，我也不知道...



...一首歌唱了一半又唱另外一首

...just start another songin the middle of another.



你懂吗，好像，又停下，然后这样

You know, like,stop again, and be like:



&quot;You over there,can you move that fan.

那边那位，你能挪挪那电扇吗



You&apos;re cute.

你真可爱



哦，耶

Oh, yeah.&quot;



Baby, you are gonna miss that plane.

宝贝，你会错过你的班机的



I know.

我知道



</影评>
<有用数>283</有用数>
<没用数>6</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>jo</作者>
<作者评分>4</作者评分>
<时间>2013-06-25 11:04:43</时间>
<影评>

        &quot;The difference between a caprice and a lifelong passion is that a caprice lasts longer.&quot; When the great Oscar Wilde wrote this sentence, he probably didn&apos;t expect that three people (Richard Linklater, Ethan Hawke and Julie Delpy) would make a movie to vividly and thoroughly interpret this famous sentence of his. &apos;Before Sunrise&apos; was all about caprice. An American guy spent a night with a French girl in Vienna. They flirted, drank, laughed, had sex and parted before the Sun rose again. The night passed by pleasantly with all the pretentious conversations between two typical twenty-some pseudo-intellectuals. He felt like a different person with her; she wanted to be lost in this beautiful dream. Although it&apos;s a corny one-night stand with an even cheesier poem inserted weirdly into the middle of the film, &apos;Before Sunrise&apos; demonstrates how every love story starts. As two people connect and fall in love, they present to each other the best versions of themselves, the no-liability view on life and the impractical ideals about relationship.

        Nine years later, when &apos;Before Sunset&apos; caught up, the honeymoon stage was long gone and the bitterness just kicked in. Instead of talking about &apos;911&apos; or any major events that had happened (since both of them were in New York for some time), the two people assumed that the other was better off in his or her life. He wondered why she never showed up; she found it unfair that he became successful while she was aging and trapped in failed relationships. The presumptuous thing about knowing a person by just a little bit is that one forgets that a story, by default, has to be interesting. Both the storytellers and listeners tend to omit the intermittent uneventfulness, hence the illusion and insecurity of other people&apos;s lives being more exciting than their own.

        Eventually through all the things that didn&apos;t work, the man and the woman realized what was most important for them and got together. Another nine years later, they took the offer to spend a romantic night away from the kids and the mid-life crisis but the fighting couldn&apos;t stop, not even by sex. &apos;Before Midnight&apos; darkened and deepened the two characters&apos; relationship, it was brutally honest about life&apos;s toll on couple, its impatience on love and its immunity to communication. When passion becomes commitment and sacrifice; man becomes a rationalist without emotion, woman a philosopher without reasoning.

         Recently I had a conversation with a friend about how long it would take to know your partner in a relationship. While I argued that it takes as long as it gets, my friend confidently claimed that one month, at most, should be more than enough to know all the things needed to know about the other person. His Charlotte Lucas &quot;Don&apos;t ask, don&apos;t tell&quot; style made me wonder: how can a person be sure of the love of his life just by meeting her twice over 9 years? At the end of &apos;Before Midnight&apos;, Jesse himself answered my question: he threw away everything because of Celine&apos;s little waltz; he put up with all the craziness because he decided to &quot;miss that plane&quot;. The ultimate answer to the Before trilogy is that love is about the good, the bad and the ugly. There is no such ending as happily ever-after. After going through the pretentious, the presumptuous and the preposterous, the finale of love is a conscious choice, a decision to take a chance with someone, to give to him or her without asking why. So I guess there is no fairy tale here, just great sex in the Southern Peloponnese of Greece.


</影评>
<有用数>120</有用数>
<没用数>7</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>幽草</作者>
<作者评分>4</作者评分>
<时间>2019-04-22 23:01:56</时间>
<影评>

看完爱在三部曲，给我留下印象最深刻的不是浪漫激情落入现实后的一地鸡毛，而是那个从未出现过的Jessie的前妻。
起初她模模糊糊地出现在两人的交谈中，是一个遥远而温柔的背景色：
《爱在日落黄昏时》
而后Jessie和Celine生活在一起后，她变成了两人无数矛盾中的一个：
《爱在午夜降临前》
我莫名地心疼那个从未露过面的女人，在这个浪漫得惊天动地的爱情故事中不小心沦为过客和配角的女人。
她原本是个聪明独立又优雅的女性，原本幸福而稳定地经营着三口之家，而在某一天，她认为足以信任依靠的丈夫告诉她，他从未爱过她，他与她相处的日子里一直在想念着另一个女人，而现在他找到了她，他们要在一起，他要结束这段有了孩子却没有爱的婚姻。
拼命用伤害儿子和自己的方式来介入他的幸福生活，是她唯一能想到的报复。你总不能要求那个被伤害的人去理解男女主的爱情多么浪漫珍贵然后理应让路吧，对一个以为自己拥有过爱情而实际上不过是现实的凑合的要强的人来说，这大概是世界上最难承受的痛苦了吧。
而我们大多数人，在这个故事里的角色，难道不是这样以安稳为爱情去接受生活并努力经营，一辈子也难以遇到无法割舍的爱人的配角么。
当你不是命运的宠儿，而这往往是最可能的情况，我们该如何安放自己的渴望、尊严和骄傲呢。


</影评>
<有用数>121</有用数>
<没用数>0</没用数>
</review>
</reviews>
</movie>
