<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
<电影名>快乐的人们 Happy People: A Year in the Taiga</电影名>
<年份>2012</年份>
<评分>8.7</评分>
<封面>https://img2.doubanio.com/view/photo/s_ratio_poster/public/p1813037653.jpg</封面>
<导演>沃纳·赫尔佐格 / 德米特里.瓦萨科夫</导演>
<演员>沃纳·赫尔佐格</演员>
<简介>地球上的天堂在哪里？通过赫尔佐格的镜头，那就是巴赫塔，位于俄罗斯北部叶尼塞河畔的一个村庄，他与导演德米特里.瓦萨科夫捕捉了当地人的生活，砍伐树木，建造渔船，捕鱼，收货食物，漫长的冬季和四季，加上他们分享的观点。</简介>
<reviews>
<review>
<作者>雪上飞鸿</作者>
<作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2013-10-12 20:48:35</时间>
<影评>
        今天刚看，还是一向的赫尔佐格的风格，内敛，冷静的记录着一个村庄的人们在一年四季的生活，有勤劳的，也有酗酒的机会主义者，还有猎人口中道出的自己的贪婪同行，能最终在这片茫茫的西伯利亚针叶林里生活快乐的秘诀其实是：勤劳，取之有道，顺应季节和万物的生长。非常像咱们中国的道家文化，而赫尔佐格为了透露这个秘诀也耗费了整整一年，非常欣赏他这种润物细无声的风格，当镜头最后落在那只奔跑的哈士奇身上的身上，我想连赫尔佐格都很羡慕那只紧紧跟随在主人身后但整个风雪长路却始终没有乘雪橇的狗吧：自由，独立，忠诚。和自己敦厚却不失智慧的主人永远的归属在这片雪白的净土之上...
      </影评>
<有用数>26</有用数>
<没用数>1</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>小是小非</作者>
<作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2014-03-27 19:20:10</时间>
<影评>
        这里的春天冰河溶解，流动，缓缓而壮观；夏天有铺天盖地的蚊子；秋天人们和金花鼠一齐收集松果，用比锤哥的还霸气的大锤子。

他们的春夏秋都是在为冬天做准备。因为冬天是狩猎的季节。


“现在，猎人们只身闯荡。他们回归了自己的本来面目，快乐的人们。只有几只狗陪伴着，远离故土。他们完全靠自己。他们自由自在，没有规则，没有税收，没有政府，没有法律，没有官僚组织，没有电话，没有收音机。只带着他们自己的价值观和行为准则。”


从一个猎房到另一个猎房，在这个taiga林的世界中，掌握所有的生存技能，摸索与狗的相处方式，见证空旷、寒冷与沉寂之美。这一切就是他们的快乐。


看着雪地摩托在针叶林间和冰面穿行，好想哭。我也有过类似的快乐，和他们相比，就像一眨眼那么短。


这部片子也感觉有点短。这样的快乐永远看不够。
      </影评>
<有用数>22</有用数>
<没用数>2</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>最后一代沉树</作者>
<作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2017-05-06 22:14:44</时间>
<影评>

Happy People: A Year in the Taiga: Documentary or Poetry?
http://postdefiance.com/happy-people-a-year-in-the-taiga-documentary-or-poetry/

Nobody tells me what to do…I am my own man.
Such is the claim of one of the virile characters in Happy People: A Year in the Taiga, a documentary co-directed by Dmitry Vasyukov and the prolific German filmmaker Werner Herzog.
These words seem familiar to an American audience, almost stereotypical of the mentality by which we are regularly defined. But the words are spoken by a Russian sable trapper living in the middle of Siberia with nary an outlet to civilization as we know it. “Amurrican?” Far from it.
The film follows a year in the lives of sable trappers in a remote Bakhtian village: a year that, like every other, is a quest to survive the harsh conditions. Herzog and Vasyukov present the narrative as a slice-of-life drama, an everyday epic for which the camera crew is merely along for the ride.
Herzog and company are enthralled with the lives of the men they’re following. In fact, the directorial duo seems more than glad to cooperate with the decidedly masculine culture they document. Women make brief and obligatory appearances; the rest of the time, we spectators follow the Russian men through the wilderness and let Herzog’s narration wash over us.
When that smooth German accent does its best, it easily persuades us of the extraordinary nature of the men we’re watching. Yet Herzog’s narration can be just a little problematic. At one point he rises to sublime heights of description/sinks into the worst kind of glorified othering:
“Now, out on their own, the trappers become what they essentially are: happy people. Accompanied only by their dogs, they live off the land. They are completely self-reliant. They are truly free. No rules, no taxes, no government, no laws, no bureaucracy, no phones, no radio, equipped only with their individual values and standard of conduct.”
As this voiceover overlaps with symphonic music, we see footage of a man steering a canoe upriver by means of an outboard motor. Herzog goes on to tell us that this man’s name is Mikhail Tarkovsky, relation of the acclaimed Russian film director Andrei Tarkovsky. In a truly odd juxtaposition, the film insists on the technological self-sufficiency of the Taiga people, while aligning them with modern advancements like the internal combustion engine and one of the most technologically advanced forms of art: cinema.
And Herzog’s narration isn’t the only aspect that rings less as documentary and more as poetry. The invisibility of the camera’s presence that makes this otherwise lovely journey is also problematic. A documentary common practice, to be sure, but Herzog is among the most adept and savvy of documentarians; he knows what he’s doing when he makes the choice to keep the presence of a non-native film crew completely out of the camera’s field of vision. The technique potentially ignores the camera’s very real and very foreign presence on that home turf, keeping at arm’s length a world that it conflictingly wants to bring within our reach.
By distancing the audience from the Siberian snow and its inhabitants, Herzog is free to perform a documentary of poetry, a free-form ode to an idealized people that he profoundly admires and wants us to admire, too. And what’s wrong with poetry? Nothing, of course…but beware of poetry masquerading as simple history.
To be fair, Herzog acknowledges the presence of chainsaws and snowmobiles in this land of self-reliance. And the camera records myriad other technologies that have somehow made their way into this inaccessible wilderness. And herein lies the real hazard of Herzog’s hidden camera: there is no such thing as a “pure” culture since every culture is the progeny and interpretation of others. By holding aloft the Taiga people as “other,” therefore perhaps better, idealization becomes falsification.
Herzog wants us to see this world as unblemished by all that is modern, a time warp into an edenic realm. In so doing, he makes choices about what we see and what we don’t. But enough contradictions slip through the cracks to reveal his construal of this society.
Even a glorified interpretation is an interpretation, not equal to the original.
But to be even more fair, the subjects that Happy People documents deserve our attention. As we complain about spotty 4G service and navel-gaze about “the nature of art” and other such privileged questions, there remain folks in this world whose isolation brings out something we are unlikely to see in ourselves.
When the Siberian trapper says he is his own man, he says it without the pretense that we almost reflexively hear in such a statement. He knows his dependence on the land, the ecosystem of which he is a part. When he recounts his dog’s death at the hands of a bear, we are not likely to roll our eyes at his tears, perceiving his reliance on and love for an animal whose loyalty allowed him to keep on living.
The moral of this story is not: “Eat your dinner; there are starving children in Africa.” On the other hand, it’s not far from it.   

 第二篇：  by   |  Steven Boone  
http://www.rogerebert.com/reviews/happy-people-a-year-in-the-taiga-2013
Film director Werner Herzog's voice is so distinct and soothing that those of us who swear by it as a tonic for the soul sometimes assume the man is a household name. I made that mistake recently while chatting with a friend who praised Christoph Waltz's performance in "Django Unchained." "Yeah," I said, "The only person who could play a multilingual, multi-genius German impresario better than Waltz would have been Herzog."
"Wha? What's a hearse hog?"
I played her Herzog's reading of the children's book Go the Fuck to Sleep and his narration for Ramin Bahrani's short film "Plastic Bag." She was hooked. The mellifluous German accent, that rising-falling modulation, worked its magic.
And that was just Werner lending his singular sound to other people's projects.
Herzog's voiceover narration has been as powerful a utility for his own potentially ponderous documentaries as Clint Eastwood's profile has been for the latter's tough-guy dramas. The films could probably stand on their own merits without That Voice, but why should they?
Like "Grizzly Man," Herzog's latest documentary, "Happy People: A Year in the Taiga" is mostly built around another filmmaker's priceless footage. Russian videographer Dmitry Yasyukov shot four documentaries about Russian fur trappers in the Siberian Taiga, a remote wilderness larger than the whole of the United States. Herzog happened upon the films at an L.A. friend's house and became as obsessed with their beauty as he once was with Timothy Treadwell's footage of grizzly bears.
His authorial signature comes through in the way he edits the material and gives it meaningful context through narration. It's a touching gesture, one filmmaker finding the glory in another's images and amplifying it through his own generous and idiosyncratic vision. What Herzog gleans from Yaskyuov's exhaustive material is a simple observation: The men of the Taiga are heroes of rugged individualism.
“They live off the land and are self reliant, truly free,” Herzog intones, as a Klaus Badelt score works to send a chill of admiration up our spines. “No rules, no taxes, no government, no laws, no bureaucracy, no phones, no radio, equipped only with their individual values and standard of conduct.”
In nearly every Herzog documentary there is a speech like this one, wherein the director reveals in plain language his passion for his subject. This particular song of praise says that people who live simply, honestly and responsibly are generally happy people. It also sings of tradition more eloquently than Teyve in "Fiddler on the Roof." Work and tradition abide. One hunter boasts that his skill is an inheritance of a thousand years of practice and refinement.
There is another way to interpret Yasyukov's material, as a bleak, miserablist view of the hunters' circumstances that emphasizes the fact that they hardly ever have a moment's rest. Work is a constant, and nature always threatens to freeze, drown, starve or (in the form of aggressive bears) eat them. This is the perspective a young Herzog might have chosen. “Overwhelming and collective murder” is how he described nature during the making of his bleakest, angriest epic, "Fitzcarraldo." (His grandiose rants were just as fun to listen to when they were depressing.)
Instead, this time we get celebratory scenes of a hunter and his son serenely enduring mosquitoes that swarm over every centimeter of exposed flesh during a dank Taiga summer. Yasyukov's footage exhaustively documents the hunters' work processes, so Herzog uses it to take us through each step of making mosquito repellent from scratch. (To my surprise, it's similar to preparing old-fashioned blackface.)
Though they use manufactured equipment like snowmobiles and wear some presumably factory-made clothing, much of the technology these trappers and their families employ is built from scratch. In a fascinating segment that suggests Herzog and Yasyukov would produce great instructional DVDs ("How to Survive the Apocalypse"), a hunter shows us how to make wooden skis that will outlast the most expensive synthetic designer ones.
Fascination with processes and with the men who master them to become expert woodsmen leaves Herzog no time to address their wives and children, whom we glimpse only at hunting sendoffs and when the men return to their homes loaded down with quarry. Whatever routines occupy the wives is of little interest to either Yasyukov or Herzog. What we do catch of them says that they, too, are very happy people. “I'm alone again,” one wife says, as her man heads out on another long expedition. In a typical arthouse fiction film, she would be the face of uncertainty and despair in that moment. In "Happy People," she just states the fact with a bittersweet smile. Herzog cuts away (or Yasyukov's cameraman stops recording) quickly.
The dogs, on the other hand, receive rapturous attention. One thing I learned from "Happy People" is that a dog in the Taiga is like a horse in the American Frontier: not merely a “best friend” but a lifeline. A brooding hunter becomes emotional when recalling a dog who gave up her life defending him from a bear attack. We see the dogs set to work with military discipline. Herzog adds some stirring, heartening Badelt music to a scene of a dog keeping pace with his master's snowmobile for nearly a hundred miles.
So the focus is tight, but the love comes through in many ways. Herzog mentions that one of the fishermen who shot some of the footage is a relative of the great Russian filmmaker Andrei Tarkovsky. The instant that name came up, I was struck with memories of all the odes to Russia's natural beauty in Tarkovsky's nostalgic films. It made me consider that Herzog might have taken on this project as a gesture of German-Russian relations—an interdependent association now, but historically one of horrific wars. Imagine a Japanese filmmaker celebrating Chinese traditions. (Actually, there are films like Kenji Mizoguchi's Japanese take on Chinese history, "Princess Yang Kwei-fei," and they tend to be weirdly interesting.)
The fact that Herzog shot none of the footage comes across most strongly when we briefly visit a couple of indigenous Taiga people. They build a boat with staggering precision, row it out onto the icy waters, and then they are gone from the film. I can't imagine Herzog having access to folks whose traditions go even further back than the Russians leaving it at that.
All of this apparent Walden-like freedom struck close to home for me—or would, if I had a home. I stepped off the grid in New York City four years ago, trying to find a simpler way to live that would free me of corporate wage-slavery. Four years later, I've found that such freedom is virtually impossible in American cities. To live as free and clear as the men of the Taiga do, I would have to go to a farm, a commune—or the Taiga. On a landscape of concrete, there is no hunting or homesteading, just purchasing and renting. Parks and community gardens preserve some testy relationship with the natural world, but, let's face it, the world I and most folks reading this essay occupy keeps us dependent upon corporate delivery systems for our survival essentials. Are we happy this way?
Herzog, whose films have captured ecstatic faces in prisons, asylums, rainforests and arctic base camps, would probably answer, “That is up to you, my friend. You must work with whatever you have been given,” in a voice that could make a man caught in a bear trap smile.


</影评>
<有用数>7</有用数>
<没用数>1</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>心暖与我安</作者>
<作者评分>4</作者评分>
<时间>2018-08-08 10:35:11</时间>
<影评>

最近看快乐的人们，一部纪录片，讲一群生活在西伯利亚的人们一年四季如何生活的，砍伐树木，建造渔船，捕鱼，收货食物之类的。这部纪录片的名字虽然叫快乐的生活，但条件真的很艰苦，感觉完全快乐不起来。冬天，大雪纷飞，那个寒冷劲儿，压在屋顶上的雪会把屋顶压垮。而夏天，到处都是蚊子，不管是人还是狗，都被蚊子包围着，只有在出风口才能稍微好一点。猎人们就用土办法，自己熬焦油，给自己、小孩子、家里的猎狗，都涂上厚厚的一层焦油，晚上洗澡把它洗掉，第二天依次往复。

可是这样艰苦的生活条件，依然可以很快乐，原因就在于可以发挥人的自主性。就像一个老猎人说，在前苏联时期，他最喜欢被分到当猎人的工作，因为没有人催促，没有人指挥，他可以自己决定什么时候开始、什么时候休息，他拥有充分自由。虽然条件很艰苦，但他们却可以用双手去制造工具，用工具去克服各种困境，这样的生活，虽然很艰苦，却很有滋味。

在现代生活中，我们常常会犯拖延症啊什么的，一方面是因为我们已经被现代技术给宠坏了，习惯了即时享乐、有求马上应的生活节奏；另一方面可能是因为我们要做的很多事情都是被安排的。一个人主动去做什么，和他被安排去做什么，哪怕是一样的事情，但是感受是截然不同。你有没有发现对于你喜欢做的事情，哪怕没有被安排，哪怕很艰难，你都是甘之如饴、乐此不疲的。

所以呢对症下药，要想跨过拖延症，一方面是延迟享受，把手机掏出来耍的时候，先数120下。另一方面，真诚的对面对工作和生活，不喜欢的事情先拒绝一下，拒绝不了再做，你也对得起自己了。对于喜欢做的事情，就持之不懈的坚持下去，哪怕没有什么产出，享受这个过程本身就是一个胜利了。如果没有发现自己特别感兴趣的事情，那么不妨多尝试一下、发掘一下，多给自己机会。特别是如果你像我一样，小时候沉迷学习，没有机会发展兴趣爱好，不妨长大了补一下这门功课，多探索一下自己的未知性。其实想想，我们一直急着去了解别人、建立关系，为什么不先静下心来，了解一下自己、探索一下自己、宠爱一下自己、做自己最好的小伙伴？

</影评>
<有用数>13</有用数>
<没用数>1</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>暁</作者>
<作者评分></作者评分>
<时间>2020-08-03 18:50:40</时间>
<影评>

Happy People: A Year in the Taiga 2010 Dmitry Vasyukov, Werner Herzog
看了小森林后想起Herzog这部纪录片 森林中的猎人和狗 同样是表现一种前工业时代的生活方式 猎人的话清醒至极 显然他对自己的生活有充分的自省 他说“猎人是诚实的” 爱他得猎狗 知道如何训练他们 但仍然和他们保持距离 他清楚人和家畜之间的情感和界限 人和自然之间的法则 人从未凌驾于自然之上 只存在于自然之间 这个朴素的思想可以推及到现代社会 尽管在人类视角下似乎是智人主宰了地球和地球上其他种类生物 但这和蚂蚁筑建巨大的蚁穴并无两样 倾覆只是一夕风雨 人类为之自傲的文明即使以地球的时间尺度衡量也只是沧海桑田
这个猎人几乎是同Herzog的镜头一样冷静而理性 他过着一种质朴理性的生活 康德的道德律和星空同存于猎人心中
记得尼采好像也说过类似的话 人类的平静生活需要仿效西伯利亚农村和东方的村落中的生活态度 但这并非在否定工业社会和现代文化 城市中有太多的影响人判断力的表象和遮蔽 未被现代工业开发过的森林和农村环境相对简单 人对自我的认识和感受也就相对清晰  而现代人对自我和自我感受的要求空前提高 代表或者伪装成这类文化的消费产品也逐渐占据市场 用消费满足精神需求从来都是饮鸩止渴 另一类人回归理性式禁欲甚至宗教式禁欲 历史已经证明违反人类自然欲望的行为最终会导致更多的危机 制度的不完善和理性的不完善导致现代社会最终的方向危机重重 历史的终结不会是现代社会 而是世界大战 核危机 流行疫病 外星人 或者彗星撞地球

</影评>
<有用数>2</有用数>
<没用数>0</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>屁点</作者>
<作者评分>4</作者评分>
<时间>2019-01-24 00:05:19</时间>
<影评>

人的本质是自由自在地劳动。
1.挑选木材制作滑雪板，买的滑雪板滑15公里就提不动脚，但自制的滑雪板可以无忧无虑一直滑（超薄且弹性十足的两块薄木板 用麻绳系在鞋上）妈蛋顿时觉得滑雪鞋怎么那么傻呢
2.制作独木舟 一门古老的技艺（唯一能感同身受的事情是皮划艇泛舟湖上真的好快乐啊）
4.夏天摸焦油防蚊子
3.捕鱼 没有什么能比得上新鲜的鱼
4.猎人和狗 忠诚的伙伴 猎人讲述他的狗被熊撕碎的故事 感人至深
5.什么是快乐 一个男人 一条狗 一把斧子 广袤的森林和雪地 生存是唯一的规则 自由所以快乐
6.猎人的哲学 朴实 深刻 
一个圈养的城市人能去想象和羡慕荒野猎人的快乐吗？我老在想，自己对田园牧歌的憧憬是一种幻想吗，如果自然的劳作最快乐，那农村人为什么愿意进城，说明手机还是比种地好玩，种地还是苦。猎人说一条狗关了6个月就会永远丧失能力，办公室坐久了，格子间就是天地。
归根结底，无论干什么，能吃苦，才配得上自由。

</影评>
<有用数>8</有用数>
<没用数>1</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>豆面茶</作者>
<作者评分></作者评分>
<时间>2020-02-11 13:51:00</时间>
<影评>

这里的快乐 来自于猎人们应季的生活 从生活中获取的哲学 继续投入到生活当中 例如猎人与狗的相处 狗喂饱猎人 猎人也喂饱狗 为了让狗远离陷阱 把狗关进陷阱而不是棒打
看到克季河本地搬运河床浮木的工人关于酗酒说道：你看 我们喝的醉醺醺的 做些零工（另一人搭话说都怪俄罗斯人发明的伏特加）不 这是我们自己的错 有些人过得很好 如果你愿意 你可以过日子做工作 如果不想 那除了喝酒还能做什么？至于该怪谁 我不知道 这很难回答。失去传统手艺无以为继，老人与年轻人都不多的当代，虽然Taiga地处边远，也许同样受到了现代工业的冲击，以至于无所适从
想到顾桃的《雨果的假期》《敖鲁古雅 敖鲁古雅》《狂达罕》酗酒的诗人失去了心中的信仰，失去了祖辈赖以生存的生活方式，回不去的家园，无法融入的山下，只能靠酒精麻痹自己得到须臾的轻松快乐吧。
相比之下 Taiga的猎人们依然保有自己的生活方式 夏天准备 冬天捕猎 算是充实快乐的吧

</影评>
<有用数>2</有用数>
<没用数>0</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>狐狸</作者>
<作者评分>4</作者评分>
<时间>2019-01-13 22:54:01</时间>
<影评>

平静，自然，客观的记录世外桃源的猎人生活，虽然是老片子了，没啥牛逼的拍摄工具和手法，顶多就点水下拍摄和直升机航拍了，但至少不矫情，不摆大道理（这里是对比舌尖三，好好说个吃的呗，动不动就升华干嘛）。就是认认真真的说了猎人的一年四季的生活和村庄的一点群像，都是日常小事，在猎人的实际言行中不着痕迹的描绘了自己独特的人生观与价值观。孤独的人生与静谧的的大自然深深拥抱，关照自我。想想现在充满欲望的社会与浮躁的我，就需要一个孤独静谧的自然环境来做做禅啊

</影评>
<有用数>1</有用数>
<没用数>0</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>大橘子</作者>
<作者评分>4</作者评分>
<时间>2017-03-14 14:51:00</时间>
<影评>
        只是觉得对于被猎狗追捕的紫貂来说太残酷。自然本身也是残酷的，但人类远比猛兽残酷太多，猛兽的残酷是出于生存饱腹，而人类的残酷已经超越生存，多的是欲望、财富、权利。当然活在城市的人更没资格说这些，对于动物的杀戮，城市人虽然没有亲自动手，但是我们的欲望和金钱是比猎刀锋利太多的杀戮工具。猎人至少是诚实的。


当然这片比如今影院的电影要强N倍。
      </影评>
<有用数>10</有用数>
<没用数>1</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>冰胡墩子爱踢球</作者>
<作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2022-10-21 20:05:00</时间>
<影评>

在我们的认知框架下，这种纯净的、往复的生活是快乐，但对真正处于那种生活中的人来说，没有什么快乐不快乐，只是平静的生活，一天又一天。但话说回来，平静大概就是最能留得住的快乐了。 印象最深的是，猎人说他们不是完成一件事情，只是成为了这件事情的一部分。这让我想起顺流而下的小船，顺应自然生活的作为动物的人。对他们来说，日子本身没有好坏，只是顺应日子做该做的事情，下雨涨水可以运东西，下雪了就用上滑雪板，结冰了就可以度过河流。 然后又想起本世纪兴起的正念疗法，在发展前额叶这么多年之后，在追求认知复杂度这么多年之后，我们又开始想要抓住最简单的知觉，仿佛一个成人，想要再次追求孩子那样的感受；一个享受了灯红酒绿的人，想要回到一片白雪皑皑的荒原。 

</影评>
<有用数>1</有用数>
<没用数>0</没用数>
</review>
</reviews>
</movie>
