<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<movie>
<电影名>达格雷街风情 Daguerréotypes</电影名>
<年份>1976</年份>
<评分>8.6</评分>
<封面>https://img1.doubanio.com/view/photo/s_ratio_poster/public/p2243184377.jpg</封面>
<导演>阿涅斯·瓦尔达</导演>
<演员>阿涅斯·瓦尔达</演员>
<简介>讲述了新浪潮教母阿涅斯·瓦尔达又一动人的纪录长片，Daguerréotypes原指法国画家达盖尔于1839年发明的“达盖尔银版摄影术“（此后世界上诞生了第一台可携式木箱照相机）,而达格雷街则是瓦尔达在巴黎居住的街道·她由靠近自己家门的“蓝蓟花“杂货店出发，将视觉范围渐渐地扩大到整条街上的商铺以及在其中辛勤工作的人们，并以一名在街上表演的话痨魔术师为梭，将整部电影以一种奇妙的方式——魔术师的絮絮叨叨成为商铺顾客与店员，店主行为动作的良好注解——串联起来。</简介>
<reviews>
<review>
<作者>阿拉蕾</作者>
<标题>一切美好空缺</标题><作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2016-03-24 01:34:04</时间>
<影评>

熟悉又陌生的感觉，仿佛一切可以回到从前，尽管一幅幅场景的对比教人心里浸润了辛酸和感怀，对真实的贪婪使我不禁大口吮吸这街上的气味。
瓦尔达献给没身于无数纵横交错大街小巷的无名邻居一首小而轻的奏鸣曲，不吝于揭短，依旧充满了爱悯地打量，即使那刻薄市侩的赌马人也透着可爱的自然。
没有功夫做梦的人们，在一个蹩脚魔术师营造的斑斓幻术中像孩童般惊讶和满足，他们不曾留意日复一日店铺橱窗上流逝的时间，等待的眼神究竟不是在期盼金钱到来，更像是追问这永恒的节奏（钟摆）、无稽的价值，莫名地渴盼着黄昏出走，即便只是跨出那扇门。
看着店里的人数着纽扣、取一盒牛奶、在牛肋条左右割下小块肥腻…这些平时毫不起眼的动作此刻引我们看得津津有味，不同的手各自经久地游弋形成空间内的气场和韵力，一切和鸣最终归入相似的寂静旋律，一如“蓝蓟花”夫人沉郁幽闭的神态，一切的结束、一切的开端，只是一系列被抽离出空间的时间定格，沾满了生命或别的迹象，叫芸芸众生一下子高大起来。


</影评>
<有用数>8</有用数>
<没用数>0</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>不建议批发</作者>
<标题>在我心中，这就是新浪潮</标题><作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2021-07-14 22:47:28</时间>
<影评>

看完了，只能说这一部就能激发到我自己的创作欲。可能我还是太年轻，看得太太太少了，知识面狭隘让我对好的艺术品碰到了就特激动，就特别有三分钟热度大喊“我也想做这种作品我也可以！”花了两天看完今天这个半小时很多细节我还调回去重看。虽说这是一条街道的纪录片，却包含了太多普通人真挚的爱情，衰老，日常，记忆的偏颇，对于爱情的态度。
如电影所说，有不少黄昏后想离开世界的时刻，而我作为我正常的梦就像一个个牢笼，让我在每日的繁琐当中扩大所有恐惧的方面。很庆幸原来我不是唯一。
早前法国影展的时候，朋友问我，“你来讲讲什么是新浪潮？”
我可能会用《美好的五月》和《达格雷街风情》回复他，这就是。
是小人物的大思想，是小街区的风情，总有一个普通的时刻会和你碰撞出不普通。而不是陈腔滥调的情节剧，而是真实的挣扎和新奇的思想跳跃。
新浪潮真美！

</影评>
<有用数>1</有用数>
<没用数>0</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>风马</作者>
<标题>笔记</标题><作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2022-07-24 11:27:35</时间>
<影评>

摒弃了宏大叙事的现实主义生活智慧
特别的片头 - acknowledge工作人员，mini documentary/纪实 about the film’s making (think: Mugler campaign中结尾的”The name is Mugler. Remember and remember it well.”)
What’s a documentary? Difference between a documentary and a film; Performance &amp; camera - to what degree is a film-documentary scripted? Acknowledgement of the camera  
太空、魔术、日常生活、科学、梦境
32mins左右的剪辑(grated cheese &amp; rice)
33:50; 34:18; 50mins (also think: Chaïm Soutine) audio &amp; video disjunction; 魔术音频作为一些clip的narration; 剪辑中对于相关的联想很有创意：钱、火、切割、折叠，既The Gleaners and I探讨了社会职责的overlap (gleaners of food &amp; gleaneuse of images; magicians of everyday life &amp; magician of illusions)
爱情故事 - 心有所依
世外桃源般的小镇生活，似乎是现实生活，有似乎把现实生活的起起落落以平常心展现，那是一种浪漫的英雄主义
1:07:40
“我相当的多愁善感。所以，我梦想逝去的都会回来”

</影评>
<有用数>0</有用数>
<没用数>0</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>float_x</作者>
<标题>1975年，Varda探店达格雷街的一天</标题><作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2022-04-20 23:09:15</时间>
<影评>

用法语单词的双重含义，引出 从早到晚的达格雷街。
是瓦尔达眼里的邻居，也是瓦尔达在1975年达格雷街探店的一天。


片头念职员表 红字小心思 玻璃倒映摄制组 
击中。
给肉
珍贵的是 镜头的存在像个店铺常客 似乎没让他们过于紧张
该发呆发呆  衣服肩膀破洞  
面糊包浆的法棍筐 切完肉直接手往围裙一抹（包肉用牛皮纸像包糖一样 可爱）
门口聊八卦 清晨扫地 抓拍黑乎乎的脏手不给握 
香水针织店、肉店、理发店、裁缝店、面包店、手风琴店、练车教练、日杂牛奶店
摄影式纪录片


魔术师变魔术、店主采访的话头话尾  互相衔接。
魔术变钱时 画面依次是店铺收银瞬间 旁白仍是魔术现场（ps口金包真可爱）
魔术表演吞火时 画面跳转面包师傅正把法棍推进火炉
魔术表演用刀扎手臂时 画面跳转肉店老板切肉骨
平行交叉蒙太奇 顽皮。

超级可爱！想去买肉！

就 美

阿姨奶奶们 穿得太好看了。



采访夫妻店主 对彼此初次见面的记忆
聊家常的氛围 温暖。
是散文 是诗 是散漫的严肃。
每个人都像落日。
像回家路上骑自行车 迎风下坡 忽然想通了点什么。

影像是什么呢？
就是写字人的笔和纸，做衣服人的布和剪刀。



</影评>
<有用数>1</有用数>
<没用数>0</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>Gymnopedie</作者>
<标题>瓦尔达重映</标题><作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2020-02-17 15:33:33</时间>
<影评>

大阪梅田loft地下一楼的电影院从这周开始会放三部瓦尔达，选了估计日后重映机会比较少的《达格雷街风情》，巴黎平民街上的人物志。
就跟瓦尔达的其他作品一样，时间才是真正的主题，这次镜头对准了商店橱窗内部缓慢流动的时间，开门关门，人来人往，日升日落，各行各业的商铺主人们讲述着各自的家庭记忆。将魔术师的表演片段和日常生活中的特写镜头剪辑到一起的平行蒙太奇非常有趣，既完成了对神秘的超自然巫术的祛魅，同时也赋予了循环往复的手工劳动不一样的意义。在魔术师的催眠表演中间穿插人们的梦话访谈，又像是在探讨梦境与现实的关联；随着催眠术进一步施行，电影中所有的音效完全消失，配合上橱窗背后一幅幅静止的全家福，本来拥有自觉性的人仿佛变成了提线木偶，由此产生了一种超现实主义的氛围。
魔术师在表演之前所说的话也非常有意思：人类已经登上了月球，还拍出了很多科幻电影，现在请大家想像我们来到了数千年之后，在不同的星球上有着不同的幻术……虽然表演的内容跟任何一个国家的街头魔术并无二致，但叙述过程中的语境确实反映出了那个年代宇宙主义的盛行。

</影评>
<有用数>1</有用数>
<没用数>0</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>夜礼服假面</作者>
<标题>转自REVERSESHOT：The Little Universe</标题><作者评分 />
<时间>2019-04-03 21:04:57</时间>
<影评>

The Little Universe
Julien Allen on Daguerréotypes | October 3, 2016
"What is this film? A reportage, an homage, a regret, a reproach? An overture?" —Agnès Varda
Streets in France, by a clear majority, are named after people: heroes of the patrie(fatherland) for the most part, such as presidents and generals, but also artists and writers . . . and inventors. One unprepossessing suburb of Paris, just west of Versailles, with the optimistic name of “Plaisir,” has a whole bank of streets named only for French film directors: Vigo, Truffaut, Tati, Carné, Pagnol, Clair. As for Agnès Varda, there are two streets in France that bear her name, as well as a “Traverse Agnès Varda,” a tiny gap between two rows of houses on the quayside in the southern town of Sète, near Montpellier, where Varda grew up.
There is a street in the 14th arrondissement of Paris named after one of the pioneers of photography, Louis-Jacques-Mandé Daguerre, whose giant lifelike photographic portraits (“daguerreotypes”) first entranced Parisians 170 years ago. When Varda moved to the capital to study history and photography at the École des Beaux Arts in the late forties, she lived on the rue Daguerre and stayed in that neighborhood for over twenty-five years, regularly passing by the local boutiques, wondering to herself why so many of the window displays never seemed to change. Gradually overcome by a growing sense of guilt and curiosity, in 1975 Varda finally ripped off the sticking-plaster and brought her camera to this tiny place (one block of the street between numbers 70 and 90) mindful that the onrush of modernity—a modernity of which Varda herself was artistically and politically at the absolute forefront—meant that its frozen-in-time aesthetic could be on the cusp of disappearing. Having promised her neighbors that she would use only her own electricity supply to shoot—and being tied to home in any event by a new baby—she created an electrical umbilical cord which she ran from her house to power her equipment, ensuring that on a daily basis she could not film further than 90 meters from her own doorstep. The resultant 80-minute marvel, Daguerréotypes, is part reportage and part existential reflection, and Varda’s delicate assemblage of artistic methodologies—poetry, portrait photography, painting, illusionism, documentary filmmaking—serve to create not just a devastatingly elegiac social portrait but also an open meditation on the nature and value of Agnès Varda’s art. Even in the context of a body of work that more or less exemplifies the concept of personal cinema, Daguerréotypes is as close to a self-portrait as you can get without being one.
The film begins with the sort of quaintly demonstrative foreplay which Daguerre himself might have used in a Clignancourt street market to drum up popular interest in his invention. We see a caped magician, standing on the Place du Trocadéro in front of the Eiffel Tower, grandly announcing—for our entertainment and edification—a new film by Agnès Varda: Daguerréotypes! It’s a joke, because the film exhibits none of this showmanship, yet the magician himself will become a central figure in the piece: he is, like Varda, an “outsider” and he appears in the rue Daguerre for one night only. In a decision so bizarre that only Varda’s execution of it can make it seem entirely logical, he becomes like a second narrator: his multifaceted illusionist’s act (prestidigitation, escapism, fire-eating, divination, fakirism) is skillfully interlaced with the various, doggedly quotidian stories of a small number of the inhabitants and shopkeepers of the rue Daguerre, whose lives Varda crosscuts between in a fluid, rather than episodic, manner.
The first of these people we meet are an elderly man and woman who run Au Chardon Bleu, purveyors and makers of “perfume and hosiery.” They are presented standing still in the first of many forced portraits (of the kind Wes Anderson would one day be very keen on) framed in their own shop doorway as the camera rolls, as if they were posing rather awkwardly for Daguerre himself. Filming the wife, who is ever present in the shop but strangely passive, Varda the narrator sees the “softness of a captive,” apparently alluding to her decades of quiet, unyielding service to the same small business. During the course of the film as we return now and again to their story, the wife will not speak, but her husband pays warm and dignified homage to her skill as a seamstress. He is coy when asked about his initial attraction to her, mentioning that he is glad she kept her hair long and explaining that when he met her at a local ball as a young woman, she was “decent” to him. She is no longer capable of making hosiery, which is why the Chardon Bleu is now just a parfumerie instead of a parfumerie-bonneterie. Later in the film, we see her incongruously touching the coat of one of her customers, who half recoils in confusion. It dawns on the customer and viewer that she might have dementia, which is later confirmed. Her captivity is her condition.
As we witness these inhabitants responding to Varda’s unbroadcasted open questions with little fractured speeches (which, when they remain uninterrupted, often continue beyond the initial comfort barrier of the speaker), we may feel a peculiar sense of aesthetic familiarity. Varda’s cameraman is William Lubtchansky, who debuted on Varda’s Elsa la rose and who, a decade later, would film the testimonies of the Polish townspeople in Claude Lanzmann’s Shoah in a vividly similar way, allowing them to more or less unwittingly develop their “characters” for the film. Furthermore, Varda takes trouble to film the temps morts (dead time) when the shops are empty and the characters’ lives seem emptier still. Lubtchansky regularly holds the image for some time after the essential activity on screen has stopped, in the manner of Bresson (who in L’argent would cut a scene only when the sound of action that has left the frame—such as footsteps—has also left our earshot). This technique goes to the heart of Varda’s initial curiosity: how much of these people’s lives is spent waiting, wondering when the next customer would come, and how did they fill this time? Many of them fuss around the shop finding tasks, others sit and contemplate the world outside, they visit each other’s shops; the bakery’s closure routine is captured lovingly, in homage to the boulangère’s dedication to routine. Varda questions the characters in turn about their dreams, but not in the sense of their goals or ambitions—she wants to know their actual dreams: what they dream at night and whether they dream in the day, when the empty time comes around. As they respond hesitantly (“I dream of work”; “I dream only occasionally, sentimental dreams, mostly”), Varda the narrator grasps at her own interpretation: “We’re all undoubtedly prisoners of our lives. For those who are proud of being normal, the dream is an illness. They would rather talk of their professional anxieties than their inner thoughts.”
This approach to filming her “daguerreotypes” (which include a butcher, a baker, a clockmaker, an ironmonger, a tailor, and a lovable driving instructor) reveals Varda’s technical mastery of narrative: her juxtaposition and foreshadowing are delicately judged and her clever use of withholding, parallels, and joins is effortless. But it also goes some way to illustrating the uniqueness of her contribution to cinema, one that firmly disavows the somewhat reductive (not to mention insulting) given title of “grandmother of the New Wave.” For Varda’s work has never existed by reference, or in reappraisal, of what has gone before, nor via a reaction to what is going on at the time, rather it has always operated self-sufficiently and quite separately from her contemporaries and successors: not in a vacuum as such, more of a warm, fecund glasshouse where the richest plants can flourish, lovingly tended to by a patient expert grower. If the cool, flitty insouciance of the exterior camerawork and the messy, unfiltered noise of Parisian streets in Daguerréotypes might conjure up a Rivette of Out 1 or even a Godard of Breathless there is nevertheless a tangible distinction in Varda’s work, which goes further than the distinction between documentary and fiction, and lies in the film’s sense of personal engagement: the filmmaker is humbler and more in thrall to her subject, more uncertain, more directly affected, more vulnerable…and therefore much braver.
This ambitious commitment to her own uncertainty is even true of Varda’s first fiction features, especially in her treatment of the heroine of Cléo from 5 to 7, where there is no sense that the editing of Cléo’s journey around Paris is designed to create cohesion in her character or her circumstances. Varda’s rigorous, disciplined humility is affirmed by the quote at the top of this piece, which comes from the final lines of narration of Daguerreotypes. Allied to her artistic confidence (as if to say, “Whatever transpires here, I will back myself to find a way of presenting it, even if there may not be a name for what it eventually is”), this combination epitomizes liberated, veritably “independent” cinema. Where too many filmmakers arrive at a project with a certain number of preset ingredients (a script, a structure, a thematic concept, or at least an angle), Varda begins at the molecular level and builds outward, letting her various subjects—and their own processes, as prompted by Varda—dictate the creative decisions that she takes. This is conspicuous in more high-profile documentary projects (such as Jane B. par Agnès V.), but it applies equally to fictions such as Vagabond, wherein Sandrine Bonnaire’s nomadic heroine appears to be writing the film’s somewhat arbitrary narrative through chance encounters, rather than following any conducting arc. Varda’s subjugation to the people or places she films and/or depicts calls to mind the role of poets in the Middle Ages who were tasked with proclaiming the greatness of kings (notwithstanding that Daguerréotypes is a study of the unremarkable).
The contrast between Varda’s subservient attitude to her work and the soapbox-wielding confidence of her public image in France at the time of filming Daguerréotypes could not be more acute. One of her characters in Daguerréotypes, quite reasonably, says, “We don’t talk politics in the shop…it’s bad for business,” yet Lubtchansky’s camera alights here and there on little details which situate the film strongly in its own political time (while the street itself seems lost in the past) and lingers on them. Examples include Brigitte Bardot on the cover of Paris Match in the hairdressers and the imminent passing of the loi Veil (legalization of abortion) headlined in a newspaper being used as a prop by the magician. Varda had been a prominent campaigner for women’s rights and was one of the first public figures to confess to a criminal offense by declaring that she had had an abortion herself. She makes no express or implied reproach of the political apathy of the “daguerreotypes,” but she permits herself to observe, subtly, how detached they have become from the world outside.
By 1993 when I visited the rue Daguerre as a student I discovered that not one of the shops featured in Daguerréotypes had survived. Since then, the replacement shops have been replaced again. Leases grow shorter; time is compressed by technological progress; where people work and where they live no longer relate to one another as before . . . so these “daguerreotypes” seem ever more like relics. Only the tiny concert hall (where the magician performs) remains, and of course, so does this film: these larger-than-life pictures, these people, will live for all time. But how can we answer Varda’s question quoted above with any certainty? What is this film? If documentary cinema is meant to uncover something, then perhaps its revelation lies in cinema’s ability to seize and compel us even while depicting a hinterland that holds no outwardly objective fascination: a world we would otherwise walk straight through.
Varda’s generosity of spirit and her career-long tendency towards self-portraiture (exhibited in Daguerréotypes through her interrogation of what she herself is thinking, as much as what her subjects are thinking) afford us the opportunity to indulge in the same exercise. Daguerréotypes is all the things Varda fears it might be, but at its heart it’s a universal overture, which all cinema can live for: let me into your world; let me know what you feel; let me learn how you live.
原帖链接：http://www.reverseshot.org/symposiums/entry/2247/daguerreotypes


</影评>
<有用数>0</有用数>
<没用数>0</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>Sabrina</作者>
<标题>谁不想跟阿涅斯住一条街上啊！</标题><作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2018-02-06 23:58:24</时间>
<影评>

看了这个纪录片你就会知道为什么40年后，已经快90岁的阿涅斯奶奶能够拍出《脸庞、村庄》这样温暖、浑然天成的纪录片了。她和丈夫也算法国顶级的艺术大师了，可他们扎根于自己的街道，无论身份地位发生了多大的变化，他们的家始终在那里。不像中国人，一有钱和地位，首先想到的就是搬家。 
这个街道就是阿涅斯奶奶生活的地方，她用摄像机拍了她的邻居，香水店、咖啡店、手风琴店、裁缝店、洗衣店、肉店、杂货店、理发店，每天生活中须臾不能够离开的邻居们。还没有被大的连锁超市，连锁咖啡店、百货商场侵蚀的巴黎的一条普通街道。
《狮子、爱、谎言》中，阿涅斯这个才华横溢、有灵气的女导演，就直接的批评了美国的电影工业，那里说话算的是生意人，而不是艺术家，他们甚至有你作品最后的剪辑权，像一个快消公司的市场部，在将产品大规模推出之前，进行小范围的测试，根据结果来决定是否要对影片重新剪辑，以获得高票房为终极目标。而阿涅斯珍视的是作为艺术家，手艺人对于作品的从头到尾的把控。
这个小街道即便是几十年过去了，当时电影中的店主都不在世了，很多店仍旧留存了下来，而且进行了精心的，细腻的改造，尤其是那个面包店的新店主，请来了艺术家，用快要失传的手艺来装饰他的店，有这样的投入，他能不好好做面包吗？
那个香水店的女主人，真的也给我留下了深刻印象，她一定是非常有灵气，心中是有翅膀的人，她优雅又神伤，每天要出去看看夕阳。
上面的内容中，有一部分是2000年后，阿涅斯在DVD花絮中给出的镜头。




</影评>
<有用数>4</有用数>
<没用数>1</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>好响亮的名字</作者>
<标题>犹如视频博物馆，穿越感</标题><作者评分>3</作者评分>
<时间>2016-05-23 10:29:37</时间>
<影评>
        时间已经不能复返，影像却可以，这是纪录片的另外的价值。

看起来导演在画面剪辑上还是费了不少心思的，前半段貌似自然的记录，到后半段更多掺入拍摄者的思想，这些都要在庞大的繁琐的胶片中去反复寻找，对号，横向纵向，前呼后应，别有用心的铺垫。

一条街上不同职业的店铺老板的日常记录，客观记录和主观剪辑的融合，如果后面的一场魔术秀串接起来，如魔术师的手跳接到各行业人们的手的语言，如人脑消失后的开箱展示跳接到店铺的关门歇业的动作，不知是导演的灵感显现还是有意而为之，在采访了老板们的各种梦境的表述后镜头切换到魔术师在召唤助手醒来的镜头，然后魔术师又对着屏幕说：“我要把你们都送人梦乡”，紧接着就是影片结尾的各种人在银板照相时的安静的合影，似乎他们在拍照的几分钟内真的进入自己的梦一样，最后的最后画面回到刚开始的老夫妇俩的画面。

个人不喜欢太过主观的意思表达，本人比较喜欢前半段部分，什么！1976那会还没有超市，什么，买面包和牛肉不用塑料袋而用两张看着类似牛皮纸的东东，什么！烫发要把脑袋钻入太空头盔，什么！买了面包棍直接用手拿，那手刚才付钱拉门了好不好，

导演是通过这样区分时间的，采访回忆初恋结婚的事表示昨天，现在手头的忙绿是今天，白日梦表示未来，最后定格在相片中，莫非是要表达？最开始是魔术师的在铁塔下的披斗篷的玄幻造型，莫非预示着一切如梦幻，呵呵

有一点看不懂，画面中几次出现蒙娜丽莎的名画，这，谁能解析下
      </影评>
<有用数>1</有用数>
<没用数>1</没用数>
</review>
</reviews>
</movie>