<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<movie>
<电影名>卓别林短片精选 The Chaplin Revue</电影名>
<年份>1959</年份>
<评分>9.1</评分>
<封面>https://img9.doubanio.com/view/photo/s_ratio_poster/public/p2534897405.jpg</封面>
<导演>查理·卓别林</导演>
<演员>查理·卓别林 / 艾伯特·奥斯汀 / 亨利·伯格曼 / 希德·卓别林 / 艾德娜·珀薇安丝 / 马克·斯旺 / 洛亚尔·安德伍德</演员>
<简介>Three Chaplin silent comedies &quot;A Dog&apos;s Life&quot;, &quot;Shoulder Arms&quot;, and &quot;The Pilgrim&quot; are strung together to form a single feature length film.</简介>
<reviews>
<review>
<作者>舒</作者>
<作者评分></作者评分>
<时间>2022-04-09 11:14:44</时间>
<影评>

当我真正开始爱自己[1]
作者：卓别林
当我真正开始爱自己，
我才认识到，
所有的痛苦和情感的折磨，
都只是提醒我：活着，不要违背自己的本心。
今天我明白了，这叫做“真实”。
当我真正开始爱自己，
我才懂得，把自己的愿望强加于人，
是多么的无礼，就算我知道，时机并不成熟，
那人也还没有做好准备，
就算那个人就是我自己。
今天我明白了，这叫做“尊重”。
当我开始爱自己，
我不再渴求不同的人生，
我知道任何发生在我身边的事情，
都是对我成长的邀请。
如今，我称之为“成熟”。
当我开始真正爱自己，
我才明白，我其实一直都在正确的时间，
正确的地方，发生的一切都恰如其分。
由此我得以平静。
今天我明白了，这叫做“自信”。
当我真正开始爱自己，
我不再牺牲自己的自由时间，
不再去勾画什么宏伟的明天。
今天我只做有趣和快乐的事，
做自己热爱，让心欢喜的事，
用我的方式、我的韵律。
今天我明白了，这叫做“单纯”。
当我开始真正爱自己，
我开始远离一切不健康的东西。
不论是饮食和人物，还是事情和环境，
我远离一切让我远离本真的东西。
从前我把这叫做“追求健康的自私自利”，
但今天我明白了，这是“自爱”。
当我开始真正爱自己，
我不再总想着要永远正确，不犯错误。
我今天明白了，这叫做“谦逊”。
当我开始真正爱自己，
我不再继续沉溺于过去，
也不再为明天而忧虑，
现在我只活在一切正在发生的当下，
今天，我活在此时此地，
如此日复一日。这就叫“完美”。
当我开始真正爱自己，
我明白，我的思虑让我变得贫乏和病态，
但当我唤起了心灵的力量，
理智就变成了一个重要的伙伴，
这种组合我称之为，“心的智慧”。
我们无须再害怕自己和他人的分歧，
矛盾和问题，因为即使星星有时也会碰在一起，
形成新的世界，今天我明白，这就是“生命”。
卓别林《当我真正开始爱自己》英文原文：[1]
AS I BEGAN TO LOVE MYSELF
CHARLIE CHAPLIN ON HIS 70TH BIRTHDAY
As I began to love myself I found that anguish and emotional suffering are only warning signs that I was living against my own truth.
Today, I know, this is AUTHENTICITY.
As I began to love myself I understood how much it can offend somebody as I try to force my desires on this person, even though I knew the time was not right and the person was not ready for it, and even though this person was me.
Today I call it RESPECT.
As I began to love myself I stopped craving for a different life, and I could see that everything that surrounded me was inviting me to grow.
Today I call it MATURITY.
As I began to love myself I understood that at any circumstance, I am in the right place at the right time, and everything happens at the exactly right moment, so I could be calm.
Today I call it SELF-CONFIDENCE.
As I began to love myself I quit steeling my own time, and I stopped designing huge projects for the future. Today, I only do what brings me joy and happiness, things I love to do and that make my heart cheer, and I do them in my own way and in my own rhythm.
Today I call it SIMPLICITY.
As I began to love myself I freed myself of anything that is no good for my health – food, people, things, situations, and everything that drew me down and away from myself. At first I called this attitude a healthy egoism.
Today I know it is LOVE OF ONESELF.
As I began to love myself I quit trying to always be right, and ever since I was wrong less of the time.
Today I discovered that is MODESTY.
As I began to love myself I refused to go on living in the past and worry about the future. Now, I only live for the moment, where EVERYTHING is happening.
Today I live each day, day by day, and I call it FULFILLMENT.
As I began to love myself I recognized that my mind can disturb me and it can make me sick. But As I connected it to my heart, my mind became a valuable ally.
Today I call this connection WISDOM OF THE HEART.
We no longer need to fear arguments, confrontations or any kind of problems with ourselves or others. Even stars collide, and out of their crashing new worlds are born.
Today I know THAT IS “LIFE“!

</影评>
<有用数>1</有用数>
<没用数>0</没用数>
</review>
<review>
<作者>LION.</作者>
<作者评分>5</作者评分>
<时间>2021-03-26 20:38:01</时间>
<影评>

最近爱上了卓别林的默剧，全剧没有声音，但是他的动作、表情丰富，淋漓尽致的表现出了情境，让人开怀大笑。卓别林短篇精选有三部短剧《狗的生活》《从军记》《朝圣者》。
生活在社会底端的卓别林，为了保护一只小狗的粮食，将它从恶狗堆中救出，为了不让卖酒女失去工作，有钱后第一件事就是返回酒吧与她共享，尽管找工作的时候因为矮小受尽不公他仍温暖待人，最后坐拥美人和一窝可爱的狗狗，人生赢家。
在一战时期参军，环境恶劣，在水中睡觉，战友们收到家里的慰问时他什么也没有，看着别人阅读家中来信时一起笑了，挺心疼，他没有家人关心了。勇争上前线，用自己的小机灵和巧妙掩护打入敌军内部解救战友，立下战功，途中还收获了美人一个，最后战争结束，世界和平。
剧情设定被通缉的卓别林莫名其妙来到一个地方被当做新来的牧师，寄宿在女主家里，展开了一系列的误会。在传道的那段中，还表起演来了哈哈哈，下面的人是一脸蒙圈，蛋糕又被熊孩子换成了帽子，演绎出滑稽可爱的样子。百般阻挠他的狱友偷钱，帮寄宿主人找回钱财，不惜被当做惯犯抓起来，所幸警长是个好人，放他流落墨西哥。
每个小故事都展现了卓别林善良的一面，小小的人物，发散出来的光芒无人可挡，照耀在我们心上，没有台词照样描绘得栩栩如生，让观众完全进入到情境中，让人捧腹大笑。

</影评>
<有用数>1</有用数>
<没用数>0</没用数>
</review>
</reviews>
</movie>
